<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A nevv eight-fold probation of the Church of Englands divine constitution prooved by many pregnant arguments, to be much more complete then any Geneuian in the world against the contrary assertion of the fifty three petitioner-preachers of Scotland in their petition presented in the later Parliament to the Kings most excellent Maiesty. With a ten-folde probation of the same churches doctrine touching one of the most important points of our creede, which is of our sauiours descending into Hell. By Iames Maxvvell. Master of Artes, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Maxwell, James, b. 1581.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 263 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07316</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17704</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103373</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839129</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839129</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3528</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07316)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3528)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1247:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A nevv eight-fold probation of the Church of Englands divine constitution prooved by many pregnant arguments, to be much more complete then any Geneuian in the world against the contrary assertion of the fifty three petitioner-preachers of Scotland in their petition presented in the later Parliament to the Kings most excellent Maiesty. With a ten-folde probation of the same churches doctrine touching one of the most important points of our creede, which is of our sauiours descending into Hell. By Iames Maxvvell. Master of Artes, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Maxwell, James, b. 1581.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 74, [2], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legatt, printer to the Vniversitie of Cambridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In two parts.</note>
                  <note>Part 2 has separate title page, "A demonstrative defence or tenfold probation of the doctrine of the Church of England touching one of the most important points of our creed", and separate pagination; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3528:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NEVV EIGHT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FOLD PROBATION OF THE CHVRCH OF ENGLANDS DIVINE CONSTITV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION, PROOVED BY MANY PREG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant arguments, to be much more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete then any Geneuian in the world <hi>againſt the contrary aſſertion of the fifty</hi> three petitioner-preachers of Scotland <hi>in their petition preſented in the</hi> late Parliament to the Kings <hi>moſt excellent Maieſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a ten-folde probation of the ſame Churches doctrine touching one of the moſt important points of our Creede, which is of our Sauiours deſcending into Hell,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> IAMES MAXVVELL Maſter of Artes, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by IOHN LEGATT, Printer to the Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of Cambridge. 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:3528:2"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 122. verſe 6.</hi>
               </bibl> Pray for the peace of Ieruſalem, let them proſper that loue thee.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſay 41.8, 9, 25.</hi>
               </bibl> Thou <hi>Iacob,</hi> whom I haue choſen, I haue taken thee from the endes of the earth, and called thee before the cheife thereof, and ſaid vnto thee, thou art my Seruant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I haue raiſed vp from the North, and he ſhall come: from the Eaſt Sunne ſhall he call vpon my Name.</q>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3528:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST LEARNED, RELI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GIOVS AND RENOWNED PRINCE IAMES the Concorder, <hi>King of Britaine, France, and Ireland,</hi> defender of the faith, all felicitie.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt gratious and redoubted Soueraigne.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>NEVER read thoſe words of the Euangelicall Prophet prefixt in the former page; (and I haue read them often;) but as oft did I thinke of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Gods raiſing of you our <hi>Iacob</hi> from the North, and endes of the earth, to performe the part of his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect Seruant for the especiall good of his Church: and euen, ſo oft did I call to minde your gratious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours for the farthering of the glorious worke of Vnitie and Concord amongſt diuided Chriſtians: but more especially, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your Royall and proper intereſt, among your owne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vniformed Britaines. Wherefore perſwading my ſelfe, that it is both the duty of all good Chriſtians to applaude your mest Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian &amp; Commendable endeauours and deſignes; and the part of all your good ſubiects to concurre with your Maiestie in ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy a worke, for the aduancing thereof; I haue brought vnto the
<pb facs="tcp:3528:3"/>building of this ſpirituall Temple of Concord and Peace, two ſtones, to wit two Treatiſes penned and framed to the common peoples capacitie. Such as they are, I doe humbly exhibite both heere together into your Royall hands, to dispoſe of according to your moſt gratious and wiſe pleaſure, and as ye ſhall thinke good for them; for whoſe good they are intended. The firſt Treatiſe, containeth an eightfold probation of the diuine and perfit conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Church of England, the which I doe demonſtrate to be much more complete then any <hi>Genenian</hi> forme whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer in the world, for a moderate, quiet and calme refutation of a certaine contrary aſſertion contained in the three and fifty prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of Scotlands petition preſented vnto your Maieſtie in the late Parliament. And though there were many reaſons; which might induce me to dedicate the ſame vnto your Royall Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie; yet nothing mooued me ſo much thereunto, as that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration which I doe vſe, is drawen out of the diuine Booke of the <hi>Reuelation</hi> of <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> the diuine; the which I may in a manner call the Booke of King <hi>Iames</hi> the diuine, a demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration that no writer hath vſed, before me ſo farre as I know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for I ſuppoſe, that no diuine will or can denie; but that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Booke of the <hi>Reuelation</hi> is contained a repreſentation both of the Church Triumphant in Heauen by ſuch externall or ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſignes or ſhowes, as were moſt fit to repreſent the ſame by; and likewiſe of the Church militant on earth, ſuch as it was to bee after our Sauiours aſcenſien in the two times of perſecution and peace, aye vntill the laſt period of his glorious comming to iudgement. For as the beloued and diuine man of God <hi>Moſes,</hi> made the Tabernacle according to the patterne or modele ſhewed him in the mount; as the Scripture ſpeaketh; ſo our Sauiour Chriſts beloued and diuine diſciple <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> repreſenteth vnto vs the forme and faſhion of the militant Church, according to the patterne of the Triumphant, ſhewed vnto him by reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Ile of <hi>Pathmos.</hi> So that (in the opinion of all diuines) amongſt the many particular Churches, that are on earth, that which is likest vnto the Church in heauen, muſt needs bee the
<pb facs="tcp:3528:3"/>diuinest and beſt; and that ſo much the more becauſe that our Sauiour himſelfe hath taught vs to pray and ſay daily, thy will be done in earth, as it is in heauen. Now that the Church of England doth more neerely reſemble the heauenly Church, then the Geneuian doth; I make it apparant by eight pregnant proofes, and irrefragable arguments; founded and grounded all of them in Gods written word, especially in the foreſaid diuine booke of <hi>Saint Iohns</hi> Reuelation. <hi>1.</hi> in that the Church of England is more diuine, or God-like then the <hi>Geneuian,</hi> in her ſupreame Gouerner on earth, the Prince. <hi>2.</hi> in that ſhee is more Angelicall, or Angel-like in her ſecondary Gouernours of Archbiſhops and Biſhops. <hi>3.</hi> more celeſtiall or heauen-like for holineſſe. <hi>4.</hi> more heauen like for humble reuerence. <hi>5.</hi> more heauen-like for harmonie. <hi>6.</hi> more heauen-like for habite. <hi>7.</hi> more heauen-like for locall decencie, Church-implements conueniency, Church-ſeruice ſolemnity, and ſacramentall ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. <hi>8.</hi> and laſtly, more heauen-like for honour of the miniſtery. In the handling of which eight arguments, I doe demonstrate the lawfulneſſe, vtility, and conueniencie of the chiefe rites vſed in the Church of England, as namely of holy dayes, of ſtanding vp at the reading of the Goſpel, of kneeling at the rehearſall of the Law, and in receiuing the holy Sacrament, of Church<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke conſiſting of ſong and Organs, of the Church habite of Surplice and Rotchet, of the comely Structure and ornaments of Churches, of hauing a Font with a ſtanding Table for the celebration of the Sacraments, and of ſigning with the croſſe in Baptiſme; for the which I doe produce thirteene arguments all grounded in Gods word. I doe likewiſe iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the title of <hi>Prieſt</hi> giuen to the inferiours of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, and of <hi>Lord</hi> giuen to the ſuperiours by diuers good reaſons: and by thirteene arguments I prooue the lawfulnes and equity of paying tithes to the miniſters vnder the Goſpel, adding thereunto an Invectiue againſt the Genevian or Puritane impure ſinne of ſacriledge. And in handling the firſt of the eight branches of this our new demonſtration, which is, that the
<pb facs="tcp:3528:4"/>Church of England is more diuine or God-like then the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uian</hi> in her ſupreme Gouernour on earth; I do procue theſe ſixe important points after following, moſt part againſt the common contrary opinions of Romanes and Geneuians; firſt that the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly power is immediatly from God, and not from man, by eight Teſtimonies of Scripture and three arguments. Secondly that the kingly dignitie is abſolutely greater then the prieſtly, and of all other the diuineſt, by eight arguments. Thirdly that chriſtian kings are not meere lay-men, but of a mixt condition partly, ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall and partly ſecular, by ten ſacred examples and three arguments. Fourthly that kings are lawgiuers vnto their people, and haue power of God to make lawes for the good both of church and common-wealth, by ſixe arguments. Fifthly that kings are to be honourably and magnificently maintained, and that God hath allotted them a certaine competent portion of their ſubiects goods Sixtly, and lastly, that Kings are endowed with a ſacred immunity from all manner of coercion and cenſure ſpirituall or temporall at their ſubiects hands. The which thing I procue against Romanes and Geneuians by ſeuenteene arguments, And this is the ſumme of the first Booke which I moſt humbly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vnto your maieſties patronage; the other beeing onely a briefe of a certaine part of a larger worke, I haue begun in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, containeth a ten-fold probation of the doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> touching our Sauicurs locall deſcending in his ſoule after death into the hell of the damned, against the different and repugnant dostrines of Genenians and Romanes the which I do dedicate vnto the Reuerend prelats and paſtors of the Church of Scotland. The verity of which doctrin I do ſhow &amp; confirme <hi>1.</hi> by Typical prefiguration both perſonall and real, <hi>2.</hi> by propheticall praediction. <hi>3.</hi> by holy Scriptures pregnant hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall alluſion. <hi>4.</hi> by Euangelicall aſſeueration, <hi>5.</hi> by apostolical explication, <hi>6</hi> by all chriſtians catholicall confeſſion, <hi>7,</hi> by three &amp; fortie ancient doctors and fathers vnanime and harmonious profeſſion, beſides ſome ſixe or ſeauen Councels. <hi>8.</hi> by thirtie chiefe protestant writers ingenuous reception and ſubſcription,
<pb facs="tcp:3528:4"/>beſides ſome particular reformed Churches. <hi>9.</hi> by irrefragable reaſon and demonſtration. <hi>10.</hi> and laſtly, by the conſideration of the diuers groſſe abſurdities, impieties, contradictions, and ridiculous expoſitions that they haue committed, which haue op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned this auncient doctrine of the Church of England or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented from the ſame. And here I will likewiſe profeſſe pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely, that in caſe our preciſe Diuines can but ſhew as great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety, and as good ſolidity of arguments and reaſons, euen for all their opinions ioyned together, wherein they do diſſent from the Church of England, as I ſhall ſhew for this one point onely, that I ſhall not be aſhamed to retract my preſent opinions, wherein I doe diſſent from them, and ſubſcribe vnto theirs, and ſo become as preciſe, as euer I was knowne to bee once before. And thus haue I briefly laid open vnto your Maiestie the ſumme and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of theſe two little bookes, which I haue written of late for the furthering of a perfit vniformity both in doctrine and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline in the Churches of theſe two Kingdomes; and euen for the perſwading and enducing of my deere Countrey men to the reception of the auncient primitiue forme of Church, ſuch as it was in the dayes of glorious <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, and during the purer time of the first fiue hundreth yeares; which is one of your Maiesties most christian and commendable deſires and deſignes, worthy of the memorie and celebration of all ſucceding ages, the which, I pray the God of vnity and veritie that yee may as happily atchieue, as yee doe holily wiſh it and worthily haue begunst. That ſo the Church of Scotland may in your Maieſties bleſſed time receiue the conſummation and accompliſhment of her reformation from England, like as from her, ſhee had the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choation or beginning thereof, as our owne historie, doth witneſſe: and that as the ſaid Church hath already receiued of England their Engliſh Bible and Pſalme-Booke, ſo may ſhe now likewiſe receiue her Liturgie or Seruice-booke with the whole rites and orders contained therein. And though I be haply the first of my Countrey that euer wrote thus earnestly in defence of the Church of England; yet let not my deere Countrey-men, (vnto
<pb facs="tcp:3528:5"/>whom God is my witneſſe, I doe dayly wiſh all manner of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) thinke that I haue done it out of any worldly reſpect to priuate profite, benefit or benefice either already confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or hereafter to be confered vpon me; by Prince or Prelate, but out of a meere affection to verity and vnity &amp; to the pure primitiue Church. The truth of which my protestation may hence appeare in part, in that theſe ten yeere past that I haue liued in England, I was at no time a Suter vnto your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie nor yet beholding to any Biſhop, nor euer aimed at any benefice; as being at this houre and intending to continue euer hereafter a Lay-man; notwithſtanding that the learned and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Deane of Exeter, Doctor Sutcliffe, the nominated Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoſt of that begunne Controuerſial Colledge, which beareth your Maiesties name, hath choſen me to be a fellow and an Antiqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry therof. So that my deere countrymen ſhal haue no cauſe I hope to charge me with any preposterous affection or flattering hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor in the behalfe of England; ſeeing that I haue no purpoſe of aſpiring to Church preferment amongſt them, who haue worthie Schollers enough of their owne and most complete Preachers to brooke their Benefices. Neither ſhal the learned ministery of my country take it euill, that a lay-man ſhould thus meddle in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical matters, if it ſhal pleaſe them to conſider, how that a lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man may with greateringenuity &amp; indifferencie handle ſuch an argument as this is, then a Church-man who might happely be ſuſpected offlatterie or fauour in the behalfe of one churches formemore then another, &amp; that meerely for loue of preferment, from the which kinde of ſuspicion, one of my faſhion is free. And as for capacitie requiſite in the handling of this argument, I am content, they ſhould haue no better opinion of me then the courſe of my life and stadies in their owne good iudgement may challeng at their hands: abreefe narration whereof, I thought good, by your Maiesties gracious leaue, here to inſert, not out of any humour of oſtentation, but onely that it may thereby appeare, that though I be a lay-man; yet I haue spent a good part of my time in the ſtudy of diuinitie, vnto the which, I was knowne at
<pb facs="tcp:3528:5"/>home, ſo much to haue addicted my ſelfe, that at the age of <hi>19.</hi> yeares, and euen before, I proceeded Maſter of Artes, I was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quested of ſome of our Miniſtery to preach by way of exerciſe: And though I did refuſe to condeſcend vnto their earnest deſire proceeding from their good opinion of me, for the which courſe I was not a little commended of that learned and renowned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine of good memorie, (Master <hi>Robert Rollock</hi>) who diſliked the vnripe forwardneſſe of ſome young spirits, howſoeuer other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of great towardneſſe; yet I ommitted not my priuate ſtudie of diuinttie, but followed the ſame aſſiduonſly, being thereunto en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by the the foreſaid Reuered Diuine, who had diuerted me from my intended voyaege into Denmarke, towards the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and noble Philoſopher and Astrologian <hi>Tycho Brahe,</hi> with whom I thought to haue proſecuted my begun Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall studies, and ſo perſwaded mee to finiſh my Academicall courſe in the learned Colledge of Edenburgh, before I went to trauaile. And there beeing past ſome ſeuenteene yeares ſince the time I proceeded Maſter of arts, &amp; went beyond ſea, which was in the yeare <hi>1601.</hi> I haue all this while giuen my minde wholly to good letters, and aſwell diuine as humane. For three yeares of the ſaid ſpace I spent in the priuate ſtudie of Philoſophy, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering of the more noble and choice queſtions, that haue beene mooued or disputed by the followers of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> but eſpecially of diuine <hi>Plato,</hi> vnto whom I was alwayes more deuoted, and of the renowned Aegyptian Philoſopher <hi>Hermes Triſmegiſtus;</hi> following therein the example of thoſe foure famous Italian Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, <hi>Franciſcus &amp; Ioannes Picus Mirandula, Marſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Ficinus, &amp; Franciſcus Patricius.</hi> Other three years I ſpent in reading and pondering the Church questions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies of our time, as they haue beene learnedly and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly debated on both hands, by diuers great Diuines of theſe dayes. One yeare I ſpent in peruſing ſome fourty treatiſes, diſcourſes, commentaries, and conſuitations written by ſome of the more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate and ingenuous, tending to pacification. Fiue yeares I ſpent in reading and peruſing ſome of the choicest bookes of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors
<pb facs="tcp:3528:6"/>of the Church, Greekes and Latines, and of the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned amongſt the Schoole-men, and other fiue I ſpent in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing politicall and hiſtoricall workes penned by diuers authors, eſpecially Italians and Germans: together with the Genealogies of the Kings and Princes of Chriſtendome. And for ſome clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer euidence and proofe of this ſtudious paſtime, beſides ſome ten little things already publiſhed in engliſh, most part vpon diuine and morall arguments, namely, the Looking glaſſe of grace and glory, the Treaſure of tranquillity, the Mirrour of religious men &amp; godly Matrons, the Golden art or the right way of enriching, the Game of concord and vnion, admirable Prophecies of <hi>24.</hi> famous Romane catholikes, touching the deformation and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Rome, two Pamphlets containing ſome ſeauen ſhort Poems in honour of your Maieſtie, and your noble children, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with theſe two preſent Treatiſes written of late in defence of the Church of Englands diſcipline and doctrine, beſides theſe ten little exerciſes, I ſay, I haue written diuers things in Latine vpon Philoſophicall, Hiſtoricall, and Politicall arguments, but moſt of all vpon Theologicall points: for being once a follower of the moſt preciſe ſort, and euen a profeſſed Puritane as they tearme it, I began at nineteene yeares of age, to write in Latine two bookes againſt Poperie; one of the which I haue entituled, <hi>of the admirable Antipathie or contrariety of Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie and Papalogie, or of Gods word and the Popes.</hi> Wherein I point forth the oppoſitions &amp; contradictions betweene the Scripture and the Romane doctrine, from the beginning of the Bible vnto the end thereof, going thorow euery chapter of both Teſtaments; anſwerable whereunto I haue deuided the ſaid worke into two parts, the firſt containing an hundred and fourty nine Sections, the ſecond an hundred and thirty: and it hath bin ſeene and well liked of ſome learned Schollers. The other is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Tyrannie which was to be exerciſed vpon the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litant Church, according to the tenure of the two noble propheſies of <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Saint Iohn;</hi> where I doe entreat of the authors, inſtruments, duration, beginning, manner and ending of thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:3528:6"/>great troubles: and doe compare the opinions of writers, together touching the foreſaid circumſtances with the reaſons thereof: a worke of no ſmall labour conſisting of eighteene large Sections or Chapters, and was by me dedicated vnto the Church and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> where I tooke my degree, and therefore I ſent it home out of <hi>France</hi> with my Cooſin <hi>M. William Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> of <hi>Kauens,</hi> to be preſented accordingly; though as I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood ſince, it was the fortune of my Booke, to fall into the hands of <hi>M. Iohn Welſhe,</hi> then a famous Preacher in thoſe parts; who borrowed the ſame for a few daies, but not deliuering it againe, carried the ſame away with him into <hi>France,</hi> and hath kept it vntill this houre. I haue likewiſe written in Latine ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Booke called <hi>Romaſe redarguens,</hi> or Rome rebuking and reproouing her ſelfe: Wherein I doe prooue by the expreſſe Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of Popes, Cardinals, Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Monkes, Friers, Prophets, Propheteſſes, Schoolemen, and Cell-women of the Church of Rome, that ſhee ſtandeth in need of reformation, againſt the contrary aſſertion of the learned Ieſuite <hi>Martinus Becanus.</hi> The Propheticall part, (if ſo I may call it,) of which worke, I did publiſh of late in Engliſh, a Booke containing a col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of more then an hundred ſtrange Propheſies vtteredin former times touching the deformation, and reformation of Rome, by twenty foure famous Romane-Catholikes, whereof ſome twelue haue beene canonized for Saints, to wit, ſeauen men, and fiue women. I haue likewiſe written a diſputation or diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition touching the ſeate of Sathan: whether it was to be in the North, as the Romiſh Doctors doe holde, or in the South, where I prooue againſt the Romane Doctors by Scripture and nature, by Theologie and Aſtrologie, by Philoſophie and Hiſtorie, how that the North is abſolutely the moſt diuine, eminent and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, the very ſeate of God, and not of Sathan, and the chiefe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle of his Church. Another disputation and diſquiſition I haue written touching the ſeate of ſoules, where I refute the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh opinions of Purgatory, <hi>Limbus Patrum, Limbus infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,</hi> and the like hollow habitations of ſoules within the earth,
<pb facs="tcp:3528:7"/>and I doe ſhow that the ancient Fathers, knewne more places but three at moſt, as the Greekes doe at this day; Paradiſe; Heauen and Hell. In the ſame I doe refute the erroneous opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Romanes and Geneuians, Papiſts and Puritanes touching our Sauiours deſcending into hell, and prooue the doctrine of the Church of England touching that article to be only orthodoxe; a briefe of which part of that Booke, I haue here publiſhed in Engliſh. And in the ſame larger worke, I do defend the ſaluation of <hi>Salomons</hi> ſoule againſt <hi>Cardinall Bellarmine,</hi> and others, iumping with him in that vnprobable and vncharitable opinion. Another disputation I haue written in Latine vpon the Inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Saints, againſt the Romane Knight of <hi>Saint Peter Gaſpar Scioppius,</hi> against whoſe allegations of Scripture, and probations fetcht from thence: I who am a layman like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, howſoeuer inferiour for humane letters and titles doe em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy ſome <hi>28.</hi> arguments fetcht not only from Scriptures, but alſo from Greeke and Latine Fathers, beſides Philoſophers, Poets, and Hiſtorians: and the ſame Methode and manner of probation, I doe vſe in a certaine Theologicall and Historicall Plea againſt the learned Ieſuite <hi>Iames Gretſer,</hi> for the prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence of the Emperour, and Kings aboue Popes, Patriarkes, Archbiſhops and Biſhops, and generally of all Priests, and for their mixt condition of Eccleſiasticall and ciuill. Lastly, I haue written a Treatiſe called <hi>Catholico-Iacobus, Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co. Britannus;</hi> wherein I do demonstrate the true Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſme of Britaines, and doe euidently prooue that your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and your ſubiects haue all thoſe things, that Gods word re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, to make men true Christians and Catholikes, againſt the contrary aſſertion of the learned French Archbiſhop, <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall Iames Perron.</hi> The which two Treatiſes laſt mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, written in defence of <hi>King Iames,</hi> and this Church, against two learned and famous Romane Catholikes of the name of <hi>Iames,</hi> by your Maiesties ſubiect and ſeruant of the ſame Name, ſhall be (God willing) ſhortly publiſhed for the first laïck fruits of that begunne Colledge, which beareth the name of
<pb facs="tcp:3528:7"/>
               <hi>King Iames,</hi> whereof I am to bee a <hi>Fellow.</hi> The which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes beeing conſidered, I hope the more eaſily to gaine the Church of Scotlands good opinion, and that they ſhall not charge me with incapacitie to handle ſuch a weighty argument as this, hauing written ſo much in matters belonging to Church and Religion. To be briefe, thus haue I ſpent theſe ſeuenteene yeares yeares of my priuate &amp; obſcure life, ſince I proceeded Maſter of Artes, and went beyond ſea, in giuing my ſelfe to ſtudie and contemplation, endeauouring to know much, and to contentation, in no wiſe coueting after much; and to Temperance and Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency, Whereof I take the all-knowing God and his chaste An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels to witnes. And now theſe my poore labours, ſuch as they are, I moſt humbly lay downe at your Royal feet, begging your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties moſt honourable patronage and acceptance, and in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the God of Vnitie and Veritie, to giue them a bleſſing for the furthering of your moſt Christian deſire, and glorious deſigne, ſo that we may euen in your owne happie daies, ſee with our eyes the full accompliſhment thereof, to the glorie of his name; the comfort of his Church, the good of great Britaine, and your Maiesties eternall honour. So prayeth daily</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>YOVR MAIESTIES Moſt humble ſubiect and ſeruant, and euen the grandchilde of your moſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Grandmothers and Mothers houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſeruant, <hi>William Maxwell</hi> ſonne to the Laird of <hi>Kirkonnell,</hi> and in his life man at armes to the moſt Chriſtian King IAMES MAXVVELL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:3528:8"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS OF THESE TWO BOOKES.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> THat Vnitie and Concord in matters belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to Gods Worſhip amongſt Chriſtians, eſpecially Proteſtants, and more eſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Britaines, both for reaſon of Church, and reaſon of State is to bee by all meanes deſired and endeauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <hi>Sect. 1.2.3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> That one Churches conſtitution is more perfit and complete then anothers, and that the leſſe perfit ought to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forme it ſelfe vnto the more perfit. <hi>Sect. 4.5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> That the conſtitution of the Church of England is much more perfit then an Geneuian whatſoeuer, or whereſoeuer. <hi>Sect. 6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> That the Church of England is more Diuine and God-like in the ſupreme Gouernor, the Soueraigne Prince then the Geneuian. <hi>Sect. 7.8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> That the Kingly power is immediately from God, and not from man as both Romanes and Geneuians doe hold, prooued by eight teſtimonies of Scripture and three irrefragable arguments. <hi>Sect. 9.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> That the kingly dignitie is abſolutely greater then the prieſtly, and of all other the diuineſt, contrary to the opinion of Romanes and Geneuians, prooued by eight arguments. <hi>Sect. 10.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> That Kings are not meere lay-men, but mixt of an eccleſiaſticall and ſecular condition, contrary to the opinion of Romanes &amp; Geneuians, prooued by three ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, &amp; ten examples of Kings that haue exerciſed ſpirituall power for the good of the Church. <hi>Sect. 11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3528:8"/>
                  <hi>8.</hi> That Kings are Law-giuers to their people, and haue power of God to make lawes for the good both of Church and Common-weale, prooued by ſixe arguments. <hi>Sect. 12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> That Kings are to be honourable and magnificently maintained, and that God hath allotted them a certaine portion of their ſubiects goods. <hi>Sect. 13.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> That Kings are indued with a Sacred immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie from all manner of coercion, and cenſure ſpirituall or temporall at their ſubiects hands, prooued againſt Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes and Geneuians by <hi>17.</hi> arguments. <hi>Sect. 14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11.</hi> That the Church of England is more Angelicall or Angel-like in her ſecondary Gouernours of Archbiſhops and Biſhops. <hi>Sect. 15.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12.</hi> That their is an imparitie or inequalitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Gods Miniſters in the Church triumphant in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and that their hath beene alwaies the like imparitie in the Church militant on earth, firſt vnder the Law, then vnder the Goſpel; and aſwell in the time of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, as of their ſucceſſours. <hi>Sect. 15.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13.</hi> That the Church of England is more heauen-like for holineſſe, where the conueniency of holydaies beſides the Sunday, is prooued and demonſtrated by vnanſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able arguments. <hi>Sect. 16.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14.</hi> That the Church of England is more heauen-like then the Geneuian for humble reuerence, where the conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencie of the geſtures of ſtanding vp at the reading of the Goſpel, capping or bowing at the name of Ieſus, of kneeling at the rehearſing of the Law, and eſpecially at the receiuing of the holy Sacrament is declared and prooued. <hi>Sect. 17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15.</hi> That the Church of England is more heauen-like then the Geneuian, for harmonie, where the conueniency of Church-muſicke conſiſting of voices and organes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtruments is declared. <hi>Sect. 18.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3528:9"/>
                  <hi>16</hi> That the Church of England is more heauen-like then the Geneuian for habite, where the conueniencie and decencie of Church-habites, as of the Surpliſſe and Rotchet is prooued. <hi>Sect. 19.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17.</hi> That the Church of England is more Heauen-like then the Geneuian, for locall decencie, Church-implements conueniency, Church-ſeruice ſolemnitie, and ſacrament all ceremony; where the conueniencie of a Font or the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of Baptiſme, and of a ſtanding Table for the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the Lords Supper is declared, and the vſe of the ceremonie of the ſigne of the Croſſe in Baptiſme prooued moſt lawful and commendable by <hi>13.</hi> arguments. <hi>Sec. 20.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18.</hi> That the Church of England is more heauen-like then the Geneuian for honour of the Miniſterie, where the lawfulneſſe of the ſtile of Prieſt amongſt the Miniſters of the Goſpel, and likewiſe of the ſtile of Lord, conferred on the reuerend Gonernours of the Church is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the Geneuian-church gouernors of Lay-elders prooued to be a thing vnlawfull and abſurd. <hi>Sect. 21.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19.</hi> That the maintenance of the Miniſterie is more diuine, heauen-like and honourable in the church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, then in the Geneuian, where the perpetuall mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Tithes is prooued, and the Geneuian ſinne of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge exagitated and ſhewed to be more hainous then heatheniſh Idolatrie. <hi>Sect. 21.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20.</hi> The diuerſitie and repugnancie of the opinions of diuines touching our Sauiours deſcending into hell, breif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly propounded. <hi>Tract. 2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>21.</hi> The doctrine of the church of England touching the foreſaid point demonſtrated to be only orthodoxall by a Ten-folde probation. <hi>Tract. 2.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3528:9"/>
                  <head>A Primitiue patterne for the Church of Scotland.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 1.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nitie and Concord amongſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, eſpecially amongſt Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants or reformed profeſſours, but more eſpecially amongſt Britaines,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 133.1, 2, 3. Ioh. 17, 20, 21, 22, 23. 1. Pet. 3.8. Heb. 12.14.</note> as they that are the worſhippers of one and the ſame true God, the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of one and the ſame only Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt, the children of one Church, and the ſubiects of one and the ſame Soueraigne, is in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all them that are truely wiſe, of all other things moſt to bee deſired and endeauoured, as a thing moſt pleaſing to God, and moſt profitable to man.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</head>
                     <p>Vnitie and Concord is to bee deſired and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured in all things, but eſpecially in thoſe things,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 122.6. Rom. 15.6. 1. Cor. 1.10, 11, &amp; 3, 3, 4. Eph. 4.3, 4, 5 Phil. 3.16.</note> that concerne Gods worſhip, the ſaluation of mens ſoules, and the good conſtitution of the Church: becauſe by the meanes and occaſion of diſcord and diſſention, ſuch as be without, are ſcandalized, and ſtill kept out of the Church; and thoſe that are within, are ſo pittifully diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that either they are driuen out of the Church, or if they ſtay ſtill in it, they prooue no better then dull or dead members of the Church, (much like the parts of a blaſted body,) for lacke of true deuotion and ſpirituall life. For whileſt wee contend about veritie, wee looſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3528:10"/>vnitie, and ſtriuing about the ſhaddowes of ceremonie and circumſtance, we ſlip from the body and ſubſtance; opinion oppreſſeth pietie, faction vndermineth faith, controuerſie quelleth charitie, and reaſoning rooteth vp religion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</head>
                     <p>The procuring, furthering and preſeruing of Vnitie and Concord in the Church appertaineth principally vnto the Chriſtian Prince,
<note place="margin">Iſay 49.23. Exod. 4.16. &amp; 22.8. Pſal. 82.1.6. Ioh. 10.34, 35 Math. 5.9. 2. Tim. 2.24, 25.</note> whom God hath called to be a nurſing-father vnto his Church, and hath honoured moſt highly, with the ſtile of the Son of the moſt high, and euen of a God, to put him in minde of his care and ſtudie for the things of God, and the good of his Church which principally conſiſteth in the Vnitie thereof, and next it appertaineth vnto the Paſtors, who are to ioyne with the Prince in this glorious worke; whom of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it becommeth leaſt to be men of ſtrife and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or inſtruments of diſcord and diuiſion, ſeeing that the God of peace hath called them to bee Meſſengers and makers of peace and Vnion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</head>
                     <p>Amongſt the many particular Churches that are at this day diuided from themſelues, one from another, whether in doctrine or diſcipline, in ſubſtance or circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, there is a difference in perfection; and I thinke no man doubteth of it, but that one Church may be of a more perfit and complete conſtitution, then another Church: yea we are ſo farre from doubting any thing of this point, that euery profeſſour holdeth the Church that he is off to be the more perfit then that which hee diſclaimeth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 5.</head>
                     <p>It beeing moſt certaine that the particular diuided Churches are not alike perfit; it ſtandeth the leſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit in hand to conforme it ſelfe vnto that which ſhall by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3528:10"/>the light of Gods word and good reaſon appeare to bee more perfit; both becauſe our Sauiour Chriſt comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all Chriſtians to aſpire vnto perfection, ſaying,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.48. Phil. 3.15.16 Coloſſ. 1.28. Heb. 6.1.</note> 
                        <hi>Bee ye therefore perfit, as your Father which is in heauen, is perfit,</hi> and the Apoſtle exhorteth all men to bee led forward to perfection, and becauſe that this is the only way to knit vp the Churches in Concord and Vnitie, and to draw them to an vniformitie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 6.</head>
                     <p>Amongſt the particular reformed Churches: that of England is more perfit and complete in many reſpects then any Church reformed after the faſhion of <hi>Geneua,</hi> contrary to the petitioners aſſertion, and namely, then that of Scotland, whoſe forme and conſtitution was meerely <hi>Geneuian,</hi> before that our ſacred Soueraigne di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinely enſpired began the ſecond reformation thereof, tending to the conformation of it with England, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Primitiue, whereunto it is much more like then the other.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 7.</head>
                     <p>The perfection of the engliſh Church is apparent whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we compare her with the Church of God, and the bleſſed Spirits in heauen, or with the Church of God &amp; beleeuing men on earth, before Chriſts time, in his time, or after his time: or whether we reſpect the warrant and authoritie of Gods word or mans, of diuinitie or huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, of Scripture or nature, of religion or reaſon; or whether wee reſpect her eſſentiall perfections and parts for piety or charity, faith or repentance, deuotion or reuerence, illumination or ſanctification, doctrine or diſcipline, ſubſtance or circumſtance, ſeruice or ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, order or decency, the honour and dignity of Prince or of Paſtors, with the edification and conſolation of the whole people.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="section">
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3528:11"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 8.</head>
                     <p>Conſidering that the pregnanteſt proofe that can be brought of a particular Churches perfection,
<note place="margin">The Church of England more diuine and God-like then the Geneuian.</note> and painting out as it were to the life, the analogie and affinitie, likeneſſe or reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance, that it hath with that Church which is knowne to bee abſolutely the moſt diuine, compleate, and perfit. I ſhall therefore prooue in this preſent diſcourſe by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places of Scripture, eſpecially of that moſt diuine part of it called the Reuelation of <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> the diuine, that the Church of England is much more diuine, and farre liker the Church of God in heauen, then any <hi>Geneuian</hi> Church is, and therefore much more perfit, contrary to to the Petitionerslate aſſertion. For ſeeing that as oft as in praying the Lords prayer we ſay,
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.9.10.</note> 
                        <hi>thy will bee done in earth as it is in heauen,</hi> wee doe deſire of God with all our hearts, that his Church on earth militant, may bee euery day more and more conformable and like vnto his Church in heauen triumphant, which wee beleeue and confeſſe to be the moſt perfit; it muſt needs follow that the more conforme a Church on earth bee vnto the Church in heauen, the more it findeth and feeleth the efficacie and force of our Lords prayer, and the neerer that it doth reſemble the Church in heauen, the perfiter muſt it be: for that thing is the more perfit, which is the more like vnto the moſt perfit. And that the Church of England is much liker the Church that is aboue, then the Geneuian is, it may appeare by comparing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of the two Churches together. And firſt I ſay that the Church of England is liker vnto Gods Church in heauen, then any other Church Geneuian or Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, as beeing more diuine and God-like in reſpect of the ſupreme Gouernour. For like as the Soueraigne go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of the Church in heauen conſiſting of thoſe bleſſed Spirits which <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> ſaw almoſt beyond
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3528:11"/>number in the preſence of the throne of God ſeruing him day and night in his Temple,
<note place="margin">Ruele. 4, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. &amp; 5.8, 9, 10, 11, 14. &amp; 7.9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15 &amp; 19.1. &amp; 21.1, 2, 3. Exod. 15.18. 1. Sam. 8.7. Pſal. 2.6. &amp; 30 9, &amp; 22.28. &amp; 24.7, 8, 9, 10. &amp; 29.10. Gen. 2.20. Exod. 3.1, 2, 3 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. &amp; 4.16. &amp; 7.1. &amp; 22.28. Pſal. 82.1.6, &amp; 95.3. &amp; 50.1.</note> is ſuch a one as is both God and King: ſo the Soueraigne Gouernour of the Church of England is ſuch a one, as is both a King and a God on earth: for in the holy Scripture wee know that Kings are called Gods, as God himſelfe is called a King. And euen God himſelf hath called Kings by this name, &amp; not any creature: for <hi>Adam</hi> gaue al other things their names, but could not giue this: for none but God can giue this name. Thou ſhalt be to <hi>Aaron</hi> as God (ſaid the Lord to <hi>Moſes</hi>) whom he had made a ſoueraigne Prince ouer his people. And againe, I haue made thee a God to <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> calleth the ſoueraigne Iudges by the name of Gods, ſaying, thou ſhalt not rayle vpon the Gods, for ſo it is in the originall, and the Pſalmiſt to the ſame purpoſe (ſpeakes thus) God ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth in the aſſembly of Gods, he iudgeth among Gods: and againe, he brings in the great God ſpeaking thus of his little Gods, I haue ſaid ye are Gods, &amp; yee are all children of the moſt high.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 9.</head>
                     <p>In that Kings are called Gods,
<note place="margin">That the Kingly dignitie is immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from God.</note> wee learne ſixe notable leſſons hereafter following, The firſt, that the kingly power is immediately of and from God, and not of man, as both Geneuians and Romanes moſt erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſly doe hold: for none can make of a man a God on earth, but God in heauen, neither is it in the power of man to make one Gods ſeruant or miniſter, but we muſt leaue it vnto God himſelfe to chooſe and ordaine his owne ſeruants. And truely if the King were ordained of man as he is for the good of man, (and therefore is by <hi>Saint Peter</hi> called an ordinance of man) the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> would neuer haue named him Gods ſeruant and miniſter, but mans.
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.13. Rom. 13.4.1. Chron, 29.23.</note> The King ſitteth in the Lords throne, (ſaith the holy Chronicler) now it belongeth not vnto man to ſet another man in Gods ſeate, but muſt let this alone for God himſelfe to doe. The throne
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3528:12"/>is Gods and not mans,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 21.3.1. Sam. 9.15, 16, 17, &amp; 10, 1, 24, &amp; 13, 13, 14, &amp; 16, 1, 2. 1. King. 3.7. &amp; 10.9. 1, Chr, 29, 29 2, Chro, 2.11 Nehe 13, 26. Dan. 4.14.23. Prouerbs 8.15.16. Wiſd. 6.1, 2.3. Rom. 13.1, 4.</note> and he that ſitteth in it is Gods miniſter and not mans, yea he is of God, called God, for man cannot make a man God, and therefore Kings are immediately from God, and not from man, an argument that all the Geneuians and Romanes in the world, ſhall neuer be able to anſwer. And therefore to ſhut vp this firſt leſſon (for in our worke of kingly controuerſies, we diſputeit more largely and accurately) three Kings, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, Salomor, Hiram,</hi> one Queene of <hi>Sheba,</hi> one Prince, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah,</hi> one high Prieſt <hi>Samuel,</hi> one chiefe Prophet <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> one principall Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> yea Gods Angel and God himſelfe doe all of them anouch that kings are choſen of God, nominated, ſent, crowned, created and ſet in Gods throne by God himſelfe, and not by man.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 9.</head>
                     <p>The ſecond leſſon that wee learne here is that the kingly dignitie is of all other dignities abſolutely the greateſt and the diuineſt,
<note place="margin">That the kingly digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Reuel. 2. &amp; 3. Pſal. 82.6. Dan. 3.26, &amp; 6.20. Ioh. 15.14, 15.</note> and not the prieſtly, as both Romane &amp; Geneuians do erroniouſly ſuppoſe. For firſt as none can be greater in heauen then the God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, or ſo great: ſo none in earth can be greater then he, who is called of God to be a God on earth, nor none can beſo great. Secondly, as the higheſt ſtile that can bee giuen to any, is giuen to Kings, ſo a lower ſtile is giuen to Prelates and Prieſts, for they are in the Scripture no where called Gods, but well are they named Angels, ſo that as the Angels in heauen are inferiour to the God of heauen, ſo are the Angels on earth, to wit, the chiefe Prieſts and Prelates inferiour vnto the Gods on earth; which are Soueraigne Princes: thirdly, Princes are called the children of the moſt high, where as Church-men are inſtiled onely the ſeruants and friends of the moſt high.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 21.3. 1. Chron. 29.23.</note> Fourthly, God putteth a crowne of golde vpon the Kings head, and he ſetteth him in his owne throne to ſit there for God as God; ſo that as the Apoſtle (ſpeaking of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3528:12"/>the inferioritie of the Angels of heauen beeing compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with Chriſt the annointed of the Lord) ſaith, vnto which of the Angels ſaid he at any time,
<note place="margin">Heb. 1.13.14.</note> ſit at my right hand till I make thine enemies thy footſtoole, are they not all miniſtring Spirits, ſent forth to miniſter for their ſakes, which ſhall be heires of ſaluation? In like manner may it be ſaid in this matter, touching the inferioritie of the Angels on earth, that is prelates, beeing compared with the Lords Chriſt and annointed one, the Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Prince, vnto which of the Angels on earth (for Prelates are called Angels in the <hi>Reuelation</hi> ſeauen or eight times) ſaid the Lord euer, ſit in my throne,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 1.20. &amp; 2.1.8, 12, 18, &amp; 3, 1, 7, 14.</note> as hee ſaith vnto Kings? yea I haue ſought much in reading and could neuer finde in old Teſtament, or new, in Scripture or Father Greeke or Latine, that euer the Lord ſaid, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately or mediately vnto the great Archangel him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that ſitteth in <hi>S. Angel,</hi> ſit thou in my throne; for no man taketh, or at leaſt ſhould take this honor vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but he that is called of God, as was <hi>Dauid,</hi> or <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi> What are the angels on earth elſe then, but as mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring ſpirits ſent forth by the Gods on earth,
<note place="margin">2. Chro. 17, 7, 8, 9. Exod, 32.21.22. Numb. 12, 11 1. King, 1.33, 34. 2, Chton, 29, 11. Exod. 5.1, 4, 20, &amp;, 1, 6.8, 20. &amp;, 10, 20. &amp; 9, 8, &amp; 10, 3, &amp;. 11, 10, &amp; 12, 1. Pſal, 77, 20. 2, Chron, 24, 12, 13, 14, &amp;, 31, 13.</note> the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>Ichoſophats,</hi> to teach in Iuda through al the Cities of their kingdomes to miniſter the holy Sacraments to them that ſhal be heires of Saluation, &amp; to gouerne the Church. Fiftly, the high prieſt <hi>Aaron</hi> calleth the Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Prince <hi>Moſes</hi> his Lord: and Salomon a king is called <hi>Zadoks</hi> the high Prieſt Lord, Ezekiah a king cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the prieſts his ſons: which doth argue the ſuperiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and maieſtie of kings, for the Lord is ſuperior to his ſeruant, and the Sonne inferiour to his father. Sixtly, the Spirit of God euery where placeth Kings before the chiefe Prieſts; <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> the King and <hi>Iehoiada, Ezekiab</hi> the King and <hi>Azariah</hi> the chiefe of the houſe of God, and preferreth the Princely dignitie before the prieſtly where they meete in one and the ſame perſon.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3528:13"/>
                        <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Geneſis,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Gen. 14, 18, Heb. 7, 1, Exod 19.6, 1. Pet. 2.9, Reuel. 1.6, &amp;, 4.10.</note> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> doe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue this order in <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> whome they name a King and a Prieſt. The ſame <hi>Moſes</hi> or rather the Lord himſelfe calleth his people a kingdome of Prieſts or a royall Prieſthoode, as ſpeaketh Saint <hi>Peter;</hi> and Saint, <hi>Iohn</hi> in the Reauelation hath theſe words, and made vs Kings and Prieſts vnto God, and the ſame words are vſed of the foure and twenty Elders. Seuenth ly,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 2, 6, &amp;, 20, 9, &amp; 24, 7, 8, 9, 10, &amp; 29, 10, &amp; 95, 3, &amp; 98, 6, Eſther 13, 9, 15, &amp;, 14, 3, 12. Reuel. 1.5, &amp;, 15, 3, &amp; 17, 14, &amp; 19, 16, 1. Tim. 6, 15. Mat. 28, 18, 1. Cor, 15, 25 26, 27. Philip. 2, 8, 9, 10, 11, Heb, 2, 7, 8, 9 10, 17, 18. Reuela. 1.5. &amp; 19.16.</note> the greateſt glory and dignitie in heauen is the Kingly and the higheſt title or ſtile, that is giuen to God in the old Teſtament, or to our Sauiour Chriſt in the new, is to be called a King, a King of glory, a King for euer, a great King aboue all Gods, the King almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, a king of Gods, the Prince of the Kings of the earth, the Lord of Lords, the king of Saints, and King of Kings, and thus is he called foure times in the booke of the diuine Reuelation, which is queſtionles the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and higheſt ſtile, that Chriſt hath, and by many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees greater and higher, then his prieſtly ſtile of high prieſt after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech:</hi> for this ſtile hee had on earth in the ſtate of his humility, wheras he was not an actual king, vntill he roſe, aſcended into heauen, and receiued all power in heauen and earth, as the Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne King of both, at the hands of his Father, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as both Goſpell and Epiſtle do teſtifie. Wherefore alſo the kingly dignitie is the greateſt on earth, and ſuch as do repreſent Chriſt in his kingly dignitie as Chriſtian kings doe, are greater and more eminent then thoſe that repreſent him in his Prieſtly dignitie;
<note place="margin">Mat. 22, 23, Dan, 2, 34, 45. 1. Pet. 2.17.</note> that is then Prieſts, Biſhops Archbiſhops, or Patriarkes. Eight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and laſtly, the honour of the king is commanded next vnto the honour of Godin holy Scripture, Giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God the things which are Gods, and giue vnto <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things which are <hi>Caſurs,</hi> ſaith our great <hi>Caeſar,</hi> who as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaketh; is the <hi>Stone,</hi> that was without hand,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3528:13"/>
                        <hi>cut</hi> of the <hi>mountaine,</hi> of the bleſſed Virgine <hi>Mary,</hi> and euen the corner <hi>stone</hi> of the Church. <hi>Feare God, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the King,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Peter</hi> another <hi>ſtone,</hi> yea,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.42, Galat. 2, 9. Pſal. 118, 22, Iſay. 28, 16. Mat. 21.42. Mark. 12, 10. Luk. 20.17. Act. 4.11. Rom. 9.33, 1. Pet. 2, 7. Ioh. 1.42, Galat. 2.9,</note> a <hi>pillar</hi> and chiefe ſtone of the Church, whome I wiſh the Pope may immitate, in this and all other Chriſtian duties. To be briefe (for in our royal controuerſies and diſputations wee doe handle this queſtion more accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, and employe beſides Scriptures, the fathers, Greeks and, Latines, the Schoolemen, Philoſophers, Polititians, Poets and Hiſtorians both ſacred, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, to prooue the truth of this point, againſt the ilearned Ieſuit <hi>Iames Gretſer</hi>) in the creation of <hi>Salomon,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t is ſaid that the people bowed downe their heads, and worſhipped the Lord, and the King. So that it is more then manifeſt, that the King is the perſon next vnto God, in power, dignitie, honour, and authoritie,
<note place="margin">1. Chron, 29, 20.</note> and therſore greater: and higher then the greateſt and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt prieſt, of them all.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 11.</head>
                     <p>The third leſſon that we learne hence, to wit,
<note place="margin">That kings are not lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men but of a mixt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</note> in that kings are called Gods, is that Kings, are called of God to be nurſing Fathers vnto the Church, and haue a ſpecial power about the things of God, and conſequently that they are not meere lay-men as both Ieſuits and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uians, Papiſts and Puritans doe holde, but of a mixt condition, partly Eccleſiaſticall, and partly ciuill or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, as in our latine workbefore named ſhal be largely proued both by Theology, &amp; by Philoſophy &amp; hiſtory. For the preſent; I ſay that the truth her of is apparent in Scripture, by precept made vnto Kings, by the practiſe of kings, vnder the law, and by Propheſie of Kings to be fulfilled vnder the Goſpell. And firſt it doth appeare by precept, in that Kings are enioyned in the Scripture to make themſelues able for the mannaging of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3528:14"/>things of God,
<note place="margin">Deut. 17, 18, 19. Pſal. 2, 10, Wiſe. 6, 1. Ioh. 10, 34.</note> for they are enioyned to <hi>study Gods word</hi> diligently, to <hi>reade in his Law</hi> continually, to bee <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>learned</hi> exceedingly: and therefore our Sauiour, teacheth vs that <hi>Kings</hi> are called <hi>Gods,</hi> becauſe the <hi>word of God, was giuen vnto them,</hi> meaning Principally, and to the end that they might gouerne Church and commonwealth according to God, and for God, as his vicares or depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, on earth. Secondly it doth appeare by the practiſe of Kings vnder the law,
<note place="margin">Exod. 39, 43. Ioſh. 3, &amp; 6, &amp; 22, 1.6. 2. Sam. 5, 6, 21 &amp; 6, 12. 1. Kings 2, 27 35, &amp; 5, 5. &amp; 8.14, 15, 10, 22. 2. King. 18, 4, &amp; 23, 4.5. &amp; 24, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25. 1. Chron. 13, 1, 2, 3. &amp;, 15, 1, 2, 3.4, 11, 16. 2. Chron, 15, 8, 9, 10, 16, &amp; 17, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, &amp; 19, 8. &amp; 20, 3, &amp;, 24, 4.5, 6, 7, 8, &amp;, 29, 4, 5, 11, 15, 18, 21, 25, 27, 30, 31, &amp; 31, 2.10, 11. 1. King. 2.27, 35, 2. Chron. 19, 11. Iſay 49, 22, 23.</note> and not onely of thoſe that were both Princes, and Prophets, as were <hi>Moſes, Dauid</hi> and <hi>Salomen,</hi> but alſo of thoſe that were meere Princes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Propheticall gift, ſuch as were <hi>Ioſhnah, Aſa, Icho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat, Ioaſh, Ezekiah, Ioſias</hi> &amp; <hi>Manaſſes;</hi> they haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man ded the Prieſts, yea euen the chiefe prieſts to doe the parts of their office, and appointed them to their courſes and charges, they haue placed and diſplaced the high Prieſts, themſelues, they haue ſuppreſſed Idolatrie, remoued and depoſed, yea put to death Idolatrous Prieſts, broken downe the Idols, reſtored religion, to her purity, aſſembled both the prieſts to bring vp the arke of the Lord, and the people to celebrate the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeouer, and to ſerue God, haue read the law publikely in the audience of the people, proclaimed faſts, &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for them, and bleſſed them likewiſe in the houſe of the Lord. Thirdly the Eccleſiaſticall power of Princes doth appeare by propheſie, for the Euangelicall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſay</hi> when hee foretolde the conuerſion of the Kings of the gentiles to the Chriſtian faith he likewiſe propheſied of their Eccleſiaſticall place and power, of being <hi>Nurſing Fathers</hi> vnto the <hi>Church</hi> ſaying; <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord God beholde I will lift vp mine hand to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, and ſet vp my ſtandard to the people, and they ſhall bring thy ſonnes</hi> (meaning the Churches children) <hi>in their armes, and thy Daughters ſhall bee carried vpon their ſhoulders; and Kings ſhall bee thy nurſing Fathers, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3528:14"/>Queenes ſhall be thy nurſes.</hi> And in our Latine worke of royall Controuerſies, we ſhall ſhow how this Propheſie hath beene accompliſhed in the perſon of Chriſtian Princes, Kings and Emperours, and how they haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed that part of the Eccleſiaſticall power, which ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the ſupreame gouernment of the Church. To wit that they haue made lawes of eccleſiaſticall matters, and for the confirmation of faith, haue tried matters of hereſie &amp; puniſhed heretickes, rooted out &amp; ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed I dolatry, exhorted and conuerted nations to the Chriſtian faith, inſtituted Biſhops, and ſent them to preach, placed paſtours in the Church, called councells and preſided in the ſame.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 12</head>
                     <p>The fourth thing that wee learne of this ſtile of God giuen to Kings by God himſelfe,
<note place="margin">That kings are lawgiuers vnto their people.</note> is that Kings are Lawgiuers vnto their people, that is to ſay, that they haue power from God to decree, and make lawes for the good gouernment of their kingdome, and not onely that they are appointed for the cuſtody, expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and execution of lawes, made or to bee made by the people, as ſome phanaticall ſpirits ſprong from the Lema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nian lake haue ſuppoſed. The people are law-takers not law-makers, and law-keepers, not law-giuers; for the law-giuing power is a diuine power, and therefore belongeth to God, or to him whom hee hath called by the name of God, to make lawes for God, and in his name, for the good of the people. And this doth appeare by diuers ſound and infallible arguments drawne from Gods word. Firſt in that <hi>Moſes</hi> gaue lawes and ciuill or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances vnto his people of the Hebrewes, wrote,
<note place="margin">Exod. 18.15, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26.</note> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered and declared them, and appointed inferiour Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates for the execution of them, to wit, the ſeuenty Elders, whereby we ſee how that the execution of lawes
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3528:15"/>appertaineth to the inferiour Magiſtrates, not to the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne; but that it is his part to make lawes, to giue &amp; expound them, like as it is the peoples part to take them and keepe them. Secondly, that Princes are law-giuers, it doth appeare in that the Lord commaundeth the King to write vnto himſelfe the law of God, to keepe it with him, and to reade therein all the dayes of his life. Now to what end all this? queſtionleſſe, that hee may learne there by to be like <hi>Moſes,</hi> euen a faithfull ſeruant of God in all his houſe,
<note place="margin">Numb. 12.7. Heb. 3.2.5.</note> and ouer all his houſe, and not onely that he might keepe Gods law the better in his owne perſon, but alſo, that he might deliuer the ſame to his people as <hi>Moſes</hi> did,
<note place="margin">Exod. 24.34 Deut. 17.18, 19. Ioh. 10.34, 35</note> to be obſerued of them: and that the lawes hee ſhould make himſelfe, might bee conformable to Gods lawes: for as God the King almighty is the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuer of Kings, ſo Kings, whom God hath called Gods, are the Law-giuers of their people. Thirdly this doth appeare in that <hi>Salomon</hi> calleth Mans law, the word of <hi>the mouth of the King, and the Kings word,</hi> like as the law of God euery where in the Scripture is called <hi>Gods word,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Eccl. 8.2, 3, 4. Pſal 119.1, 4, 5, 9, 10, 13, 16, 17. Exod. 24.28.</note> and the ten commandements the <hi>ten words of Gods mouth. I aduertiſe thee to take heed to the mouth of the King</hi> (ſaith the Spirit of God by <hi>Salomon) and to the word of the eath of God. Where the word of the King is, there is power, and who ſhall ſay vnto him what doeſt thou?</hi> Fourthly this doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, in that queſtionleſſe the more diuine power doth belong vnto the Prince,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 82.1, 6. 1. Chron. 29.23.</note> to whom God hath both giuen his owne diuine name, (and not to the people) and hath ſet him in his owne throne. Now to make a law is the moſt diuine thing that can be done of a man, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it appertaineth vnto the Prince, that ſitteth in Gods throne, and not to the people, that ſtand before the throne. Fiftly the eternall wiſedome ſaith, <hi>By mee Kings raigne and Princes decree instice,
<note place="margin">Prou. 8.15, 16</note> By mee Princes rule, and the Nobles and all the Iudges of the earth:</hi> out of which place,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3528:15"/>it is more then manifeſt that it belongeth to Kings and rulers to make decrees and lawes of iuſtice, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe rules of vpright liuing vnto their Subiects. Sixtly and laſtly it is ſaid of Kings in the Scripture, (and to their higheſt commendation) that they haue made certaine good lawes and decrees for the glorie of God, and the good of their people:
<note place="margin">Dan. 3.29. &amp; 6.25, 26.</note> thus <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> King of Babel, <hi>made a decree or law,</hi> that euery people, nation and language which ſhould ſpeake any blaſphemie againſt the God of <hi>Shadrach, Meſſach</hi> &amp; <hi>Abednego,</hi> ſhould be drawen in pieces, and that their houſes ſhould bee made a iakes, and <hi>Darius</hi> King of Medes and Perſians, <hi>made a law or decree;</hi> that in all the dominion of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, men ſhould tremble and feare before the God of <hi>Daniel:</hi> and by theſe ſixe arguments it is more then eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that the Prince, (and hee principally) hath an <hi>affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue</hi> voyce, and not onely a <hi>negatiue</hi> in the aſſembly of his eſtates. The which thing we ſhall prooue likewiſe by politicall and philoſophicall arguments in our Latine worke of Kingly controuerſies.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 13.</head>
                     <p>The fifth leſſon that we learne,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>That Kings are to be libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained.</hi> Prou. 3.9, 10.</note> in that Kings are of God, called Gods, is this, as we muſt honour God with our riches, and the oblation of our hands, according as <hi>Salomon</hi> exhorteth, ſaying, <hi>Honour the Lord with thy riches,</hi> &amp;c: ſo muſt we likewiſe honour them whom God hath called Gods, to wit, Soueraigne Princes, whom when as wee honour with our riches in giuing them a portion thereof, for their honourable prouiſion, then we honour God himſelfe with our riches, as <hi>Salomon</hi> exhorteth all men to doe, that would haue God to bleſſe them with abundance. And truly, if wee would be loath to let God want (if hee were ſubiect to want in his owne perſon, as man is) then ought we likewiſe be loath to let the Prince
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3528:16"/>want, who repreſenteth God, and therefore is called God, to teach vs, that what we beſtow vpon him wee offer vnto God and in whoſe perſon God oftentimes carrieth himſelfe as one that wanteth, and ſtandeth in need of our helpe. And if we would willingly, cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and without murmuring beſtow vpon our moſt bountifull Father, our goods in whole or in halfe, then truly wee ought not to murmure or grudge to beſtow vpon Princes (whom God hath called by the name of the children of <hi>the moſt High</hi>) a conuenient portion of the ſame,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 82.6.</note> at leſt for their fathers ſake. So that the good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſubiect when he ſeeth a King, eſpecially a Chriſtian King, and ſuch a one as beſides his diuine power is ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the diuine qualities and perfections of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, bounty, iuſtice and mercy, he ought to thinke with himſelfe, that he ſeeth God in mans likeneſſe, and when ſuch a King asketh ſubſidie or releefe at his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects hands, they ought to ſhew themſelues, as willing and ready thereunto, as they ſhould, if God himſelfe in mans likeneſſe were come downe amongſt men to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a ſacrifice or oblation at their hands. And though it bee true that that Almighty God doth not ſtand in need of any thing we haue, (for he is alſufficient in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe) yet wee muſt thinke that it is his pleaſure to carrie himſelfe oftentimes, as one that doth need in the perſon of the Prince, the Prieſt and the Poore. And this hee doth, to trie whether wee loue Almighty God and our neighbour better then our goods, or no, and to know by the effect, if we haue as yet attained to this perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as to giue vnto God all that we haue, if he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it at our hands; for the man that will grudge to giue a part vnto Gods Image and chiefe Miniſter for his ſake, will neuer be willing to forſake all for Gods ſake: no hee would neuer bee willing to beſtow his whole goods vpon God himſelfe, that will refuſe or repine to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3528:16"/>giue a part vnto his cheife Miniſter. And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariwiſe, the man that doth cheerefully beſtow vpon the Prince, in regard that hee is Gods Image, Deputie and Miniſter, (<hi>For he is the Minister of God for thy wealth</hi> ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>and for this cauſe ye pay alſo tribute,
<note place="margin">Rom 13.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</note> for they are Gods Ministers</hi>) doth in ſo doing euidently ſhow that hee lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth God better then his golde, and goodneſſe better then his goods, and that he would make no difficultie to beſtow moſt willingly 6all that he hath vpon God, yea to forſake his whole goods for Gods ſake. But of this matter of the Princes maintenance I haue entreated elſewhere, in another worke publiſhed ſome two or three yeares agoe, called the Golden art, or the right way of enriching, dedicated to the two Royal cities of theſe two kingdomes, but much more copiouſly in another worke of Kingly Controuerſies not as yet finiſhed, where I doe diſcourſe of the particular manner of the maintenance of Princes amongſt Gods people, both ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Scripture, the Iudgement of diuines, and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticians, and according to the ſeuerall cuſtomes of king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. And there I ſhow 1. that the ſoueraigne Prince, is not Lord of the whole goods of his ſubiects, and that his right doth not extend ouer their whole faculties, as ſome flatterers of Princes doe falſely and dangerouſly hold them in hand. Secondly, that the ſoueraigne Prince hath a right only to a certaine proportionable portion of the ſubiects goods. Thirdly, that as God and not man is the inſtitutor, author and ordainer of Kings, ſo is he the appointer of their portion, and the preſcriber of their manner of maintenance: for if God hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and inſtituted Kings to bee his Miniſters and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, for the gouernment of his people, as we haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſhowed that he hath; then muſt it needs be true, that the ſame God hath taken order for their mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. And truly ſeeing that all wiſe and good maſters
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3528:17"/>doe prouide for their ſeruants, and allow them meanes for their ſuſtenance and maintenance, it were a thing moſt vnbeſeeming the wiſedome and goodnes of God, who is the Maſter of maſters, both for wiſedome and goodneſſe, to thinke that he hath not as great care, and taken at leaſt as good order, for the maintenance of his ſeruants, namely of Kings, as other men being maſters, haue taken and doe take for theirs. God doth alwaies that which is moſt fitting, and therefore hee hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned and ordained the particular manner of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces maintenance: for it is moſt fitting that the maſter ſhould preſcribe and appoint the quantitie of his owne ſeruants wages. And it was ſo fit that God ſhould do it, that it was not fit nor expedient to referre the doing thereof, vnto the will or diſcretion of man. It was not fit that it ſhould be remitted to the will of the Prince him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, for he might perhaps require more then inough, as for example, the halfe, third, fourth, or fifth part of the ſubiects goods, neither was it fit that it ſhould be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the diſcretion of the people; for they lightly might allow the Prince leſſe then inough; and therefore God hath taken order for this thing himſelfe, and not left it for man to doe.
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.4.</note> For as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Who art thou that iudgeſt another mans ſeruant?</hi> ſo may it bee well ſaid in this matter; who art thou that takeſt vpon thee to ſhare out a portion or allowance for another mans ſeruant, yea for Gods owne chiefe ſeruant? doth not ſuch an office properly belong vnto God? Fourthly, that God hath ſet downe the manner of the Princes maintenance, and hath ſpecified the quantitie of his portion in ſome place of his word, and that hee hath done it in the fitteſt place that could bee for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: for except it were ſo, it ſhould not appeare, when it is, that a Prince playeth the Exactor, for ſeeing that he hath a right vnto a certaine portion of his ſubiects
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3528:17"/>goods (as all doe grant) how ſhall they know, when it is that he craueth more then hee ought, except there bee ſome law to determine his portion, and to inhibite him to leuy any more then the quantitie thereof doth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. In one word, Exaction in a Prince is the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Gods law, and not the breaking of ſome humane ſtatute or decree; and therefore there muſt be a certaine ſpeciall law in Gods word, touching the quantitie of the Princes portion, aſwell as there is of the Prieſts, the one beeing as important as the other, and Princes beeing Gods Miniſters and Seruants aſwell as Prieſts, and ſo conſequently to bee maintained aſwell as they. Yea it behoued ſo much the more, becauſe that Soueraigne Princes or Kings are Gods Miniſters in a higher, more eminent and honourable degree and kinde, then Prieſts are, as hath beene before abundantly ſhewed. So that it is not likely that the Spirit of God would haue omitted ſo important a point as this is; being ſuch as that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the certaine knowledge thereof, neither can Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes nor Subiects doe their dutie to one another. For neither can they know when it is that the Soueraigne keepes himſelfe within the bounds of equitie and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, or contrariwiſe that he debordeth into oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, extortion, or exaction; neither yet when it is, that the ſubiect offendeth by detention or diminution of his Soueraignes due. Seeing then it was ſo neceſſarie for the quiet, iuſt, and vpright conſtitution of a kingdome amongſt Gods people, that the Kings portion ſhould be ſpecified aſwell as the Prieſts, we need not doubt, but that the Spirit of God hath propoſed the ſame, ſome where in holy Scripture, and euen in that place which was of all other the moſt conuenient for ſuch a purpoſe; and what place of Scripture ſo conuenient as that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the firſt inſtitution of Kings amongſt amongſt Gods people is propounded and expounded? The which
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3528:18"/>place, becauſe ſome Geneuians and moderne diuine haue monſtrouſly miſconſtered, I ſhal refute their errour (God-willing) other where by 13 vnanſwerable argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. And amongſt other probations, we ſhal ſhow it by the Hebrew Text, the <hi>Chaldaick Thargums</hi> or <hi>Paraphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> the Greeke tranſlation of the <hi>Septuagints,</hi> the Latine tranſlations of <hi>Hieronymus, Pagninus, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>atablus, Munste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, Leo, Montanus,</hi> with the old Engliſh, and namely, that the word MISHPAT, which is tranſlated <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> in Greeke, and in Latine <hi>Ius</hi> or <hi>Lex,</hi> is alwaies taken in the Scripture, and in no fewer then 210. places for the vpright iudgement of God, and of the Kings and Iudges of the earth, and no where for vniuſt and tyrannicall gouernment, or for a Princes abuſiue power; as ſome mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derne writers haue vnderſtood it moſt groſſely in that ſame place of Scripture, whereupon the reſolution of this queſtion doth wholly depend: a thing which I wiſh our diuines ſhould well conſider, that they doe not runne into their errour;
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 8.9.10, 11.21, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17.</note> in expounding thoſe words of the Prophet <hi>Samuel.</hi> But of this more in another worke. In the meane time I would entreate all good ſubiects to beware of charging, either now or hereafter, their Prince with the odious aſperſion of Exaction, vnleſſe they can ſhow that he requireth and receiueth more of his people, then the law of God doth allow him; but that they would honour him with their beſt opinion, not only of a iuſt and vpright Prince, but euen of an indulgent, and beneficent Father, incaſe it ſhall be well and ſufficiently prooued vnto them, that he is ſo farre from the iniuſtice, of requiring or taking from them any part of their own, that hee euen releaſeth and giueth them a part of his owne, which is indulgencie, bounty and beneficence, and in a word: that he is content for his louing ſubiects further eaſe, to leuie much leſſe then Gods law doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, for the maintenance of himſelfe, his chiefe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3528:18"/>officers in the Common-wealth and in the Court, and of his other ſeruants at home or abroad, in peace and in warre.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 14.</head>
                     <p>The ſixt and laſt leſſon that we learne,
<note place="margin">That kings are free from all manner of coercion &amp; cenſure.</note> in that Kings are called Gods, is that Almighty God in giuing them this name, euen his owne name, hath exempted them from all manner of violence, coercion or cenſure at their ſubiects and inferiours hands; where as our Geneuites aſwell as Ieſuites, and Caluiniſts, aſwell as Papiſts doe hold the contrary; for both of them wil haue Soueraigne Princes ſubiect to coercion, excommunication and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuation: a doctrine and opinion, repugnant I dare ſay both to Theologie and Philoſophie, to Diuinitie and Humanitie, as we ſhal (God willing) ſhow at large other where. For the preſent, becauſe in this worke we thought good for ſoliditie and breuities ſake to employ only te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of Scripture and ſome reaſons deriued from thence, it ſhall ſuffice that we ſhow and confute the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie and abſurditie, yea the vnlearnedneſſe and ſtupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie of this doctrine of Geneua and Rome, by theſe 17 reaſons after following. The which if any Diuine can anſwere ſufficiently and ſoundly, or bring better rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for the contrary opinion, I ſhall not be aſhamed to change the opinion that I now hold, and ſubſcribe to theirs, and freely confeſſe this of mine to bee as blockiſh and vnlearned, as now I hold theirs to bee. Firſt, God himſelfe by his ſeruant <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith vnto euery Subiect, <hi>Thou ſhalt not raile vpon the Gods,
<note place="margin">Exod. 22, 28.</note> nor ſpeake euill of the Ruler of thy people:</hi> if it bee not lawfull to rayle vpon the Prince, then muſt it bee as vnlawfull to rage or riſe vp againſt him; and if wee muſt beware of vehement words in his behalfe, then much more, of violent deeds: and if the ſubiects muſt not ſpeake euill of their Ruler or Soueraigne, then they cannot excommunicate him:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3528:19"/>for whoſoeuer excommunicateth a Prince, muſt needs ſpeake the greateſt euill of a Prince that can bee, euen that hee is a moſt wicked man, and fitter to bee Sathans ſlaue then Gods ſeruant.
<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. 10.20.</note> To the ſame purpoſe appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that other precept or prohibition of the Spirit of God, by the mouth of <hi>Salomon,</hi> proclaimed to ſubiects, <hi>Curſe not the Prince, no not in thy thought:</hi> if it be not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to curſe the King, then is it not lawfull to excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate him;
<note place="margin">1, Chron. 29.23. Pſal. 21.3.</note> let both <hi>Rome</hi> rage, and <hi>Geneua</hi> iangle as much as they can to the contrary. Secondly, God hath ſet the King in his throne, and ſet on his head with his owne hand a crowne of pure gold; now who can ſay that it is fitting or comely that any man or order of men, eſpecially ſubiects, and ſuch as ſtand before the throne, ſhould offer violence to him that ſitteth in the throne, or put out the hand to thruſt him out of the throne, or to pull off the crowne that God hath put vpon his head. Thirdly, <hi>It is the most high,</hi> (ſaith the holy Angel and the Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Dan. 4.22.28.29. Prouerb. 21.1</note> to King <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>) <hi>that beareth rule ouer the Kingdome of men, and giueth it to whomſoeuer he will: The Kings heart is in the hands of the Lord, as the riuers of waters, he turneth it whither ſoeuer it pleaſeth him</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) and therefore the moſt high is the onely <hi>Ruler, Curber, Connerter,</hi> and <hi>Scourger</hi> of Kings, and men muſt not bee ſo bould, as to take Gods proper office vpon them: for in ſo doing, they commit a greater offence againſt God, then doth the greateſt Tyrant that can be, in plaguing and perſecuting his people. For no ſubiect, one or moe, eccleſiaſticall or ſecular can meddle in ſuch a matter as this, without impeaching God of a notable imperfection: for either they muſt thinke that God ſeeth not the wickednes of the tyrannous or idolatrous King, which is to deny his diuine omniſcience and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute knowledge, or if hee ſeeth it, that he careth not for it, which is to deny his diuine prouidence, and to charge
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3528:19"/>him with humane negligence; or if he care for it, that he is either vnable to reuenge it without the hand of the Kings owne ſubiect, which is to deny his diuine omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency, and to brand him with humane infirmity, or elſe that he is vnwilling to reuenge it; which is to charge him both with iniuſtice and want of mercy. Whence it followeth, that ſuch ſubiects as would correct their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, doe both make God no God, and make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues God: in a word, ſuch a ſubiect is <hi>Dauids</hi> foole,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 53.1.2. Theſſ. 2.4.</note> that hath ſaid in his heart, there is no God, except perhaps himſelfe, and ſo becommeth ſuch an Antichriſtian Anti-god, as exalteth himſelfe both aboue Gods God on earth the King, and aboue the God in heauen, in taking his proper place and office vpon him. No,
<note place="margin">Ioſh. 6.8, 10, 11 12, cap. Iudg. 1.2.6, 7, &amp;, 3, 15, 16, 17, 20, 21, 22, 26, 27, 28, 1. Sam. 13, &amp;. 15. &amp;. 22, &amp; 31 1. King. 16, &amp; 22. 2. King. 16. &amp; 25. 2. Chron. 28. &amp; 33. Exod. 14, 28, &amp; 15, 4. Dan. 4.22, 28 29, 30. 1. King. 1, 2, 3, 4, 16, 17, &amp; 15, 4, 5. 2. Chron. 26, 16, 17, 18, 19 20, 21.</note> God needeth not the hand of any ſubiect, to be reuenged on a wicked Prince, for hee can ſtirre vp other Princes and people or forraine perſons againſt him, as we reade, that hee did againſt theſe Kings of <hi>Iericho,</hi> of <hi>Ai,</hi> and of the Amorites, againſt <hi>Adonibezek</hi> King of <hi>Canaan, Eglon</hi> King of <hi>Meab, Saul, Ahab, Ahaz, Manaſſeth,</hi> and <hi>Zedekias,</hi> Kings of <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael:</hi> or he can make the wicked King (as it were with his own hand) execute Gods ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> himſelf: thus he ſuffered <hi>Saul</hi> to ſlay himſelfe, and <hi>Zimri</hi> to burne himſelfe. And as he wil not employ a Princes owne ſubiects in ſuch a buſineſſe, ſo he needeth not to vſe the hand and power of any perſon whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer; for God can drowne the wicked Prince in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or ſea with <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> or hee can ſtrike him with mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> or hee can burſt him or breake his necke with <hi>Ahazias,</hi> or can ſtrike him with leproſie like <hi>Vzziah</hi> or <hi>Azariah.</hi> The very elements, and beaſts of the field are at his beck and bidding, the beaſts to deuoure, the fire to burne, the aire to infect, the water to drowne, and the earth to ſwallow vp ſuch Princes, as God will be auenged on, yea he hath armies of painefull
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3528:20"/>and ſhamefull diſeaſes, of wormes, of mice and of lice to conſume and vexe wicked Kings with.
<note place="margin">Dan. 4, 10, 11 12, 13, 14, 22 23, 28, 29, 30. &amp; 5.6, 7, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28 2. Micha. 6.9. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10 11, 12, 13, 14 15, 16, 17, 18 28.</note> And as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of God (which are his higheſt creatures) ſmote <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar</hi> with madnes, &amp; droue him from amongſt men, to dwell with the beaſts of the field, and ſo depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him of his kingdome for a time (for thoſe Noters and Geneuian Gloſſers are deceiued, that doe thinke his owne ſubiects did depoſe him for tyrannie) and as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Angel did write vpon the wall, the ſentence of King <hi>Belſchazzars</hi> deſtruction; ſo the wormes that are the Lords loweſt creatures, conſpired to vexe the wicked tyrant <hi>Antiochus</hi> the cruell perſecuter of the Iewes, that he died miſerably; and both theſe creatures together, the higheſt in heauen,
<note place="margin">act 12.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 21, 22, 23</note> and the loweſt on earth, did at Gods appointment concurre to plague <hi>Herod</hi> the perſecutor of the Chriſtians, who had vexed many of the faithfull, killed <hi>Iames</hi> and impriſoned <hi>Peter:</hi> for the Angel of the Lord ſmote him, becauſe he gaue not glory vnto God, ſo that hee was eaten vp of wormes. Thus we ſee how God getteth glory, when he correcteth wicked Kings with his owne hands,
<note place="margin">1. Sam 13.9, 10, 11, 12, 13 14, &amp; 15, 1, 2 3, 8, 9, 10 11, 16, 17, 22, 23 &amp; 19, 20, 22, 23, 26, 28, cap. 1. King. 16.30, 31, 32, &amp; 17, 18, 19, 20 21, 22, cap, 2. King. 21, 1, 2, 3, 4.5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 16 2. Chron. 33.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</note> whereas he is robbed of his glorie by ſuch ſubiects as dare take the rod, as it were out of Gods hands, and put it into their owne, to ſcourge Kings with. Fourthly, the people of God vnder the old Teſtament did not impriſon or depoſe their moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Princes, ſuch as were <hi>Saul, Ahab,</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> nor did the high Prieſts excommunicate them for their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie, tyrannie, apoſtaſie and idolatrie, perſecution and ſeduction; and therefore the people of God vnder the new Teſtament ought to doe the like, in following the example of their pietie and patience in the behalfe of bad Princes; otherwiſe Chriſtians ſhould come ſhort of the Iewes in morall perfections, which were abſurd. Fifthly, the conſtitution and creation of Kings is of God and not not of man, it is Gods hand only that can
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3528:20"/>make a King, according as he ſaith himſelfe, <hi>By me Kings raigne,</hi> and as we haue prooued aboue in the firſt leſſon, and therefore the depoſition of Kings,
<note place="margin">Prouerb. 8.15</note> and their coerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, belongeth likewiſe to God, and not to the Kings owne ſubiects, for the power is equall in the one and the other. And therefore wee ſee that the voice that depoſed <hi>Nebuchadnezzer,</hi> came from heauen.
<note place="margin">Dan. 4.22, 28, 29.</note> 
                        <hi>Thy kingdome is departed from thee,</hi> like as the Angel and the Prophet doe both of them auouch, that it is the moſt high that giueth the kingdome to whomſoeuer hee will. Sixtly in the new Teſtament Chriſt and his appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, do oftentimes command ſubiects to <hi>giue</hi> vnto Kings, but no where they bid <hi>take away</hi> or <hi>withhold</hi> any thing from Kings, howſoeuer vnworthy, neither tribute and liuing by detention, nor libertie by incarceration, nor Kingſhip by depriuation, nor life by ciuil (or rather vnciuill and ſinnefull) execution, nor the benefits of the Church and kingdome of heauen, by helliſh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication. <hi>Giue</hi> (ſaith the King of Kings) <hi>vnto Caeſar the things which are Caeſars,</hi> like as he had comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>Peter</hi> his very prime Apoſtle to <hi>giue</hi> the Kings Receiuer poll money for them two,
<note place="margin">Mat. 22, 17, 21, &amp;, 17, 24, 25, 26, 27, Mark. 12, 14, 15, 16, 17. Mat. 10.1, 2. 1. Pet. 2.17. Rom. 13, 1, 2, 24.</note> 
                        <hi>giue</hi> (ſaith hee) the <hi>twenty pence vnto them for me and thee,</hi> and the ſame prime Apoſtle, commandeth all ſubiects both ſpirituall and temporall perſons, euen as many as haue Soules, (for his fellow Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith <hi>let euery ſoule beſubiect to prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) to feare God and honour the King,</hi> Ergo ſubiects muſt not diſhonour the King by coercion, incarceration, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication or depriuation. Yea Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor himſelfe (if he hath any) hath no power to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour the King, whom God hath honoured with his crowne and throne, let him be neuer ſo vnworthy in his conceite, nor to expoſe him to the diſhonour, or danger of any of his ſubiects, by his cenſure of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, or ſentence of depriuation. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3528:21"/>bids <hi>giue</hi> to Kings, Saint <hi>Peter gaue</hi> to Kings' and bids <hi>giue</hi> them honour, and ſo doth <hi>S. Paul, ſaying, Giue to all men their duty,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.7.</note> tribute to whome yee owe tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, custome, to whome cnſtome, feare to whome feare, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to whom yee owe houour.</hi> And no where they bid <hi>take away</hi> any thing from Kings: and therefore ſuch men as take away from Kings their liuings libertie or life, or the benefits of the Church, Gods kingdome, or their owne doe diſobey God, the father of Kings, and obey the deuil the diſhonourer, &amp; debaſer of kings. Seuenthly, wee doe not read in Gods word that euer a King was deliuered vnto Satan; ſo that it wanteth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; and as for precept, the very formal words vſed in the inſtitution of excommunication by our Lord, do ſhew that it was neuer intended for Kings, by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God. For beſides they were not as yet within the boſome of the Church,
<note place="margin">Mat. 18, 15, 16, 17.</note> by calling, when it was ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, thoſe words; <hi>If thy brother trespaſſe againſt thee, If thy brother hoare thee, If thy brother heare thee not, If thy brother refuſe to heare the Church alſo,</hi> do euidently, and pregnantly euince, that excommunication is a cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of an offending brother,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.12.</note> not of the father of the people. And therefore the Apoſtle entreating of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, extendeth it no further, then unto ſuch a one as is called a <hi>brother. If any that is called a brother</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>be a formcatour,
<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 3.13.14, 15.</note> or couetous, or an idolater, or a railer, or a drunkard, or an extortioner, with ſuch a one eate not, neither companie together;</hi> and againe, <hi>And ye brethren be not wearie in well doing, if any man</hi> (to wit beeing a brother) <hi>obey not our ſayings, note him by a letter, and haue no compante with him, that he may be aſhamed; yet count him not as an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie but admoniſh him as abrother.</hi> And though it bee true that the beleeuing Soueraigne aſwel as the Subiect is a <hi>brother</hi> in Chriſtianitie, and might well haue beene ſo called by our bleſſed Sauiour, and his Apoſtle, yet I
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3528:21"/>ſay it doth not appeare that they vnderſtood by the title of brother in thoſe places, but ſuch as did then beleeue the Goſpell, who were all ſubiects, for as yet there were no beleeuing Soueraignes; yea both our Sauiours and the Apoſtles words doe euince that a King though hee bee a beleeuer and ſo a brother, yet that he can not bee brought in amongſt thoſe excommunicable brothers, becauſe the excommunicated brother muſt be vnto the other brethren as an <hi>Heathen</hi> and a <hi>Publican,</hi> as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour commandeth, that is to ſay, they muſt auoide his conuerſation, and decline his companie, and flee his familiaritie, as the Apoſlle expoundeth it. But ſo it is that ſubiects can not by any meanes ſhunne or abhorre the preſence and conuerſation of their Soueraigne, both becauſe of duty, and becauſe of neceſſitie. As for duty, the lawes of nature and of Scripture, of reaſon and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of Church &amp; State, doe oblige ſubiects to doe their duty to their Soueraigne be he neuer ſo bad; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they muſt repaire vnto his preſence and conuerſe with him, whenſoeuer it pleaſeth him to command. And as for neceſſitie; ſubiects can not chooſe but repaire to the Prince to haue iuſlice, and ſuch other helpe as they ſland in need of at his hands. And therefore I ſay, though both Rome and Geneua ſhould ioyne their iarring and warring wits together, yet they ſhall neuer bee able to ſolue or ſatisfie this argument,
<note place="margin">Mat. 18.17. 1. Cor. 5.5.9.11. 2. Theſſ. 3.14. 1. Tim. 1.20.</note> all excommunicated per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons preſence, ſocietie and companie, is to be ſhunned as a Heathens, a Publicanes, or which is worſe, as a mans deliuered to the Diuell. But no Kings preſence, ſociety and conuerſation can bee ſhunned of their ſubiects, for both duty and neceſſitie binde them to the contrary. <hi>Ergo</hi> no Kings can be excommunicated: or thus; the effects of excommunication can not haue place in the perſon of a Prince, as for example, his preſence and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation can not be declined of his ſubiects, without
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3528:22"/>both ſinne and their great hurt, and therefore the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure it ſelfe hath no place in Princes. Ninthly, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication of an vniuerſalitie or multitude, as of a whole citie, Body, Common-wealth or kingdome is in the iudgement of all, thought a thing vnlawfull; and ſemblably the excommunication of the Soueraigne, as he that repreſenteth the whole Body of his kingdome, muſt bee vnlawfull: neither can the head be puniſhed without the ſenſible hurt of the whole body. Tenthly, God is a God of order &amp; not of diſorder or confuſion,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.33.</note> as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, and therefore hee hath not giuen the inferiours power to puniſh corporally or ſpiritually their ſuperiours, for this were moſt contrary to order, &amp; conſequently he hath not giuen ſubiects any power vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Soueraigne, nor Prieſts any power to puniſh Princes; for both people and prieſts be inferiours, and their Soueraigne is their ſuperiour; they are as members of the body taken ſeuerally, the commons as feete, the Nobles as hands, the Prieſts as eyes: or they are as the bodie, being taken coniunctly, but the Soueraigne is as the head, higher then all the other members, and aboue the whole body, and as the ſoule more diuine, excellent and eminent then the whole body; the ſubiects are as ſeruants, the Soueraigne as the Maſter or Lord, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as the children, and the Prince as their common fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. It is againſt good nature and order, for the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our members to riſe or rebell againſt the ſupreame mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, for the body to beate or breake the owne head, and it is repugnant both to good nature and grace, for chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to ſtretch forth the hand to chaſtiſe or puniſh their father bee hee neuer ſo furious. And as for the chiefe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Prieſts and Prelates they are as Angels and Archangels, indeed, but the Soueraigne Prince, is as the God of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Archangels farre aboue their reach. Eleuenth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if it belongeth not vnto one man or more men to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3528:22"/>beate, puniſh, iudge or condemne another mans ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant as the Apoſtle <hi>S. lames</hi> teacheth, ſaying, <hi>Who art thou that iudgest another man?</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iam. 4.12, Rom. 14.4.</note> and the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul</hi> likewiſe, ſaying, <hi>Who art thou that condemneſt another mans ſeruant?</hi> then it belongeth much leſſe to one man or more to iudge, puniſh, excommunicate, depoſe or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne Gods chiefe ſeruant;
<note place="margin">Rom, 13 4.</note> now the Prince is Gods ſeruant, ſaith the ſame Apoſlle and in the ſame Epiſtle to the Romanes (and I wiſh that both Romanes and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuians would weigh thoſe words better then they do) and therefore who is hee that condemneth ſuch a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, as is not only another mans ſeruant, but euen the beſt mans ſeruant, to with Chriſts, and his chiefe ſeruant, yea Gods ſeruant? <hi>He ſtandeth or falleth to his owne master,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, and that is, neither the Pope of Rome, nor the maſter Miniſter of Geneua; but God and Chriſt; who will not haue his ſeruant ſubiect to the proud cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure eitheir of the Romane Conſiſtorie, or of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uian Preſbyterie. The Apoſtle would not preſume to iudge them that are without the Church, becauſe they belonged to Gods iudgement in propriety, <hi>what haue I to doe to iudge them alſo which are without</hi> ſaith he, <hi>doe ye not iudge them that are within?</hi> but God iudgeth them that are without, and ſhall we thinke that he would haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to iudge thoſe that God hath placed aboue the Church, I meane Chriſtian Princes,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.12.13.</note> who though they be within the boſome of the Church as Chriſtians, yet are they without or aboue the reach of the hands of the Church, as the nurſing-fathers and heads of the Church on earth, vnder Chriſt the Soueraigne King of the Church, whoſe immediate ſeruants they are, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as his peculiars are ſubiect to nones iudgement but his only. Twelfthly, if ſeruants muſt be ſubiect to their maſters with all feare, and not only to the good and courteous, but alſo to the froward, as the Apoſtle Saint
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3528:23"/>
                        <hi>Peter</hi> teacheth;
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21 22, 23.</note> then muſt ſubiects be loy all and dutifull to their Soueraigne, and not only to the good, but alſo to the euill; for as the family is a little kingdome, and the maſter of the family, a little king, and the ſonnes and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants of the family, are the ſubiects of this little king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; ſo is the kingdome a great family, the King the great maſter of this great family, and his ſubiects are the children and ſeruants of the ſame family. Thirteenthly, if the Angels of heauens Church, from their heauenly ſeates and habitations, doe not exclaime or giue out rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling iudgement againſt Princes before the Lord, though they ſee and know their wickedneſſe much better then men doe,
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.10, 11</note> and that they be aboue them in dignitie, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and place, as the Apoſlle S. <hi>Peter</hi> doth auouch and witnes; then much leſſe muſt the Angels of the Church on earth, Romane or Geneuian, from their earthly ſeats, and pulpits, Conſiſtories or Preſbyteries exclaime a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Princes, be they neuer ſo wicked, or yet proclaime any railing iudgement againſt them, ſeeing they are not only inferiour vnto the Angels in heauen which ſpare them, but euen vnto the Princes themſelues, which are Gods by their place, though in their perſons they were neuer ſo prophane. And I wiſh with all my heart that the great Angel that ſitteth in <hi>S. Angel,</hi> would now at laſt learne this Angelicall leſſon, of thoſe Angelicall Doctors in heauen, and of his owne ſuppoſed Euangelicall Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor <hi>Saint Peter,</hi> who profeſſeth in expreſſe words, that it is one of the properties of falſe Prophets to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe Princes, and to ſpeake euill of them that are in dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and authoritie;
<note place="margin">Iude. v. 8.9, 10</note> 
                        <hi>Where as the Angels which are greater both in power and might, giue not railing Iudgement against them,</hi> and the ſame thing is ſaid of <hi>Saint Iude.</hi> Fourtenth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if a moſt holy Angel, yea euen <hi>Michael,</hi> the higheſt Archangel durſt not raile vpon the diuell, who is all wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, nor blame him with curſed ſpeaking, when as he ſtrone againſt him, and diſputed about the bodie of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3528:23"/>
                        <hi>Moſes,</hi> as the holy Apoſtle <hi>Iude</hi> witneſſeth, how then dare ſubiects, which be ſinfull men themſelues raile vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Prince, or how dare either the Romane Archan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel that ſitteth in <hi>S. Angel,</hi> or the Angelings of Geneua, from their conſiſt orie or preſbyterie, or yet from their pulpits pronounce any curſe or excommunication a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Princes, or deliuer them vnto the diuell, though they were liker little diuels, then little Gods on earth, by reaſon of their wicked liuing? And if wee muſt not ſo much as raile vpon wicked Kings, nor reuile and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame them with our tongues, much leſſe muſt wee hurt them with our hands, or offer their perſons any violence. <hi>If ye loue them which loue you,</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour,) <hi>and dee good to them which doe good to you, what thanke haue yee, or what reward?
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.46, 47, Luk. 6.32, 33</note> doe not the Publicanes and ſinners euen the ſame?</hi> and the like may be ſaid in this caſe, if Chriſtians loue and loyally obey ſuch Princes as loue them, and if they ſpeake well of ſuch gouernours, as doe wel to them, and ſubmit themſelues to ſuch Princes as are vertuous, godly and iuſt, what thanke, or what reward haue they, or what ſingular worke doe they worthy of a ſingular reward? doe not the heathen and infidels, euen the ſame? and as our Sauiour ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>Except your righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe exceede the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies,</hi> and not only of publicanes &amp; ſinners,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.10.</note> 
                        <hi>ye ſhall not enter into the kingdome of God;</hi> So may it bee ſaid to Chriſtian ſubiects, except your obedience, ſubiection &amp; patience, in the behalfe of your Princes and Rulers exceede the obedience, ſubiection &amp; patience of heathen and vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing ſubiects in the behalfe of their Soueraignes, yee cannot bee ſubiects of the kingdome of heauen.</p>
                     <p>Fifteenthly, Subiects ought to bee moſt tender and carefull of the ſaluation of their Soueraigne, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ought not to ſeclude him from the vſe of the ordinary meanes of his amendment, his ſanctification
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3528:24"/>and ſaluation; as from the hearing of the word, the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Church, and the receiuing of the Sacrament.</p>
                     <p>Sixteenthly, a wicked Prince in receiuing the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, either receiueth it worthily and penitently, and ſo is pardoned, or elſe vnworthily and impenitently, and ſo is plagued of God, according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Hee that eateth and drinketh vnworthily,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.28.29.</note> eateth and drinketh his owne damnation, becauſe he diſcerneth not the Lords body,</hi> and ſo hee is either made better or worſe; if better, then it ſhould not haue beene well done to keep him from the Communion, if worſe, then God himſelfe hath puniſhed and plagued him with his owne hand, which is much more fit, then that any of his owne Subiects ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to puniſh him. So that it is euery way more for the glory of God and the good of the Church, that a Prince be admitted to the Sacrament, then that hee be ſecluded there-fro; for either Gods mercie is manifeſted, when as receiuing it worthily and wel, he amendeth his manners, or his iuſtice is executed and notified, when as receiuing it vnworthily, he runneth into ſome greater ſinne, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curreth ſome temporall or ſpiritual iudgement, and both the wayes Gods glorie is more and more demonſtrated, and the Church edified by ſo notable an example. Seuenteenthly and laſtly, our moſt bleſſed Sauiour when he exhorteth vs vnto perfection, (ſaith thus,) <hi>Loue your enemies,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.44, 45, 48. Luk. 6.27, 28, 35.</note> bleſſe them that curſe you, doe good to them that hate you, pray for them which hurt you wrongfully, trouble and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute you, that ye may be the children of your Father which is in heauen, who is kinde and good, both vnto the good and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill;</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>Saint Paul</hi> writing to the Romanes ſaith the ſame: <hi>Bleſſe them which perſecute you, Bleſſe and curſe not, recompence to no man euill for euill, auenge not your ſelues, but rather giue place vnto wrath, for it is written, venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is mine,
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.14, 17, 19, 21.</note> I will repay ſaith the Lord.</hi> Whereof it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that if Princes bee our foes, which ought to bee our
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3528:24"/>friends, yea our fathers, and ſo both hate vs and hurt vs which are their ſubiects: yet wee ought to loue them, and helpe them what wee can, though they doe euill to vs, yet wee ought to doe good to them, though they op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and perſecute vs, yet wee ought to pray for them, though they ſpeake euill of vs, yet wee ought to ſpeake well of them, though they grieue vs, yet we ought not to grudge againſt them, though they require too much of vs, and more then we can well ſpare, yet we ought not to refuſe them, much leſſe to reſiſt them, or rebell againſt them: though they haue many imperfections, yet wee ought not to aggrauate them, or blaze them abroad by ſlandrous wordes or infamous writes: yea rather wee ought to extenuate and to leſſen them, hide them, couer them, and excuſe them. Finally though they ſeeke to kill both our bodies and our ſoules, yet we ought to ſeeke the preſeruation of their bodies, and the ſaluation of their ſoules; and in ſo doing we ſubiects ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit as the children of the moſt high, and our reward ſhall be great and ineſtimable in the heauens.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 15.
<note place="margin">The Church of England more Angelicall or Angel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.</note>
                     </head>
                     <p>We haue ſhewed at large the perfection of the Church of England in regard of the diuine condition of the <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Gouernour</hi> thereof vpon earth, which is the King, whom God himſelfe hath called by the name of God, as hee that hath his royall power immediately from God, and not from man, contrary to the opinion of <hi>Romanes</hi> and <hi>Geneuians,</hi> and whoſe dignity is abſolutely the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and diuineſt of all other, and much more eminent then the Prieſtly, contrary to the opinion of the ſame, and whoſe perſon and power is mixt of eccleſiaſticall and ciuill, as he that is not a meere lay-man, contrary to the opinion of them likewiſe, and whoſe Maieſtie and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie is inuiolable, and not liable to any kinde of cenſure or puniſhment at the hands of man, ſpirituall or tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3528:25"/>otherwiſe then both <hi>Romanes</hi> and <hi>Geneuians</hi> would make vs beleeue, in all which points for all their ium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping together, they erre moſt groſſely, and the Church of England holdeth or thodoxally. Now in the next place wee ſhall prooue the perfection of the ſame Church by ſhewing how that ſhe is more <hi>Angelicall</hi> or Angel-like in reſpect of the ſecondary Gouernours of the Church, and conſequently liker vnto Gods Church in heauen then any Geneuian Church is. For like as in the Church of God in heauen, God himſelfe gouerneth ſoueraignely and ſupreamely, as Monarch and King, and the <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angells</hi> doe gouerne the inferiour <hi>Angels</hi> ſecondarily as Senatours, and the twenty foure crowned Elders, which are of the bleſſed Spirits of men doe gouerne the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſpirits, as we may learne by ſome ten chapters of the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> and as all ancient Diuines doe deliuer; ſo in the Church of England, the <hi>Soueraigne Prince</hi> as God, and for God, doth gouerne it ſupreamely vpon earth, and ſecondarily the <hi>Archbiſhops,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Colloſſ. 1.16, 1. Theſſ. 4.16.</note> as <hi>Archangels</hi> doe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide aboue the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> which againe as <hi>Angels</hi> (and ſo are they called in the ſame Diuine <hi>Reuelation,</hi> ſeuen times in two chapters) doe gouerne the inferiour <hi>Ministers</hi> of the Word and Sacraments; and theſe againe like vnto thoſe more perfit ſpirits or ſoules of men,
<note place="margin">Reuela. 45, 7, 8, 9, 12, 14, 15 16, &amp; 19. cap. Reuel. 2.1, 8, 12, 18, &amp; 3, 1, 7, 14,</note> doe gouerne the lay multitude of men and women. So that the <hi>Anglicane</hi> or Engliſh Church is more <hi>Angelicall</hi> or <hi>Angel-like</hi> then the Geneuian is, which admitteth no ſuch Angelicall diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and order of Miniſters; for there they are equall, and neither like the <hi>Angels</hi> in heauen, which haue their chiefe Princes,
<note place="margin">Dan. 10.13, &amp; 12.1. Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e verſ. 9. Reuel. 12.7. Coloſ. 1.16. Reuel. 9.11. &amp; 12.7.</note> and their inferiours, as namely, <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangel and his Angels; euen <hi>Thrones, Domimons, Principalities, Powers,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, nor like the <hi>Diuels</hi> in hell; which are better ordered, as hauing a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of degrees, for the <hi>Angel-king</hi> of the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe pit, otherwiſe called the <hi>Dragon,</hi> hath many blacke
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3528:25"/>Angels vnder him; whence it followeth that the <hi>Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane</hi> Church as being the more <hi>Angelicall</hi> or Angel-like is perfiter then the <hi>Geneuian</hi> by farre.</p>
                     <p>And truly I can not wonder inough of this paritie of theirs from whence they had it, for it is more then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that they had it not from heauen, nor yet from hell, as hath beene before ſhewed; belike they haue learned it of the <hi>Graſhoppers,</hi> that leape about the banks of the Lemannian lake, <hi>for they haue no King, yet goe they forth all by bands</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon.</hi> From the Church of God vnder the law they had it not, for they had their high Prieſts their principall or chiefe Prieſts, and their inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Prieſts,
<note place="margin">Exod. 28. Leuit. 8. Numb. 3. &amp;, 4, &amp;, 8, &amp;, 18, 1. Chron. 9. &amp; 15, &amp; 16, &amp;, 24, &amp; 25, &amp; 26 2. King. 23. Nehem. 12. Heb. 5, 5, 6, 10 Mat. 10, 1, 2, &amp; 28, 16, Mark, 3.14, &amp; 6, 7, Luk. 6, 13, &amp; 9, 1, Act. 1.22, 16, &amp; 2, 14, &amp;, 6, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, &amp;, 8, 5, 6, 14, 15, 16, 17, &amp;, 19, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 7 Cor. 12.28, 29. Epheſ 4.11.12.</note> and likewiſe among the Leuites ſome were ſuperiours, and ſome inferiours, ſome were as Lords and chiefe Fathers, and other ſome as ſonnes and followers. Nor had they their paritie and equalitie of Church Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters from the Church of God vnder the Goſpell, ſuch as it was in the daies of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, for our Sauiour himſelfe was as the high Prieſt, the Apoſtles as the chiefe Prieſts, the ſeuenty Diſciples as the inferiour Prieſts, and the Deacons as the Leuites: and no man that hath his right wittes, will ſay that the Apoſtles, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Euangeliſts, and Paſtours mentioned by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> as ordained of God in the Church, were all equall in dignitie and office. Neither had they their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of paſtours from the Church, ſuch as it was after the Apoſtles daies, for within the firſt fiue hundreth yeares we read in the Eccleſiaſticall hiſtories, how that the Church was gouerned by Patriarkes and Arch bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops repreſenting the twelue Apoſtles, and by Biſhops repreſenting the Euangeliſts. Yea in the very Apoſtles daies, there were Biſhops which had vnder them inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Paſtours, as <hi>S. Iames</hi> Biſhop of <hi>leruſalem, S. Peter</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch, S. Paul</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome, S. Marke</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria:</hi> and if we will not beleeue the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3528:26"/>hiſtorie of the Primitiue Church, yet let vs beleeue the Epiſtles of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who enſtileth <hi>Timothie</hi> the Euangeliſt,
<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4. Tit. 3. 1. Tim. 5.22, Tit. 1 5,</note> the <hi>first Biſhop</hi> of the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> another Euangeliſt, <hi>first Biſhop</hi> of the Church of the <hi>Cretians,</hi> and teſtifieth that by vertue of their function, they did ordaine preſbyters or inferiour paſtours in thoſe Churches, for ordination argueth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtratiuely the ſuperioritie of the ordainer, and the inferioritie of the ordained,
<note place="margin">Act. 20, 17, 18 1. Tim. 3.1, 2, &amp;, 5.17, 19, Tit. 1 5.6, 7,</note> and without ſuch inequali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, their can bee neither ordination nor order. And though it be true that in the Scripture, the names of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and Preſbyter or Paſtour, be taken indifferently for one and the ſame office, yet that doth argue only that euery Paſtor or Preſbyter is and may bee called a Biſhop in reſpect of his people or pariſh, ouer which hee is placed, ſo that he may bee called a Biſhop aboue the Laitie, but it doth not argue that their were no ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Biſhops aboue thoſe Biſhops of the Laitie; to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, order and direct them, which were Biſhops of a more eminent degree, and diſtinct from the other; theſe Biſhops, Preſbyters and Paſtours aboue the <hi>Clergie,</hi> and thoſe Biſhops, Preſbyters and Paſtours aboue the <hi>Laitie,</hi> and conſequently inferiour vnto the former, wherefore I could wiſh that learned men would not leane ſo much as they doe, to that argument taken from the indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencie of thoſe two words <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the queſtion and controuerſie is not verball but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, for the queſtion is not, if all the Miniſters of the Church may be called by the common name of Paſtor, Preſbyter and Biſhop; but if all thoſe that are called by the common name, ought to bee of equall dignitie and authoritie? or whether or no there ought to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the multitude of Miniſters, ſome ſuperiours to gouerne, and ſome inferiours to be gouerned, for good orders ſake, and to bee called for diſtinctions ſake, by
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3528:26"/>different names, applying or appropriating the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon name of Biſhop to the ſuperiour, and the common name of Preſbyter, Prieſt or Paſtour to the inferiour? And truly in the time of my owne <hi>Puritaniſme</hi> and <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuiſme,</hi> I was wont to preſſe this verball argument aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as any man, to prooue thereby the paritie of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours; and there is not another argument to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe worth a pinne; but in the end I found it both falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and friuolous, for in the Scriptures, Kings, Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">Act. 6. Rom. 13, 4, 1. Cor. 4, 1. Coloſi. 1.25, 1. Theſſ. 3.2, 1. Tim. 3.8.12</note> Prophets, Euangeliſts, Paſtours and Deacous are called by the common name of <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Miniſters or ſeruants of God, and yet their Miniſtrations and ſeruices are not of the ſame nature, nor of equall dignitie, and the two names of <hi>preſbyter</hi> or <hi>elder</hi> beeing referred to office and not to age, and of <hi>Gouernour</hi> or <hi>Ruler</hi> or <hi>Ouerſeer,</hi> are conucrtible; for euery <hi>Elder</hi> is a <hi>Gouernour,</hi> and euery <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour</hi> is on <hi>Elder,</hi> and yet the <hi>Elderſhips</hi> and <hi>Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> are diſtinct;
<note place="margin">Numb. 11, 16.17, Ezra. 10.8, Luk. 22.66, Act. 20.17,</note> for ſome are called <hi>Lay-elders</hi> or <hi>elders</hi> of the <hi>people,</hi> to wit, in temporal matters, and thoſe were the Magiſtrates of the lewiſh Common-wealth, and others are called <hi>Elders</hi> of <hi>the Church,</hi> to wit Gouernours of the people, in ſpirituall matters; as Miniſters of the Word and Sacraments; ſo that both the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were Elders and Gouernours, and yet they were of different and diſtinct kindes, the one temporall Elders and Gouernours of the people, in the Common-weale, the other ſpirituall Elders and Gouernours of the ſame people in the Church; and ſemblably, theſe ſpiritual Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours of the Church and Miniſters of the word, both Biſhops and Preſbyters or Prieſts, are called by the common name of <hi>Preſbyters, Priests</hi> and <hi>Elders,</hi> and likewiſe by the common name of <hi>Epiſcopi, Biſhops, Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rintendents</hi> or <hi>Ouerſeers,</hi> and yet they differ both in the obiect of their office, and in their degree: for the one are cheife Prieſts &amp; Elders of the Church, and the other are
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3528:27"/>inferiour Prieſts and Elders of the ſame Church; the one are Biſhops, Superintendents and Ouerſeers of the Laitie or people in ſpirituall things, but the other are Biſhops, Superintendents and Ouerſeers of the Clergie, as well as of the Laitie; and of their inferiour prieſts and paſtours, aſwell as of the people in the ſame ſpirituall things. In a word, the Church of God being the beſt ordered Body that can be, behoued to conſiſt of <hi>Superiours</hi> to <hi>gouerne,</hi> and of <hi>Inferiours</hi> to bee <hi>gouerned,</hi> to wit, of theſe two rankes, <hi>Clergie</hi> and <hi>Laitte,</hi> and as the Laitie was to bee gouerned by the Clergie, as the children by the fathers, and ſchollers by their maſters; ſo the Clergie being a great multitude was to haue order and gouernement in it ſelfe, and therfore behoued to conſiſt of ſuperiours and inferiours likewiſe And to theſe ouerſeers of the Church were aſſigned different names and titles for diſtinctions ſake; the Ouerſeers or Rulers of the Church in the quarters of the world, were called <hi>Patriarkes,</hi> the Ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeer and Ruler of the Church of a whole kingdome was called a <hi>Primate,</hi> the Ouerſeers and Rulers of the Clergie or Church in the ſeuerall Prouinces of a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome were called <hi>Archbiſhops,</hi> and the Ouerſeers or Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the ſame Clergie in a dioceſſe or ſhiere, were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Biſhops,</hi> like as the Ouerſeers of the Laitie or people in a pariſh, were called <hi>Preſbyters, Priests</hi> or <hi>Pastours,</hi> for in the laſt Section of this worke; wherein we doe entreate more at large of the honourable titles and maintenance of the miniſterie, we ſhow likewiſe, how that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel, ought not to diſclaime the honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtile and title of Prieſts. Thus we ſee how that there muſt needs bee imparitie and inequalitie amongſt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, except wee meane to make them a multitude without order and gouernment, or elſe giue them from Geneua <hi>Lay-gouernours;</hi> for amongſt them, the Elders of the Church which bee lay men, being more in number
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3528:27"/>(to paſſe ouer their Lay-deacons) doe gouerne the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters beeing the ſmaller number; iudge and cenſure them, both in life and doctrine; and ſo are they well ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, becauſe they refuſed to bee gouerned by men of their owne order, to wit, by <hi>Biſhops,</hi> therefore God hath giuen them ouer to bee deluded, derided, debaſed, and diſhonoured by the Lay gouernment of thoſe whom they ought to gouerne and rule as the <hi>Shepheard</hi> his <hi>ſheepe,</hi> the <hi>father</hi> his <hi>children,</hi> the <hi>ſchoolemaster</hi> his <hi>ſchollers,</hi> for amongſt the Geneuians it is quite contrary, where the Lay-elders as being more in number, doe ouer-rule the Miniſters as hath beene ſaid. But thankes bee vnto Almighty God; for raiſing vp a <hi>Iacob</hi> from <hi>the North,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iſay. 41.8, 9, 25. Reuel. 1.20. &amp; 12.7</note> and calling him from the endes of the earth to doe him ſeruice in reſtoring of his Church in the North, to the ancient <hi>Angelicall</hi> forme, and in baniſhing out of it, the <hi>Graſhopper-gouernment</hi> of <hi>Geneua;</hi> and let all Britaines, <hi>North,</hi> and <hi>South,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Prouerb. 30.27.</note> euen as many as doe loue the likeneſſe of <hi>Ieruſalems Angels,</hi> better then of <hi>Geneuian Graſhoppers,</hi> ſay Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 16</head>
                     <p>Thirdly the Church of England is more like the Church in heauen for <hi>holineſſe,</hi> then the <hi>Geneuian</hi> is;
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>The Church of England more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen-like for holines.</hi> Iſay 6.1, 2, 3 Reul. 4. &amp; 5.8, 12.13. &amp; 7.15</note> for in heauen the Angels and bleſſed Spirits keepe euery day holy, inceſſantly praiſing God and ſaying, <hi>holy, holy, holy is the Lord of hostes, the whole world is full of his glory, ſo ſaith</hi> the euangelicall Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> in the old Teſtament, &amp; diuine <hi>S. Iohn</hi> in the new ſaith, that <hi>they ceaſe not day nor night to ſay and to ſing, holy, holy, holy, Lord God almighty, which was, and which is, and which is to come, &amp; that they ſerue him day and night in his Temple, ſaying, Praiſe and honour and glory and power, bee vnto him that ſitteth vpon the throne, and vnto the Lambe for euer more, and the foure ſaid Amen.</hi> Now the Church of England is farre holier then the <hi>Geneuian,</hi>
                        <pb n="38" facs="tcp:3528:28"/>becauſe the <hi>Geneuians</hi> are not ſo holy as the Iewes were, nor haue not ſo many <hi>holy dayes</hi> as they had: for beſides the two and fifty Sabbaths of the yeare,
<note place="margin">Exod. 12.14, 15, 16, 17, 18. &amp; 13.6.7. &amp; 20.8, 9, 10. &amp; 23.12, 14, 15, 16, 17. &amp; 38.18. Deut. 16. Eſter 9.17, 18, 19, 21, 26, 27, 28, 29. 30, 31. 1. Machab. 4.43, 44, 52, 53, 54, 55, 56, 57, 58, 59.</note> which are the Geneuian holy dayes, they had other holy dayes, and <hi>feſtiuities,</hi> which they did obſerue, as of the <hi>Paſſeouer,</hi> of the <hi>firſt fruites,</hi> of <hi>Tabernacles,</hi> and of <hi>Purim</hi> inſtituted by Queene <hi>Eſter</hi> and <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and of the dedication of the Altar, inſtituted by <hi>Machabaeus.</hi> But the Engliſh like good Chriſtians, which ſhould not come ſhort of the Iewes in doing of holy duties, but either match them or ſurmou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t them, haue beſides the two and fifty. Sundaies of the yeare, ſet apart to the performing of holy duties, about thirty holy daies more, in honour of God and of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt: and moreouer they haue in diuers places, as namely, in <hi>Cathedral</hi> Churches frequent holy aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, yea daily, for the holy ſeruice of God morning and euening, and in other <hi>Parochiall</hi> Churches, they haue ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſemblies for Gods ſeruice on <hi>Wodneſday, Friday,</hi> and <hi>Saturday,</hi> euery weeke throughout the yeare, and beſides theſe, they haue frequent holy aſſemblies on other daies of the weeke, vpon the religious occaſions of <hi>Chriſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, Weddings, Burials, Minde dayes, and Lectures,</hi> where the people pray and praiſe God, and heare the word of God read or expounded in a Sermon. So that if there be any holineſſe placed in praying vnto God, and in prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his name publikely in the congregation, a thing which no man that is in his right wits will deny, or if ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of life may bee holpen any whit by ſuch frequent aſſemblies and Sermons, it muſt needes follow that the Church of England hath more holineſſe then the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian, becauſe ſhee hath many more of ſuch holy aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies for ſeruice and ſermons, prayers and praiſes then the other hath. And that theſe were obſerued in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church within the firſt fiue hundreth yeares, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny holy daies beſides the <hi>Sunday,</hi> and euen the ſame that are at this day obſerued in England, wee ſhall prooue it
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3528:28"/>more particularly by alleadging the teſtimonies and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities of the Church Greekes and Latines in another worke called <hi>Dies Domini;</hi> which containeth diuers diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, and diſcourſes vpon the times of the worlds <hi>beginning, lasting, ending,</hi> according to the Scriptures, and the opinions of Hebrews, Greekes and Latines, Diuines, Philoſophers, Hiſtorians and Schoole-men; and in it we doe alſo entreate of the holy times of the Church. But becauſe that many do ſo miſconceiue of holy daies, as if they were onely fit for the <hi>Popes</hi> holineſſe, and for hypocrites, which is as damnable and deuilliſh opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion as euer hell hatcht in the diſgrace of true holineſſe, without which, the Apoſtle ſaith,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14.</note> no man ſhall euer ſee God; therefore let mee intreate and beſeech my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimen for the moſt holy Gods ſake, to aske them theſe few queſtions. Firſt, if the attaining of holineſſe, and the doing of religious duties be not the chiefe end of good Chriſtians in this life? which I hope will not bee denied. Secondly, if religious aſſemblies, and holy meetings bee not the proper meanes of attaining vnto true holineſſe? the which I take will be granted. Thirdly if the frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of ſuch holy aſſemblies, bee not in all likeli-hoode a more ready and eaſie meanes for men to attaine vnto holineſſe, and to doe religious duties, then the raritie thereof? in a word, which of the two is moſt likely, that a man ſhould attaine vnto true holineſſe by repairing vnto holy aſſemblies or places, often or ſeldome? and me thinkes no man that is in his good wits will deny, but that often repairing to the holy houſe of the moſt holy God, for the doing of holy duties, as to pray vnto God for our ſelues, and for others, to praiſe his name for bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites and bleſſings, ſpirituall and temporall, to ſing Pſalmes, to heare Gods word, and the Sermons of his ſeruants, and the like is a more direct meanes to attaine vnto holines, then ſeldome repairing as namely once in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3528:29"/>the weeke. Laſtly, I demaund, if it were not an excellent thing, and a happie condition, if men could ſet apart, a part of euery day in the yeare to Gods ſeruice, and to meete together in the holy Congregation, for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming of ſuch holy duties: and if the neceſſities of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane life will not let vs haue the leiſure to doe ſo, if at leaſt the next beſt is not to be done, which is to haue as many holy daies as poſſibly we can, and as better one then none, ſo better more, then one onely; and many then fewe: that ſo wee may the more neetely reſemble thoſe Church-members in heauen, which keepe euery day holy, according as we doe pray daylie, taught by our Lord, ſaying, <hi>Our Father which art in heauen, hallowed be thy name, thy Kingdome come, thy will be done in earth,</hi> (that is in the Church militant) <hi>as it is in heauen,</hi> or in the Church triumphant.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 17.</head>
                     <p>Fourthly, as the Church of England is more like the Church of God and Angels for heauenly holineſſe,
<note place="margin">The Church England more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen like for humble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence.</note> then the Geneuian is, ſo is ſhee more like the ſame in heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and humble reuerence, and in the expreſſion thereof by religious geſtures. In the Church of God and bleſſed ſpirits, the Angels and Saints are painted out, <hi>couering</hi> their <hi>faces, ſtanding</hi> before the throne, <hi>kneeling</hi> and <hi>falling</hi> before it on their faces, <hi>vncouering</hi> of their <hi>heads,</hi> and <hi>casting</hi> of their <hi>crownes</hi> before the throne, and moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſely <hi>worſhipping</hi> of God,
<note place="margin">Iſay. 6.1, 2, Ezech. 1.24, 25, &amp; 10, 3, 19 Dan. 7.9, 10, Zach. 6, 4, 5, Iob. 1.6, &amp; 2, 1. Reuel. 4, 10, &amp; 5, 8.14, &amp; 7, 1, 9, 10, 11, 12, &amp;, 8, 2.</note> as wee may reade in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies of <hi>Iſay, Ezechiel, Daniel, Zacharie,</hi> in the booke of <hi>Iob,</hi> and in the <hi>Reuelation</hi> of S. <hi>Iohn</hi> in many places: for <hi>S. Iohn beheld and ſaw a great multitude, which no man could number of all nations and kinreds, and people and tongues, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> (not ſitting) <hi>before the throne, and before the lambe, and ſaying with a loude voice, Saluation commeth of our God, that ſitteth vpon the throne, and of the lambe.</hi> And he ſaw all the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3528:29"/>
                        <hi>Angels</hi> likewiſe <hi>ſtanding</hi> round about the throne, and the <hi>Elders kneeling:</hi> yea <hi>falling</hi> before the ſame throne on their faces, and worſhipping God and ſaying; <hi>Amen, Praiſe and glorie, and wiſedome, and thankes, and honour, and power, and might be vnto our God for euermore, Amen.</hi> And in the Church of England anſwerably hereunto, the Preachers doe reuerently vncouer their heads, not only in praying, but alſo in preaching and expounding Gods words, and in the orations or ſermons, in honour of his name, like as thoſe holy Elders or Prieſts in heauen doe, which <hi>vncouer</hi> their <hi>heads,</hi> and caſt their crownes before the throne: whereas the Geneuians and French in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, do vnreuerently couer their heads, and not with a Church cap or bonnet (which were more tolerable) but with their ordinarie and vſual hats, more like millars or maltmen, then Gods Miniſters; though in <hi>Scotland</hi> I confeſſe they follow the godly and comely faſhion of England in preaching, with their heads vncouered, and not the capped cuſtome of Geneua: and God grant they may doe ſo in many other matters, where they haue as good reaſon, and namely in kneeling humbly, not only in making confeſſion of their ſinnes vnto God, but alſo at the repetition of the law of God, or ten commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as they doe in England, and in ſtanding vp reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently in making confeſſion of their faith, at the rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of the Creed, and at the reading of the Goſpell. The which geſtures are to bee vſed, both for reuerence and for ſignification; for reuerence becauſe their is no man ſo ignorant or blockiſh, but vnderſtandeth that <hi>kneeling</hi> and <hi>ſtanding vp</hi> are much more reuerent, humble and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectfull geſtures then <hi>ſitting,</hi> and therefore in the doing of ſuch religious duties to God wards, are to bee vſed. And for ſignification, becauſe that as by <hi>kneeling</hi> at the rehearſing of the law, wee doe profeſſe and confeſſe our miſerie and wretchedneſſe, occaſioned by the fall in the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3528:30"/>firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and doe humbly aske God mercie, for tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing his commandements; ſo by our <hi>ſtanding vp</hi> at the reading of the Goſpel, or rehearſing of the Creede, or articles of faith, we profeſſe and acknowledge that our riſing after the fall, and our ſtanding by Grace, were cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the ſecond Adam Chriſt. So that by theſe reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and ſignificant geſtures, wee doe put our ſelues in minde of the chiefe matters, that concerne ſaluation, we ſhow how that we ſtand in Gods fauour by faith, as alſo we declare and notifie, how that we ought to be alwaies ready to defend the faith. And truly the man that will not doe ſo much as ſtand vp reuerently vpon his feete, when the Miniſter maketh a publike confeſſion of faith in the name of the people, doth argue that his faith wan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth the feete of deuout affections, and ten to one, but it wanteth likewiſe the hands of charitable actions. He himſelfe loueth ſitting, and I feare me, leaſt his faith loue too much creeping or lying along vpon the ground, whereunto it is as it were tyed by the taile, ſo that hee can not minde heauenly matters. Moreouer in the Church of England, they vſe reuerently to <hi>vncouer</hi> their <hi>heads,</hi> and <hi>bowe</hi> or <hi>kneele</hi> at the naming of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> in reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of the holy Elders in heauen, which <hi>vncouer</hi> their <hi>heads,</hi> and bow before the <hi>Lambe Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> as ſaid is, and that both in imitation of the firſt Chriſtians, within the firſt fiue hundreth yeares, and becauſe the holy Apoſtle doth ioyne the bodily obeiſance of <hi>bowing</hi> or <hi>kneeling</hi> at the name of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> with the dutie of the tongues <hi>Confeſſing</hi> of his name: for writing to the Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians, thus he ſaith, <hi>Christ humbled himſelfe and became obedient vnto the death of the croſſe.
<note place="margin">Philip. 2, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> Wherefore God hath alſo highly exalted him, and giuen him a name aboue euery name, that at the name of Ieſus, ſhould euery knee bow, and that euery tongue ſhould confeſſe, that Ieſus Chriſt is the Lord vnto the glorie of God the Father.</hi> Chriſt this only Sonne
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3528:30"/>of God, had humbled himſelfe as man, for mans ſake below all men, and therefore God the father exalted him as man aboue all men,
<note place="margin">Heb. 2, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 1. Cor. 15, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 1. Tim. 6.15, Reuel. 17.14, &amp; 19, 16, &amp; 1, 5.</note> and made him the head and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, both of men and Angels, the King of kings, and Lord of lords bleſſed for euer, as the ſame Apoſtle otherwhere teacheth. And this his royal exaltation, all Chriſtians are bound to acknowledge, by <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of <hi>Tongue,</hi> and by the obeiſance or <hi>bowing</hi> of the <hi>body,</hi> and the <hi>vncouering</hi> of the <hi>head.</hi> And that it is a Chriſtian and a commendable cuſtome, I prooue it thus: All action or geſture, that declareth the ſubiection of the creature to Ieſus Chriſt, as the King of all mankinde, muſt needs be a Chriſtian and commendable geſture or action; But the bowing of the body or knee, and the vncouering of the head at the pronouncing of the name of Ieſus, are geſtures and actions declaring our ſubiection to Ieſus, as the King of mankinde, eſpecially of his Church, and therefore they are Chriſtian and commendable. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, it becommeth good Chriſtians to take all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions they can of performing Chriſtian duties; now it is a Chriſtian dutie, and one of the chiefeſt, to thanke God for the worke of our ſaluation, for louing vs ſo deerely; as that hee would giue his only begotten Son to bee our Sauiour, and to expreſſe our thankfulneſſe by ſome religious and reuerent geſture. Now what better occaſion can there bee offered of doing this duty, then when we heare that name pronounced, which ſignifieth a <hi>Sauiour,</hi> and putteth vs in minde of our <hi>Saluation,</hi> as the ringing of the bell putteth vs in minde of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to Church, and which is both his proper name, his royall name, and therefore to be ciuilly honoured, his diuineſt name, and therefore to be religiouſly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, and of all his other names the moſt comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to miſerable mankinde? In a word all Chriſtians are bound to honour, magnifie and bleſſe Gods name
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3528:31"/>at all times, in all places, and vpon all occaſions, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially and principally in the publike congregation, when we heare his principall and moſt maieſticall name pronounced, which is <hi>Ieſus,</hi> vnder the Goſpel to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, as <hi>Iehouah</hi> was vnder the law to lewes. Laſtly, to conclude this point of the Engliſh Churches Reuerence, I ſay that it appeareth yet more, in their religious ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture vſed in receiuing the holy Sacrament, which they doe not <hi>ſtanding,</hi> as at ſome hunters breakfaſt with the <hi>French,</hi> nor <hi>ſitting</hi> as an ordinary ſupper with the <hi>Scottiſh,</hi> but humbly <hi>kneeling</hi> and <hi>bowing</hi> vpon their knee as Gods humble gueſts, acknowledging themſelues vnworthy to ſtand or ſit downe at his Table, ſo long as we are in this life loaden with ſin, and doe want the wedding garment, of ſuch perfit and inherent righteouſneſſe as wee ſhall haue in the kingdome of heauen; where wee ſhall haue the honour to ſit downe with the Lambe at Gods board: for then wee ſhall bee made his glorified gueſts, when wee ſhall bee fully freed from ſinne,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 19.7, 8, 9. Mat. 15.22, 23 24, 25, 26, 27 &amp; 22, 11, 12,</note> and arraied in the <hi>white robes</hi> of inherent righteouſneſſe, as it is in the <hi>Reuelation.</hi> Whereas ſo long as wee are here vpon earth, we cannot for our life, quite caſt off old <hi>Adams</hi> skinne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coate of origin all corruption, nor yet put off perfitly the rotten ragges of actuall vnrighteouſneſſe; which makes vs with the <hi>Cananite</hi> to creepe (as it were) vnder Chriſts Table, and to be content for the time of this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full life to gather vp the crummes. But becauſe that our <hi>Geneuits</hi> for all that, are diſpoſed to be as bold &amp; homely at the <hi>Board</hi> of <hi>heauen,</hi> as they are in their owne houſes, &amp; do condemne this reuerent geſture of <hi>kneeling,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I muſt intreat my deere Countrey-men to giue me leaue to aske them a few queſtions. And firſt, if it be not only lawfull, but alſo conuenient and neceſſary to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Sacrament with the greateſt reuerence and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie that can be, and I thinke it will not bee denied?
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3528:31"/>Secondly, if it bee not lawfull, yea conuenient and nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſarie to vſe ſome one externall geſture or other in recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the Sacrament, which I take will alſo be graunted? Thirdly, if it be not onely lawfull, but alſo conuenient and almoſt neceſſarie to vſe that geſture which doth moſt ſignifie and declare, and vſually accompanie the greateſt humilitie and reuerence? and what other geſture can this bee but <hi>kneeling,</hi> which is more reuerent then <hi>standing,</hi> like as this is more reuerent then <hi>ſitting?</hi> and therefore <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> ſawe the foure and twenty Elders firſt <hi>ſitting</hi> vpon ſeates, then <hi>riſing</hi> and <hi>standing,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Reuel. 4.4, 10. &amp; 5.6, 7, 8, 14</note> and after that <hi>falling</hi> downe or <hi>kneeling</hi> before the <hi>Lambe,</hi> in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation whereof, all good Chriſtians ought to kneele be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the holy Lambe, when they receiue his bleſſed bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy as it were, out of his owne heauenly hands, for the ſpirituall foode of their ſoules, which do aſſuredly feede vpon his fleſh by faith in a myſticall, ſpirituall, and ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall manner. Againe, I aske of our Geneuites, if it be not lawfull to thanke God in receiuing of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thanksgiuing which I thinke wil not be denied? In the next place I aske if it bee not lawfull to vſe in our thanksgiuing, the geſture that the ſeruants of God haue alwaies vſed in their other religious thanksgiuings? and if not, why ſhall that geſture which is lawfull in all other religious thanksgiuings, bee vnlawfull in this? and if it be lawfull in this aſwell as in all other then let them ſhew me what other geſture it was but <hi>kneeling?</hi> and if <hi>kneeling</hi> be the fitteſt geſture for the expreſſing of a moſt humble thanksgiuing, ſuch as we ſhould offer vnto God in this Sacrament of <hi>thanksgiuing,</hi> then why doe we not <hi>kneele</hi> with the Church of England, rather then <hi>ſitte,</hi> or <hi>stand</hi> after the homely, yea vnholy and vnhumble manner of Geneua.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="section">
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:3528:32"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 18.</head>
                     <p>Fifthly,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>The Church of England more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen-like for harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie.</hi> Reuel. 5.8, 9. &amp; 14.2, 3. &amp; 15.2, 3, 4. &amp; 19.</note> the Church of England is more like the Church of God in heauen, for heauenly <hi>harmonie,</hi> then the Geneuian is; for in Gods Church in heauen, thoſe holy and vnſpotted Prieſts are painted out in ſeauen or eight places of the Reuelation, <hi>ſinging new ſongs</hi> vnto God in moſt melodious manner, both with voices and <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and namely with <hi>Harpes:</hi> and anſwerable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto in the Engliſh Church wee haue the harmonious conſort and muſicall concord of voices and inſtruments, eſpecially of <hi>Organes</hi> in the praiſing of God with <hi>Hymnes, Pſalmes</hi> and <hi>ſongs.</hi> The which kinde of muſicall inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment beeing as it were animated with the melodie of Singing-mens voices, doth moſt of all other repreſent that which <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> heard in heauen, like a <hi>voyce of a great multitude,</hi> and <hi>as the voyce of many waters,</hi> and as <hi>the voyce of ſtrong thundrings ſaying and ſinging,</hi> HALLELVIAH. Of the which my ſticall muſicke, I ſhall (God willing) deliuer many notable conſiderations, and moſt comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Contemplations in our worke called <hi>Dies Domini.</hi> And there I ſhal prooue both by Scriptures and Fathers authoritie, and by irrefragable reaſons euidencie, the lawfulneſſe and commendableneſſe of the muſicall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of voyces and inſtruments in the ſeruice of God; and that the alternatiue Church ſinging of the <hi>Quire,</hi> diuided into two parts, is conformable vnto the manner of the heauenly Churches muſicke, as may be gathered out of the prophecie of <hi>Iſay,</hi> who in his viſion of the maieſtie of God and his glorious <hi>Seraphims,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iſay. 6.1, 2, 3,</note> ſaith <hi>that one cryed to another and ſaid, holy, holy, holy, is the Lord of Hoſtes, the whole world is full of his glory.</hi> And truley the Doctours of the Church, and other eccleſiaſticall writers doe witneſſe in expreſſe words, as ſhall be ſhewed in our ſaid worke, that the firſt Chriſtians were wont to ſitte one for
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3528:32"/>againſt another, as wee ſee they doe now adaies in the <hi>Quire,</hi> and to inuite or cohort alternatiuely or by turnes, one another to the praiſing of God, by ſinging of Pſalmes. So that I cannot but wonder how our <hi>Geneui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> can ſay any thing againſt ſo auncient and chriſtian a cuſtome, or yet againſt the vſing of ſome inſtruments in the ſinging of <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> eſpecially when as the word Pſalme doth ſignifie either the melodie of the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Organ alone, or elſe the harmonie of the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall noiſe and the muſicall voice going together; ſo that indeed there cannot be a <hi>Pſalme,</hi> there may well be a <hi>Song</hi> without an inſtruments ſound, and if we haue our <hi>Pſalmes</hi> originally from <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and not from <hi>Rome,</hi> from the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> and not from the <hi>Pope,</hi> why may we not with the ſame <hi>Dauid</hi> vſe in ſtruments and organes, eſpecially when as the Spirit of God by him exhorteth men thereunto, ſo often in the ſame Booke of the Pſalmes, which wee reade and ſing euery day, in our Churches? yea with ſuch an exhortation hee ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vp his Pſalmes, ſaying, <hi>Praiſe ye him with Virginals and Organes.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 150.4. 1. Cor. 14, 26 Epheſ. 5.18, 19, 20, Coloſſ. 3.16.</note> And that we might know that the praiſing of God vpon inſtruments, was not a meere lewiſh Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonie, and to laſt only vntill the comming of Chriſt, and no longer; the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> ſheweth that the Chriſtians in his time, in their aſſemblies, were wont to <hi>ſing Pſalmes,</hi> that is to ſay, to ioyne the melodie of inſtruments with ſpirituall hymnes and ſongs, for ſomuch doth the word <hi>Pſalme</hi> in Greeke ſignifie: and therefore the ſame Apoſtle diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed betweene <hi>Pſalmes</hi> and <hi>Songs,</hi> both in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> and in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> where hee exhorteth the faithfull to the melodious ſinging of <hi>Pſalmes, Hymnes</hi> and <hi>Spirituall Songs.</hi> But if neither the example of king <hi>Dauid</hi> and the Church of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> both in King <hi>Dauids</hi> time and Saint <hi>Iames</hi> the firſt <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi>
                        <pb n="48" facs="tcp:3528:33"/>thereof, nor the practiſe of the Primitiue Church within the firſt 500. yeares, can induce vs to a liking of this kinde of Church muſicke and of <hi>Organs</hi> melody; yet let this mooue vs to like it, that the <hi>Pope</hi> doth diſlike it, for otherwiſe hee would not want <hi>Organs</hi> in his <hi>chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> as he doth, whereof I gather this new argument in fauour of <hi>Organs,</hi> at leaſt for the Kings Chappell. If it be fit that our <hi>Kings Chappell,</hi> bee vnlike vnto the <hi>Popes,</hi> then is it fit that their bee <hi>Organs</hi> in our Kings Chappel, for there are none in the Popes; but the former is fit at leaſt in the opinion of <hi>Puritaines</hi> and <hi>Preciſians,</hi> which would faine, wee were vnlike the Pope in each indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent thing, and therefore the latter is fit likewiſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 19.</head>
                     <p>Sixtly,
<note place="margin">The Church of England more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen-like for habite.</note> as the Engliſh Church, is more heauenly for harmonie, and therein reſembleth neerer the Church of God and Angels, then the Geneuian doth, ſo is ſhee more heauenly, for <hi>habite.</hi> The miniſters of the trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Church, euen thoſe bleſſed ſpirits, that doe offer vp inceſſantly the ſweet incenſe and ſacrifice of praiſe vnto God, are ſaid to bee ſuted in <hi>pure white linnen,</hi> as wee may reade in the <hi>Reuelation</hi> in ſome ten or eleuen places in ſixe ſeuerall chapters,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 3.4, 5.18, &amp; 4, 4, &amp; 6, 11, &amp; 7, 9, 13, 14, &amp; 15, 6, &amp; 19, 8, 14, Dan. 10.5, &amp; 12.6, Ezech. 9.2.3, Mat. 28.1, 2.3 Mark. 16.5, Iohn 20, 12</note> beſides that the Angels when euer they aſſumed humane ſhapes, alwaies appeared in <hi>white,</hi> as we may reade often, both in the old and new Teſtament. For this colour hath beene in all ages, and in all Churches thought the moſt comely, and conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to bee vſed in the doing of diuine ſeruice, and the moſt ſutable to ſanctitie puritie and glorie. Anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly whereunto in the Church of England, our Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall miniſters, when they doe diuine ſeruice, or cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the Sacraments both for diſtinction and decencie, and likewiſe for a ſignification of puritie and ſanctitie, doe put on a <hi>white linnen garment</hi> commonly called a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3528:33"/>Surpliſſe, and the Biſhop beareth and weareth a <hi>white Rotchet;</hi> where as our Geneuians are all for Baals and Beelzebubs <hi>blacke,</hi> and had rather bee in habite like hell then heauen, rather like the Angels of the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe pit, which dwell in darkeneſſe, and whoſe loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome liuerie is <hi>blackeneſſe,</hi> then like the Angels of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, which dwell in brightneſſe, and whoſe liuerie is <hi>light,</hi> and <hi>whiter</hi> then the fineſt and pureſt laune. But, <hi>white,</hi> ſay they, muſt bee abandoned, becauſe it hath bin abuſed in <hi>Poperie;</hi> and by the like reaſon, <hi>blacke</hi> ſhould be forborne becauſe <hi>Baals</hi> prieſts haue abuſed it to ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, and had the name of <hi>Chemarims,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2. King. 23.5, Hoſ. 10.5.</note> becauſe they wore <hi>blacke garments,</hi> or <hi>Goneuagownes</hi> in their miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, witneſſe the very Geneua note it ſelfe vpon the place marked in the margine. But it is a thing reſolued amongſt all the iudicious and wiſe, that the abuſe of a thing, doth not take away the right vſe thereof, and that the children of the Church are not tied to bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like vnto the very enemies of it,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 13.11.</note> and idolaters in euery thing. For wee may reade in the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> how that Chriſt and Antichriſt are to reſemble one another in ſome things; for the Beaſt is ſaid to haue two hornes like vnto the Lambe.
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.13 14, 15. Mat. 7 15, &amp;. 10, 16.</note> And <hi>S. Paul</hi> vnto the <hi>Corinthians</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs that Sathan will be like vnto the Angels of light in ſome things, and his falſe Apoſtles and Miniſters, will be like vnto the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt: and in the Goſpell of <hi>S. Matthew,</hi> the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt are likened to ſheepe, and the very falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets will bee like them in ſomethings, for they come in ſheepes cloathing. So that both Goſpell and Epiſtle beſides propheſie, may teach the Miniſters of Chriſt, not to forſake their owne liuerie, which is <hi>white,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they reſemble God and his Angels, and the bleſſed ſpirits, becauſe that others perhaps doe abuſe it; yea ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe that ſome doe ſo, the Miniſters of Chriſt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3528:34"/>ought to vſe it ſtill, to the end that by their example ſuch as doe abuſe it, may be brought to vſe it aright, and ſo ſhould we doe in other ceremonies of the like nature.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 20.</head>
                     <p>Seuenthly,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>The Church of England more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen-like for locall decencie Churchim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements conuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruice ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cramentall ceremony.</hi> Reuelat. 3.12 &amp; 7.15, &amp; 11 1, 2, 19, &amp; 14, 15, 17, &amp; 15, 5, 6, 8, &amp; 16, 1, 7, 17, &amp; 21, Pſal. 45, 13, 14 Iſay 60, 13, 17. Reuel. 4.1. 2, 3, 4, 5, 9, 10, &amp; 5, 1, 6, 7, 11 13.</note> the Church of England is liker the Church that is in heauen then the Geneuian is, in <hi>locall decencie, Church-implements conueniencie,</hi> in <hi>Church-ſeruice ſolemnitie,</hi> and in <hi>ſacramentall ceremonie.</hi> And this is true, whether we looke vnto the coſtlineſſe and comelineſſe of the Churches of England, which are much liker that ſtately <hi>Temple</hi> and glorious <hi>golden citie new Ieruſalem</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> then are the baſe contemptible buildings after the Geneuian forme. For wee muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how that though the Church bee all glorious within, yet all her glorie is not within, but a good part of it is without, or to be ſeene and diſcerned by the eye, as the royall Prophet teacheth, and the Euangelicall Prophet teſtifieth, foretelling that God was to haue his houſe and the place of his feete amongſt Chriſtians, to be glorious both for matter and manner, ſtructure and furniture. Or whether we looke more particularly vnto the ſplendour and magnificence of the <hi>Kings Chappel,</hi> much like vnto that ſtately <hi>Throne</hi> which bleſſed <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſaw, ſet in heauen for the almightie King to ſit on, or yet of the <hi>Cathedrall</hi> Churches, the <hi>Seas</hi> of the reuerend Biſhops, much like vnto thoſe foure and twentie ſeates round about the throne, whereon the foure and twentie Princely and Prieſtly Elders doe ſit: or whether wee looke vnto the conueniencie of the ſeates of the <hi>Quire</hi> in each <hi>Cathedrall</hi> Church, appointed for the <hi>holy ſinging men</hi> to ſit in; who like vnto thoſe <hi>holy Elders,</hi> and the <hi>yonger Quiriſters,</hi> againe, like vnto thoſe <hi>Harping <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines,</hi> which follow the <hi>Lambe,</hi> and doe ſing moſt ſweetly before the <hi>throne</hi> and the <hi>Elders,</hi> both ioyning their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodious
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3528:34"/>voices together make a ſweete conſort, and ſend forth Pſalmes and Songs of praiſe vnto him that ſitteth vpon the throne, and vnto the Lambe, to bee lauded for euermore. And as the <hi>hearts</hi> of theſe our <hi>ſinging Elders,</hi> and <hi>Virgin-yongers,</hi> are like thoſe <hi>Harpes</hi> of God, which <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> ſaw in the hands of the <hi>Elders</hi> and <hi>yongers</hi> in <hi>heauen;</hi> ſo the holy, heauenly and harmonious <hi>anthemes</hi> and accents of theſe <hi>Harpes</hi> or <hi>Hearts,</hi> beeing ſtrung and tuned by Gods owne finger, conioyned with the muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and artificial thunder of our <hi>Church-organes,</hi> do moſt reſemble the heauenly harmonie which <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> heard as the ſound of <hi>many waters,</hi> and as the <hi>ſound of ſtrong thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derings,</hi> and as the <hi>voice of harpes, harping with their harpes,</hi> and ſinging and ſaying, HALLELVIAH; the which kinde of harmonie ſuch Geneuian eares as can not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure heere on earth, had beſt to ſtay ſtill about the brinkes of the Lemannian lake, and hold as farre from heauen, as they poſſibly can: for what a gods name ſhould they doe in heauen, except they loued <hi>heauens harmonie,</hi> euen our Churches muſicall melodie, better then they doe? And as our comely Churches doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the corners, courts and chambers of the ſtately Temple, that <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> ſaw opened in heauen, our <hi>Kings Chappel,</hi> the heauenly Kings <hi>throne,</hi> our <hi>Cathedrall Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> thoſe Princely and Prieſtly <hi>Elders ſeates,</hi> our harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious <hi>Organes,</hi> thoſe heauenly <hi>harpes</hi> which <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> ſaw in the hands of thoſe skilfull <hi>Quiriſters</hi> ſome like olde men, and ſome like yong boyes, and ſo well reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by ours, and as our <hi>Quiristers Pſalmes and Songs,</hi> doe reſemble their <hi>new ſongs,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Reuelat. 8. &amp;, 9. &amp;, 10, 5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8</note> and as they are moſt like one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in their <hi>white habites,</hi> &amp; heauenly HALLELVIAHS, ſo doe our <hi>Church-belles</hi> and <hi>chimes</hi> reſemble thoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall <hi>trumpets</hi> and <hi>thunders</hi> ſeauen in number, which bleſſed <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> heard, our <hi>Church-Bible</hi> anſwereth to that great <hi>ſealed Booke,</hi> our <hi>Seruice</hi> and <hi>Pſalme-booke</hi> to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3528:35"/>that <hi>little opened booke,</hi> our <hi>Euangelicall Priests</hi> reading of the Bible to the <hi>Lambes reading,</hi> and <hi>vnſealing</hi> of that <hi>ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Booke,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Reuela. 1.2.8 9, 11, &amp; 14, 1 6.7, &amp; 21, 14, &amp; 22, 1, 3,</note> our <hi>Church angelspreaching</hi> of the Goſpel, to the <hi>Preaching of Angels</hi> which <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> heard, the <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit</hi> anſwereth to <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> whereon he ſaw the <hi>Lambe</hi> ſtanding, or rather to that <hi>Tree</hi> of life, bearing twelue manner of fruites; for from thence the word of life is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linered by the learned and reuerend Biſhops, as it were from the mouth of the <hi>Lambes,</hi> twelue Apoſtles, twelue times in the yeare, the firſt Lords day of euery moneth. To be briefe our <hi>Church-font</hi> with <hi>Holy-water</hi> for the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> doth anſwer vnto that <hi>glaſſie Sea</hi> or <hi>riuer</hi> of <hi>water of life</hi> cleere as chriſtall proceeding out of the throne of God, &amp; of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> our <hi>Euangelical Prieſts Croſſe-ſiguing</hi> the baptized on the <hi>fore-head,</hi> and our <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall Biſhops ſealing</hi> and confirming of the <hi>Virgin ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants</hi> of our God (which by Baptiſme had beene bathed and waſhed,
<note place="margin">Reuela. 4.6. &amp; 6.9, &amp;. 7, 2, 3.4, &amp; 14, 1, 2, 3, 4.</note> and ſo made fit to follow the Lambe) doe anſwer vnto the <hi>Angels ſigning</hi> and <hi>ſealing</hi> of the <hi>Seruants</hi> of God on the <hi>fore-head;</hi> our <hi>Sacrament all holy bread</hi> of life, anſwereth to that <hi>hidden Manna</hi> of heauen, promiſed to him that ouercommeth; our <hi>Lords ſupper</hi> to the <hi>Lambes ſupper;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Reuela. 2.17. &amp; 6.9, &amp; 8, 3, 4, 5, &amp; 19, 13 &amp; 11, 1, 19, &amp; 19, 9.</note> our <hi>Church golden and ſiluer Baſons</hi> and <hi>Cuppes</hi> for the miniſtration of the holy Sacrament, to the <hi>Angels golden Cenſer;</hi> and our <hi>Church, Table</hi> for the miniſtration and celebration of the ſame Sacrament, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth vnto the <hi>Golden Altar</hi> which <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> ſawe before Gods throne. And who can ſay otherwiſe but that a <hi>Font</hi> and a <hi>Church-Table</hi> are two implements or inſtruments, as requiſite to be in enery Church for the miniſtration of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> as a <hi>Pulpit</hi> is requiſite for the delinerie of <hi>Sermons,</hi> and for the reading and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the word. And thus haue I made it apparent, to all ſuch as haue but common ſenſe and vnderſtanding, that the Church of England is much and many degrees
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3528:35"/>liker then the Geneuian, to the Church that <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> ſaw in heauen: ſo that as many of vs as doe loue heauen, cannot but exceedingly like the forme of the Engliſh Church, and better then that of Geneua: and wee may well ſay it, that the forme of the Church of England, and not that of Geneua, was reuealed and repreſented to our diuine Prophet. For the Reuelation containeth a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall repreſentation of the Church of Chriſt, and of the forme and conſtitution thereof, ſuch as it was to bee after our Sauiours aſcenſion in the two times of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution and peace, vntill his laſt comming to iudgement, to confound his foes, and to glorifie his friends and elect children; as I doe ſhew more particularly in another worke in Latine, entreating of the perſecution and peace of the militant Church, according to the holy prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of <hi>Daniel and Saint Iohn,</hi> a booke that I began at the age of nineteene yeares: wherein all the opinions of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and moderne writers, and euen of the learned of both Religions, touching the authors, inſtruments, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, beginning, manner and ending of the perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or troubles, and of the tranquillity and peace of the Church are propounded and compared together, with their reaſons and arguments debated, and many errours refuted. Now becauſe I haue ſaid in this Section, that the Church of England is liker to the Church of God in heauen (in the matter of ſacramentall or ſymbolicall ceremony) then the Geneuian is, and haue giuen an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance thereof in their <hi>Signing</hi> of Chriſts new-borne babes on the <hi>fore-head</hi> with the <hi>ſigne</hi> of the <hi>Croſſe</hi> in <hi>Baptiſme,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ezech. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. Reuelat. 7.1, 2 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</note> like as the <hi>Angels</hi> in heauen are ſaid in <hi>Ezekiel</hi> to <hi>ſigne</hi> them that ſorrow and mourne, vpon the <hi>fore thead</hi> with the <hi>Croſſe-like</hi> letter <hi>Thau,</hi> and in the Reuelation of <hi>Saint Iohn,</hi> to <hi>ſigne</hi> the <hi>fore-heads</hi> of Gods ſeruants with the ſeale of God. I haue thought good to inſiſt a little longer vpon the matter of this ceremony, and to prooue
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3528:36"/>the lawfull, commendable, and Chriſtian vſe of it, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny arguments, and euen ſome new ones of our owne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation. Our firſt argument is thus: both the Prophet, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> in the old Teſtament, and the Prophet <hi>S. Iohn</hi> in the new, haue propheſied of the conuerſion of the Iewes to the faith of Chriſt, by the <hi>Angels ſigning</hi> of them in the <hi>fore-head,</hi> as the letter of the word doth beare in both places, the which the auncient Doctours of the Church haue vnderſtood of the <hi>Signe</hi> of the <hi>Croſſe</hi> to be receiued at the hands of the Church in their <hi>Baptiſme;</hi> as no diuine that euer read the Fathers, dare deny: whereby they ſhall profeſſe that they are no more aſhamed of his <hi>Croſſe,</hi> or ſcandalized at the ignominie of it as their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers had beene,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.23.</note> to whom it prooued a <hi>stumbling block,</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) but that they glorie in it, and beleeue to be made bleſſed by it, euen to bee ſaued by Chriſts ſuffering on that ſame <hi>Croſſe,</hi> which their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers had once ſet vp to ſlay and deſtroy him by. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if our Geneuians would haue the Iewes to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to their Church, they muſt needes receiue from England, or rather from the primitiue Church, the ſacred ſigne of the croſſe, that they may haue it to chriſten the Iewes with; otherwiſe they will not goe to <hi>Geneua</hi> for Chriſtendome, nor to <hi>Scotland</hi> neither, nor to any refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Church of their faſhion. Secondly, in all reaſon and common ſenſe, it is conuenient that the Iewes beeing conuerted, ſhould declare by ſome ſenſible ſigne, that they are no more aſhamed of Chriſls croſſe, but well aſhamed of their owne curſed courſe in crucifying him, that came to cure them; and though there were not any mention at all made in holy Scripture, of their <hi>ſigning</hi> or <hi>ſealing</hi> in the <hi>foreshead</hi> (as there is moſt expreſſely) yet ſhould it bee lawfull for them to declare by ſome exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall geſture or act, aſwell as by words of mouth, their Chriſtian diſpoſition of this kinde. Thirdly, as it ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3528:36"/>much to the glory of God, in that he can bring light out of darkeneſſe, life out of death, ſaluation out of deſtruction, nobilitie and fame out of ignominy and ſhame, and honour, out of diſhonour, ſo it tendeth to the edification of the Church, that this admirable working of our moſt glorious and wiſe God, bee declared and made as notorious as it can be, with all conueniencie, both by words of profeſſion and geſtures of ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and conſequently it tendeth to the edification of the Church, that the Iewes ſhould declare by the ſigne of the croſſe, that they doe acknowledge God to haue drawen admirably bleſſing and honour, out of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonour and curſe of the croſſe, and ſaluation out of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. It is a moſt Chriſtian confeſſion for Iew or Gentile, eſpecially the Iew, to confeſſe and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that the Croſſe which they once ſet vp with their hands in diſhonour of Chriſt, yea more for an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his deſtruction, Almightie God hath made it the in ſtrument of their higheſt honour, and happieſt condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, euen of their ſaluation; and therefore the outward expreſſion of this confeſſion by a geſture,
<note place="margin">Mat. 28, 18, 19</note> externall act or ſigne of the hands, muſt needs be Chriſtian and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable. Fourthly, our Sauiour Chriſt commanding to <hi>teach</hi> and <hi>baptize</hi> both Iewes and Gentiles, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth queſtionleſſe to expreſſe and declare the nature and vſe of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and conſequently commandeth to vſe the <hi>ſigne</hi> of the <hi>croſſe,</hi> for this ceremonie ſerueth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the nature and vſe of this Sacrament, in that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee are baptized into the death of Chriſt vpon the croſſe, and that our olde man is crucified with him, and euen nailed to his croſſe, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh ſaying,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.4, 5, 6 7, 8, Philip. 2.8, Coloſſ. 2.12, Galat. 2, 19, &amp; 5, 24.</note> 
                        <hi>Know ye not that all we which haue bin baptized into Ieſus Chriſt, haue beene baptized into his death? we are buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed then with him by Baptiſme, into his death, that like as Chriſt was raiſed vp from the dead by the glory of the father, ſo wee
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3528:37"/>alſo ſhould walke in newneſſe of life, For if wee be planted with him to the ſimilitude of his death, euen ſo ſhall wee bee to the ſimi-litude of his reſurrection, knowing this that our olde man is crucified with him, that the body of ſinne might bee deſtroyed.</hi> Whereby wee are taught that in <hi>Baptiſme</hi> their muſt bee a three-folde ſimilitude or repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to wit of Chriſts <hi>dying, burying</hi> and <hi>riſing</hi> bodily and of our <hi>dying, burying</hi> and <hi>riſing</hi> ſpiritually with him. Now I aske what ſimilitude there is in <hi>Baptiſme</hi> of Chriſts ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominous <hi>death</hi> vpon the croſſe, or of his bodily <hi>crucify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and of the ſpirituall <hi>crucifying</hi> of our old man with him, ſetting aſide the <hi>ſigne</hi> of the <hi>croſſe?</hi> The <hi>ſprinkling</hi> on of the water doth repreſent only a <hi>ſhedding</hi> of his blood, but not neceſſarily a ſhedding of it vntill death, for Chriſt might haue ſhed his blood without dying. And as for the <hi>immerſion</hi> or <hi>dipping</hi> of the baptized body into the water, it doth repreſent his <hi>burying</hi> directly, like as the <hi>emerſion</hi> or <hi>riſing</hi> of the body out of the water, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth his <hi>riſing</hi> out of the graue, but it doth not direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repreſent his <hi>dying:</hi> and though it doth by way of conſequence repreſent his death, in reſpect that ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily none are buried but the dead, yet it doth not for all that ſet before our eyes the kinde of his death, nor yet the accurſed and ignominious manner thereof, which are two circumſtances of eſpeciall moment and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. For our Sauiours death, was not a natural death; for he died not in his bed (as we ſay) and ſo was buried, but the death that hee died was a violent death and wrought by the hand of man. Neither was it an eaſie or an honeſt violent death, but the moſt painefull and ſhamefull of all other, and euen an accurſed death, as both in the law, and in the Epiſtle of the Goſpell wee are taught: all which circumſtances are repreſented and ſet before our eyes only by this ceremonie of the <hi>ſigne</hi> of the <hi>croſſe.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Deut. 2.23. Gal. 3.13.</note> Fifthly, if it be lawfull for a Miniſter to expreſſe
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3528:37"/>the myſteries and meaning of the Scripture of God by a <hi>Sermon,</hi> as euery one will grant that it is; then ſhall it bee as lawfull to expreſſe the myſteries of Gods Sacrament by a <hi>ceremonie:</hi> for there is the like reaſon, for the one and for the other. For ſeeing the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of God, aſwell as the <hi>word</hi> of God hath ſomething to bee explicated and declared, and that the beſt explication and declaration is made by things of the like nature, it followeth that as the <hi>audible word</hi> is explicated and declared by a <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> and by words to the eare, ſo the <hi>viſible Sacrament</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ceremonie, is to be explicated and declared by a <hi>ceremonie</hi> to the eye, ſuch as is the <hi>ſigne</hi> of the <hi>croſſe:</hi> hee that addeth vnto <hi>word</hi> or <hi>Sacrament</hi> for <hi>perfection</hi> is a blaſphemer and a deceiuer, but hee that addeth vnto <hi>word</hi> or <hi>Sacrament,</hi> either other words and rites for <hi>expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> and <hi>declaration</hi> is a true Doctor. Sixtly, by this ſigne the Church doth confeſſe her owne miſerie and wretchedneſſe, in that wee did euen crucifie Chriſt with our ſinful hands by our ſinnes, as much as the Iewes did that ſet vp the croſſe with their vnhallowed hands; this confeſſion is lawfull and good, and therefore the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of it by a ſenſible ſigne, can not be vnlawfvll or euill. Seauenthly,
<note place="margin">Galat. 3.13. Epheſ. 2.14.15, 16, 17,</note> by this ſigne the Church confeſſeth her faith in Chriſt crucified, that hee hath redeemed vs from the <hi>curſe</hi> of the <hi>law</hi> by the <hi>curſe</hi> of his <hi>croſſe,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled vs vnto God by the bleſſed peace of his <hi>croſſe,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh; this confeſſion is Chriſtian, and therefore the declaration thereof by a ſenſible ſigne, externall act or geſture of the bodie cannot bee Antichriſtian, as our Geneuians would haue vs to beleeue. Eightly, by this ſigne the Church decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth her Chriſtian diſpoſition and reſolution, of figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vnder the banner of Chriſt againſt ſinne and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and of <hi>ſuffering perſecution for the croſſe of Christ</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) ſhee declareth her Chriſtian en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3528:38"/>in <hi>crucifying the fleſh with the affections and lusts thereof,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Galat. 5.24, &amp; 6, 12, 14,</note> and teſtifieth her faithfull affection, in not being aſhamed of the croſſe of Chriſt, but that ſhee glorieth and reioyceth in it, according to that of the Apoſtle. <hi>God forbid that I ſhould reioyce,
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.39. Mark 14.35. Act. 7.60. &amp; 9.40. &amp;. 20.36. Epheſ. 3.14. Luk. 18.13. Mat. 14.19. Ioh. 11.41. &amp; 17.1. 1. Tim. 2.8. 1. Cor. 11.4.</note> but in the croſſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, whereby the world is crucified vnto mee, and I vnto the world.</hi> This diſpoſition, reſolution, endeuour and affection, is moſt commendable and Chriſtian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, and therefore the teſtification, declaration or notification thereof, muſt needs be ſo likewiſe. For if it be lawfull and laudable for the Church to declare the inward <hi>humilitie</hi> of the <hi>heart,</hi> by the outward <hi>bowing</hi> of the <hi>body</hi> or <hi>knees;</hi> and the <hi>casting downe</hi> of the <hi>eyes,</hi> the inward <hi>ſorrow</hi> of the <hi>ſoule</hi> for ſinne, by an externall <hi>beating</hi> of the <hi>breast;</hi> the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>confidence</hi> or <hi>affiance</hi> in God, in expecting at his hands, euery good thing, by the viſible <hi>lifting vp</hi> of the <hi>hands</hi> and <hi>eyes</hi> vnto heauen; and finally the internall <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence</hi> of the <hi>heart,</hi> by an externall <hi>bare head:</hi> why may not the ſame Church aſwell declare the inward <hi>reioycing</hi> and <hi>glorying</hi> of the <hi>heart</hi> in the <hi>croſſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by ſuch a <hi>ſenſible ſigne</hi> made with the <hi>hands,</hi> eſpecially it being made with the hands of the Miniſter, who is the likeſt to vſe it aright, and the beſt able to free it from abuſe? Ninethly the Church may and ought to vſe that outward act, which the Spirit of God himſelfe doth deſigne,
<note place="margin">Eze. 9.4, 5, 6. Reuel. 7.1, 2, 3 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</note> for the expreſſing of his owne inward action; but the Spirit of God doth deſigne the outward act of <hi>ſigning,</hi> for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of his owne inward action of ſpirituall <hi>ſealing;</hi> as both <hi>Ezekiel</hi> in the olde Teſtament, and <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> in the new doe witneſſe: and therefore the Church may and ought to vſe the ſame outward act of <hi>ſigning.</hi> Tenthly the Church is bound to declare and notifie the grace of Gods Spirit, working in men, and euen to make men as ſenſible of the workes of Gods Spirit in them, as they can conueniently: now it is one of the workes of Gods
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3528:38"/>Spirit, and a chiefe worke too, to <hi>ſeale</hi> men in their ſoules inwardly, and to <hi>ſtampe</hi> them as it were with the print of his Image, vnto the day of redemption,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.22. &amp; 5.5. Epheſ. 1.13. &amp; 4.30.</note> (as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaketh) and therefore for the Church to make men ſenſible of this internall and myſticall <hi>ſealing</hi> of Gods Spirit, by the meanes of ſuch a conuenient and decent ſenſible ſigne, as that of the <hi>Croſſe</hi> (though there were no particular mention at all made in the whole Scripture, of any ſuch externall geſture or act of <hi>ſigning</hi> on the <hi>fore-head</hi>) muſt needes be lawful and commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Eleuenthly, by this Signe the Church putteth her children in minde of their owne miſerie, and of Gods mercy, of Chriſts loue towards them, and of their duty and affection towards him, for his vnſpeakeable loue, and therefore it tendeth to edification. Twelfthly this ceremonie was receiued and practiſed of the primitiue Church, neither is there any eccleſiaſticall writer or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Greeke or Latine, but maketh honourable menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, as we ſhall ſhew particularly in our Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the perſecution and peace of the Church; and therefore we ought to vſe it now, if it were no more but to ſhew our conformitie with the primitiue Church: for the daughter ought to follow the footeſteps of her mother in all lawfull and commendable actions, and ought not to depart from her, otherwiſe ſhee ſhall both diſhonour her mother, and diſcredit her ſelfe. And que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſſe, the want of this primitiue ceremonie and others the like in ſome reformed Churches, hath brought a moſt dangerous diſcredite vpon the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and made it obnoxious vnto the ſuſpition and odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous imputation of the ſame noueltie, in the very ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which it carrieth amongſt them in the out ſide &amp; circumſtance. And therfore thoſe venerable Biſhops that reformed the Church of England, conſidering wiſely with themſelues, how that men are ſo apt to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3528:39"/>of the <hi>inſide</hi> by the <hi>outſide,</hi> eſpecially in Church mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and to iudge of doctrine and pietie, by the externall diſcipline and ceremonie, retained ſtil the primitiue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and auncient ceremonies of that Church, but baniſhed the abuſes. And would to God the Church of <hi>Geneua</hi> had done the like; for ſo our common aduerſaries ſhould not haue had ſo good and iuſt cauſe as they haue, to hit them in the teeth with their noueltie, as though their Church had newly crept or leapt out of the <hi>Leman nian lake,</hi> or had beene conceiued of <hi>Caluin</hi> and borne of <hi>Beza.</hi> Thirtenthly and laſtly, the enemies of the ſigne of the croſſe, can not bring ſo much as one good au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie or probable argument for their opinion: not the letter of the Scripture; for they ſee that the letter fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it both in the olde Teſtament and new; not the ſenſe of the Scripture, as it hath beene deliuered by the fathers of the Church, for they know, that they are all for it, and as for reaſons deriued from the light of nature, or Scripture, from Theologie or Philoſophie, Diuinitie or humanitie, they can bring none, worth the hearing, (for I haue read diligently their bookes and was once a Puritane my ſelfe) except it bee this one, The Church of Rome hath abuſed the ſigne of the croſſe, and therefore the reformed Church ought to forbeare it, leaſt wee ſhould ſeeme to fauour or follow their abuſes. But I wonder but they ſhould remember better that olde maxime, <hi>abuſus non tollit vſum,</hi> ſome folkes abuſing of a thing, doth not hinder or let, but that others may vſe it aright. And doe they not thinke that the Church of Rome, doth abuſe praying and preaching, and Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and pulpits, and kneeling, and Godfathers and Godmothers aſwell as croſſing, and yet we doe not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare theſe things, becauſe of their abuſe; neither is there any reaſon why we ſhould doe ſo, but rather great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to the contrary. The Church of Rome doth abuſe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3528:39"/>ceremonies; &amp; therfore the reformed Church ought to vſe them aright, to the end that in ſo doing ſhee may both ſhow her ſelfe like and conforme vnto her Mother the Primitiue Church, and by her good example doe what ſhee can, out of Chriſtian charity to reforme and amend her ſtraying ſiſter the deformed Romiſh Church. And ſo I end this my plaine diſputation for the ſigne of the croſſe in Baptiſme, beſeeching my countrymen to take it in good part, euen for his ſake that ſuffered vpon the Croſſe.
<note place="margin">The Church of England more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen like for honour of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery.</note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="section">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 21.</head>
                     <p>Eightly the Church of England is liker then the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuian, to the heauenly Church in the <hi>dignitie</hi> and <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable eſtate</hi> of the <hi>Miniſterie.</hi> In heauen Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are honoured with the holieſt ſtile of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and with the higheſt ſtile of <hi>Princes;</hi> for as vnder the higheſt of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> they are <hi>Prieſts,</hi> ſo vnder the higheſt of <hi>Princes</hi> they are <hi>Princes.</hi> And therefore we reade in the <hi>Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> how that bleſſed <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> calleth the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of the ſeauen Churches by the honourable ſtiles of <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Reuel a. 1.4, 5 6, &amp; 2. &amp; 3. &amp;. 5.3, 9, 10, 12, 13, 14, &amp; 7, 10, 12, &amp; 8, 3.4.</note> and the foure and twentie <hi>Elders</hi> doe magnifie the <hi>Lambe</hi> for making them vnto God <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> to <hi>raigne</hi> or <hi>rule</hi> vpon the earth. Anſwerably whereunto in the Church of England, the reuerend Fathers of the Church are graced by the <hi>Soueraigne Prince,</hi> repreſenting the <hi>Lambe</hi> and the <hi>Lyon</hi> of the <hi>tribe of Iudah,</hi> with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable title and dignitie of <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Barons.</hi> And good reaſon ſurely, ſeeing that the Gouernours of the Church vnder the Goſpell, are to be rather more then leſſe honoured, then were the Gouernours of the Church vnder the law, in ſo farre as the Miniſterie of the Goſpell is much more honourable and glorious then that of the law,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> as the Apoſtle expreſſely auou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth. And that the Miniſters and Gouernours of the Church vnder the olde Teſtament were called
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3528:40"/>by honourable titles it may appeare in that <hi>Moſes</hi> a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,
<note place="margin">Exod. 3. &amp; 4, 16, &amp; 18, 1. Sam. 1.3.9, 15, &amp; 7, 8, 9, 10, 15, 16, 17, Deut. 17, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 2. Chron. 17, 7, &amp; 19, 8, 9.10, 11, Ezech. 44, 24, 1. Sam. 1.9.14, 15, 16, 17 18, 26, &amp; 4, 18 1. King. 17, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20.21, 22, 23, 24, &amp; 18, 3, 4, 7, 9, 12, 13, 2. King. 1.13, 14, &amp; 4, 1, 2, 16, 27, 28, 37, &amp; 5, 15, 16, 17, 18, &amp; 8, 9, 12, Act. 10.25, &amp; 16.24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, Gen 40.8, &amp; 41, 14, 15, 16, 25, 40, 41, 42, 43, 44, Dan. 2.28, 29 30, 36, 48, 49 &amp; 5, 29, &amp; 6, 1 2, 3. Pſal. 45.9, 13, 16,</note> was likewiſe a Prince, <hi>Eli</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi> Prieſts, were Princes and Iudges, and the Prieſts iudged of ſome ciuill cauſes, together with the other temporall Iudges. The chiefe Prieſts which taught the people of <hi>Iuda,</hi> are called Princes, whom King <hi>Ieheſophat</hi> had appointed to be Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges vnder him, both in eccleſſiaſtical and temporal cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as betweene blood and blood, betweene law and precept, ſtatutes and iudgements. <hi>Anna,</hi> called <hi>Eli</hi> the the chiefe Prieſt her Lord, the widdow of <hi>Zarepta,</hi> the widdow of <hi>Bethel,</hi> the <hi>Shunamite</hi> Gentlewoman, <hi>Obadiah</hi> King <hi>Achabs</hi> ſteward, the good Captaine ſent by King <hi>Ahaziah, Naeamen</hi> the King of <hi>Syrta</hi> his Generall, <hi>Hazael</hi> one of the Princes of <hi>Benhadad</hi> King of <hi>Aram,</hi> did all of them honour the chiefe Prophets of God, <hi>Eliah</hi> and <hi>Eliſha,</hi> with the ſtile of Lords, and bowed before them. And ſo did <hi>Cornelius</hi> the Captaine, and likewiſe the Iay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, to the bleſſed Apoſtles, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul;</hi> to paſſe ouer, that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> a Patriarke and a Prophet of the Church, was likewiſe a chiefe Prince vnder the King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> euen the next vnto the King, <hi>Daniel</hi> another chiefe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of the Church, was likewiſe a Prince, and the next perſon to the King of <hi>Babel Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> and his three fellowes, <hi>Shadrach, Meſſach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> were made Gouernours ouer the Prouinces of <hi>Babel,</hi> and the ſame Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> was by King <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> made the third Ruler in the kingdome, and by King <hi>Darius,</hi> the firſt and chiefe Ruler ouer the whole kingdome. And the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> prophecying of the ſplendour and dignitie of the Fathers of the Church, vnder the Goſpel, vſeth theſe words, <hi>In ſtead of thy Fathers, ſhall thy Children be, thou ſhalt make them Princes through all the earth;</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that of the Children of the Church, there ſhould be choſen ſuch as ſhould bee Fathers and Rulers of the Church, as <hi>Arch-Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> which ſhould bee
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3528:40"/>honoured throughout the whole Chriſtian world, as Lords and Princes. For the holy Prophet, as hee deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth typically Chriſt, as the King of the Catholike Church, and none but he to be King; and the Church as the Queene and Spouſe of this King, ſo doth be ſignifie vnto vs, that the Princes of this King and kingdome, are the Rulers and Gouernours of the Church aboue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, which of the Children of the Church ſhould bee made Fathers of the Church, and ſhould be honoured as Princes, as hath binſaid. And this propheſie is moſt cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhed and verified in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> not of <hi>Geneua,</hi> nor any <hi>Geneuian;</hi> vnto whoſe Miniſters God hath not graunted ſo much honour, as they who haue vnhappily diſhonoured and debaſed themſelues, in brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging in their <hi>Lay-elders</hi> to bee Church gouernours, in ſtead of the Biſhops. I ſay they haue debaſed themſelues moſt ridiculouſly, becauſe that they haue ſubmitted themſelues, who ſhould be as Fathers and Schoolema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, vnto their owne children and Schollers: for by thoſe <hi>Lay-elders</hi> they are elected, they are iudged and cenſured, in matters both of life and doctrine, they are ſuſpended or remooued from their miniſterie: and yet they are but meere Lay-men, generally voide of learning, as being for the moſt part tradeſmen and artificers, and ſome coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try gentlemen. So that there is as great diſorder in the Geneuian Church, and as groſſe abſurditie as if the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhould command their Fathers in the houſe, or the Schollers correct their Maſters in the Schoole, or as if the Sheepe ſhould pull the paſtorall crooke out of their Sheepheards hand. And though that our Geneuians do deriue their <hi>Lay-elders</hi> and <hi>Elderſhip,</hi> from the <hi>Synedrie</hi> of the Iewes, (for I graunt them with all my heart, that the chiefe perfections of the Iewiſh Church, ought to bee found in the Chriſtian Church, which thing if they vnderſtood well, they ſhould ſee their groſſe errours)
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3528:41"/>yet I muſt tel them that they haue nothing like but the name. For firſt the Iewiſh Elders were inferiour magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ordained primarily by the Soueraigne and chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt magiſtrate <hi>Moſes</hi> to aſſiſt him in matters of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t;
<note place="margin">Numbers. 11.16, 17, Ezr. 10.8, Luk. 22.66, Act. 5.27.</note> wheras the Geneuia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are not Iudges or any ſuch pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like perſons, appointed by the Prince, but priuate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons picked out of the Pariſh by the Preacher, and ſome other with him. Secondly, the Iewiſh Elders iudged and cenſured the Laitie, and therefore were called the Elders of the people, wheras the Geneuia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preſume to cenſure &amp; correct their Clergie. Thirdly and laſtly the Iewiſh El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders concurred with the Princes of the Prieſts as their aſſiſtants or officers in matters of iudgement and debate, but the Geneuian haue no Princes of Prieſts,
<note place="margin">Deut. 17.8.9.10.11, 12,2. Chron. 19, 8, 9, 10.11, Ezech. 44.4.</note> or Prince-Church gouernours, as <hi>Primates, Archbiſhops</hi> or <hi>Biſhops,</hi> to giue aſſiſtance vnto: whereby it doth appeare that the Iudges and Iuſtices of Peace in England, are like thoſe Elders of the Iewes, eſpecially the Iudges of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall courts called by the names of <hi>Chancellour, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſary, Deane</hi> of the <hi>Arches, Officiall</hi> and the like, and in no wiſe the Elders after the Geneuian forme. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer as the Miniſters of the heauenly Church are called <hi>Prieſts,</hi> ſo are the Miniſters of the Church of England honoured,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 4.8, 9, 10.11, &amp; 5, 8 &amp; 7, 10, 12, &amp; 8, 3, 4, Heb. 13.15. Hoſ. 14.3,</note> with the ſame holy title and ſtile. Thoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall <hi>Prieſts</hi> doe offer vp vnto God the ſpirituall ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of prayer and praiſe; and anſwerably thereunto our Engliſh Euangelicall <hi>Prieſts</hi> offer vnto God, the like ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſacrifice, as the Apoſtle preſcribeth ſaying, <hi>Let vs therefore by him offer the ſacrifice of praiſe, alwaies to God, that is, the fruite of the lippes which confeſſe his name.</hi> Publike prayer and praiſe is a ſacrifice: and therfore, the Miniſter that offereth it is a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> neither could he bleſſe pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely the people, except hee were a <hi>Priest</hi> (for Church-benediction is a part of the <hi>Priests</hi> function) nor yet Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter any of the two Sacraments, in both which there
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3528:41"/>is a ſpirituall ſacrifice; for by <hi>Baptiſme</hi> our bodies and ſoules are offered vnto God by the hand of his <hi>Priest,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 12.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.27.28, 29, 30. &amp;. 28, 19, Ioh. 6.32, 33 41, 51, Reue l. 2, 17,</note> a reaſonable and liuing ſacrifice, and in the <hi>Eucharist</hi> or Sacrament of the Lords Supper, he offereth vnto God in our name the ſpirituall ſacrifice of thankeſgiuing, for giuing the ſubſtance of his bleſſed body, both corporal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for vs, a bloodie ſacrifice vpon the croſſe, and ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto vs in the Sacrament of bread &amp; wine, and euen for feeding of vs in a my ſticall and ſupernaturall manner with his fleſh, which is that <hi>hidden Manna</hi> of heauen,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 1.4, 5, 6, &amp; 5.10, Heb. 7.15, 17, 21, 24, 26, 28, &amp; 8, 1, 2, 3.</note> promiſed in the <hi>Reuelation</hi> to thoſe that ouercome. To bee briefe, the bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> writing vnto the <hi>Angels</hi> or <hi>Biſhops</hi> of the ſeauen Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> calleth them <hi>Priests,</hi> like as the foure and twentie <hi>Elders</hi> in heauen, doe call themſelues <hi>Priests;</hi> and Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe is called a <hi>Priest,</hi> yea more, an high or <hi>chiefe Priest,</hi> and conſequently muſt haue inferiour <hi>Priests</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him. And ſuch are the Miniſters of the Goſpell in <hi>England;</hi> the which ſtile whileſt our <hi>Genenians</hi> cannot endure, no more then the <hi>white Surpliſſe,</hi> and the <hi>artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall ſinging;</hi> I wonder what they meane to do in heauen, where <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> ſaw ſo many <hi>Prieſts,</hi> ſo many <hi>white habits,</hi> and heard ſuch <hi>harmonie</hi> and <hi>muſicall melodie.</hi> Now the honourable titles that God hath vouchſafed his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, doe ſhow that it is his will,
<note place="margin">Deut. 10, 9, &amp; 12, 19, &amp; 24, 23, 25, Numb. 18.12 13, 17, 18, 19 20, 21, 2, 23 24, 1. Cor. 9.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, Heb. 10. 1. Tim. 5.17, 18,</note> they ſhould haue a more honourable maintenance, then <hi>Geneua</hi> doth allow them in their beggarly contributions. The <hi>Priests</hi> and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> haue ſucceeded into the roome of the legall <hi>Priests</hi> and Miniſters of the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> and therefore they haue ſucceeded to their maintenance, and ſo much the more becauſe theſe ſerue him in a more excellent manner then the other did. And if hee would not haue his Miniſters to begge vnder the law, or yet to depend vpon popular beneuolences, ſhall wee thinke that hee would haue his Miniſters vnder the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:3528:42"/>Goſpell, to be ſubiect to ſuch a beggarly condition? Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry prouident &amp; wiſe maſter prouideth for his houſhold and ſeruants;
<note place="margin">Leuit. 27.30, 31, 32. Deut. 12.17, 18, 19, &amp; 14, 22, 23, 27, 29 &amp; 26, Numb. 18. Nehem. 10.35, 36, 37, 38 39. Ioſh. 13.14, 33. 2. Chron. 31.4, 5, 6, 7, 8, Ezech. 44, 28 29, 30, 2. Tim. 2.6. Luk. 10.2.7. 1. Tim. 5.18. Mat. 9.37, 38.</note> wherefore it followeth, that God, who is the moſt prouident and wiſe Maſter of all other, hath prouided for the maintenance of his houſhold ſeruants, and we know none other, but <hi>firſt fruites</hi> and <hi>tithes:</hi> all labourers haue certaine ſtanding wages, the Miniſters of the Goſpell are Gods labourers, therefore they ought to haue their ſtanding wages likewiſe, and wee read of none other, except firſt <hi>fruites</hi> and <hi>tithes.</hi> And therefore we ſee how our Sauiour forbiddeth his Apoſtles to goe from houſe to houſe, telling them that the workeman is worthy of his hire. And truly if hee would not haue his Apoſtles to goe from houſe to houſe, euen in that time when tithes were withholden from them by the Iewiſh clergie; ſhall we thinke that now when the Iewiſh clergie is aboliſhed, he would haue his Miniſters of the Goſpell to goe from houſe to houſe, or yet to ſend from houſe to houſe, to begge the peoples beneuolences? Thoſe that withheld from Chriſts Apoſtles and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, the duty of <hi>firſt fruites</hi> and <hi>tithes,</hi> were ſuch as perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted both them and Chriſt, and crucified him in the end;
<note place="margin">Deut. 10, 9, &amp; 12, 19, &amp; 14, 23.29, 2. Chron. 31.4. Prouerb. 3.9, 10.</note> and ſuch <hi>God ſpoiling Goſpellers,</hi> as doe now adaies withhold the Church-rents from Churchmen, what doe they elſe but perſecute Gods Miniſters, and crucifie Chriſt daily in his members? The ends of paying firſt fruites and tithes vnto Gods Prieſts are perpetuall, to wit, that the Miniſters of God may bee maintained, and not forſaken, but more and more encouraged in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God, that God may be honoured with our riches, and acknowledged to bee our great <hi>Land-lord</hi> and <hi>good Lord,</hi> that we may learne to feare the Lord, and that hee may bleſſe vs in all the workes of our hands, that ſo our ſtore may be increaſed, and our barnes filled with abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance: are not Chriſtians Gods tenants, farmers and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:3528:42"/>vaſſals as well as were the Iewes? and doe we not hold all that we haue of God as well as they? and are we not bound to pay our annuall rents vnto God as duly and truly as they? and what reaſon haue Chriſtians to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake their Miniſters more then the Iewes had? and doe not the one deſerue aſwell to bee liberally maintained and encouraged in their worke as the other? and haue not Chriſtians as great cauſe to learne to feare God, as the Iewes had? finally doe not Chriſtians deſire as earneſtly as the Iewes did, to be bleſſed in the workes of their hands, and in the encreaſe of their ſtore? wherefore it followeth neceſſarily that we Chriſtians muſt pay our Tithes as truly and duly as did the Iewes.
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5 17, 18. 1. Cor. 9.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14.</note> And therefore the bleſſed Apoſtle, as he commendeth vnto Chriſtians the honourable and liberall maintenance of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, right diligently, writing to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and euen prooueth by the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the right that the Miniſters of the Goſpell, haue vnto our carnall things and euen vnto ſuch carnall things as both <hi>Moſes</hi> doth preſcribe in his Law, and the Apoſtle himſelfe doth men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, entreating of this matter, comprehending them vnder theſe two kinds, the fruits of the field, and the flockes of the fold; ſo writing to the <hi>Galathians,</hi> he enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in expreſſe words,
<note place="margin">Heb 13.7, Galat. 6.6,</note> euery one that is taught in the word, to make him that hath taught him, <hi>partaker of all his goods.</hi> The people muſt giue a part of their goods vnto their Paſtours, as the Apoſtle preſcribeth, and all doe acknowledge to be reaſonable, now this part muſt either be equall vnto the <hi>Leuiticall</hi> part, or greater then it, or elſe ſmaller. To giue them a ſmaller, were a moſt vnreaſonable indiſcretion, and a more then beaſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, and if they will not, nor cannot beſtow a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſuch as indeed it ought to be,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> (for looke how farre the miniſterie of the Goſpell is more excellent then that of the law, ſo much the more ample and liberall ought
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:3528:43"/>to be the maintenance of the Miniſters of the Goſpell, then was that of the Miniſters of the Tabernacle) yet at leaſt for ſhame, they muſt giue an equall portion with that of the legall Prieſts. Laſtly to ſhut vp this our reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for the perpetuitie of tithes &amp; for the honourable maintenance of Chriſts ſeruants (for hereof wee haue written more amply in a worke publiſhed ſome fewe yeares agoe called the <hi>Golden</hi> art or <hi>the right way of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riching</hi> dedicated to the two moſt famous and royall Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of theſe two kingdoms) I ſay that the holy Scripture ſetteth downe the paying of theſe yearely Church-rents amongſt morall duties, and accounteth of Sacriledge, not as if it were the tranſgreſſion of a ceremoniall ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but euen the violation of a morall law. <hi>Will a man ſpoyle his Gods,</hi> (ſaith the Lord God by his Prophet <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachie) yet ye haue spoyled me in tithes and in offerings.
<note place="margin">Malacha. 3, 8. Prouerb. 3.9, 10, &amp; 20.25,</note> Honour the Lord (ſaith Solomon) with thy riches, and with the firſt, fruites of all thine encreaſe, ſo ſhall thy barnes bee filled with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance, and thy preſſe ſhall burst with new wine. But it is a deſtruction for a man to deuoure that which is ſanctified:</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that the man who will not honour God with firſt fruites and tithes, but doth deuour the holy things, and committeth ſacriledge, bringeth deſtruction vpon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, his ſoule, his body, his goods, and his houſe. <hi>Thon that ſaiest a man ſhould not commite adulterie,
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.22,</note> breakeſt thou wedlocke?</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>and thou that abhorreſt Idols doeſt thou committ ſacriledge?</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, thou that deteſteſt the honouring of a falſe God wilt thou neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe ſpoile and diſhonour the true God; whereby wee are giuen to vnderſtand, that <hi>ſacriledge</hi> is not only a tranſgreſſion of the morall law, but that it is euen a double ſinne, compounded of <hi>robbery</hi> and <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and conſequently a more deteſtable and abbominable euill then Idolatry it ſelfe. For the Idolater with his heart, his bodie and ſubſtance, yea ſometimes with the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:3528:43"/>blood of his deereſt children honoreth a falſe God,
<note place="margin">Leuit. 18.21. &amp;. 20.2. 2. King. 23.10. &amp; 16.3. &amp; 17.17. Ierem. 7.31</note> yet thinking that it is the true God indeede he doth thus worſhip; whereas the ſacrilegious God-ſpoyler robbeth the true God of his owne. The Idolater is careful to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſome God, but the God-ſpoyler careth for no God at all; a falſe god he doth not know, and it is well; and the true God he will not acknowledge, which is a worſe part then the others blind worſhipping of a falſe god. For the Idolater being miſled with an erroneous opinion, maketh and taketh that to be God which is not God, for ignorantly of an Idol he maketh God; whereas the ſacrilegious God-ſpoyler malitiouſly euen wittingly and willingly of the true God maketh no God at all but a meere Idol: otherwiſe he durſt not be ſo bold as to rob him of his right, for it is an infallible maxime, that a man will neuer robbe or ſpoyle him whom he loueth hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth or feareth.</p>
                     <p>O how vgly then is the ſinne of ſacriledge that beareth neuertheleſſe ſuch a ſway in this <hi>Ile,</hi> but eſpecially in the <hi>North!</hi> O how horrible an iniquitie is it for men of might to pull out of Gods mouth the diet of the Church to put it into their owne, and to fill the bellies of their houndes and their horſes with the meate of Gods mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters! It is a ſinne of that high nature, that becauſe of it, God hath ſaid vnto vs, as once he ſaid vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Iſrael</hi> vpon the like occaſion,
<note place="margin">Malach. 3.9, 10.11. Amos. 4.6.7, 8, 9, 10. Iſay. 16.9.10. Hag. 1.10. &amp; 2.18.</note> 
                        <hi>yee are curſed with a curſe, for yee haue ſpoiled mee, euen this whole nation</hi> (but bleſſed be our Soueraigne for labouring to remooue this curſe from our nation) and that he hath ſometimes ſent ſcarceneſſe of bread, and cleaneneſſe of teeth in our Cities and townes; ſometimes hath with holden the raine from vs when there were yet three moneths to the harueſt; and ſhut the windowes of heauen vpon vs and ſtayed the raine till the fruits of the earth were deſtroied with drought, ſometimes hath ſmitten our fruites with
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:3528:44"/>blaſting and mildew, and ſent the palmer worme to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure the fruites of our trees, yea made our ſinging and ſhouting for ioy in barneſt to ceaſe, and made vs drunke with our teares, for that the heauen aboue vs was ſtayed from dew, and the earth vnder vs from yeelding her en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe. For this abhominable ſinne God hath ſomtimes ſent the peſtilence amongſt vs to rage in moſt violent manner, to conſume our bodies and the fire to burne, and the water to ouerflowe our townes, landes, houſes and habitations. In one word, it is this horrible ſinne of Sacriledge that hath ouerthrowne the ſtrength and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of diuers mighty and wealthy houſes; God in moſt iuſt iudgement ſhutting ſuch from their inheritance as were ſo audacious and bold as to robbe him of his. The ſacrilegious God-ſpoyler is the man which (as Iob ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth) <hi>hath ſtretched out his hand against God,
<note place="margin">Iob. 15.6.27.</note> and made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſtrong againſt the almighty, therefore God ſhall runne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, euen vpon his necke, and againſt the moſt thicke part of his ſhield becauſe he hath couered his face with his fatneſſe, and hath collopes in his flankes,</hi> as if the holy man ſhould ſay, becauſe this <hi>God-ſpoyling Anti God</hi> hath preſumed to ſhut God from his inheritance, and hath taken from him his <hi>Tithes</hi> and hath made himſelfe fat with <hi>Gods meate</hi> which he hath pulled out of the hands and mouthes of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 29.30.31.32.33.34.</note> therefore God ſhall be auenged on him, <hi>hee ſhall not be rich alwaies, neither ſhall his ſubstance continue, neither ſhall he prolong the perfection thereof in the earth, he ſhall neuer depart out of darkeneſſe, the flame ſhall drie vp his branches, &amp; he ſhall goe away with the breath of his mouth. His branch ſhal not be greene, but ſhall be cutte off before his day, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the Hypocrites ſhall be deſolate:</hi> and who is ſo great an hypocrite as the ſacrilegious <hi>Church robber,</hi> who being an impure <hi>God-ſpoyler</hi> indeed will needes in the meane time be eſteemed a <hi>pure Gospeller</hi> and one of the preciſeſt profeſſours of the reformed Church? Hee
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:3528:44"/>may well make himſelfe merry with the meate of Gods Miniſters, as prophane <hi>Balthaſar</hi> did with the golden and ſiluer veſſell of Gods houſe,
<note place="margin">Dan. 5.1, 2, 3 4.5. Iob. 20.5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.</note> but he ſhall know in the end, <hi>that the reioycing of the wicked ſhall haue an end;</hi> and (as <hi>Zophar</hi> ſpeaketh) <hi>that the ioy of hypocrites is but a moment. Though his excellency mount vp to the heauen, and his head reach vnto the cloudes, yet ſhall he periſh for euer like his dung, and they which haue ſeene him, ſhall ſay, where is he? he ſhall flee away as a dreame, and they ſhall not finde him, he ſhall paſſe away as a viſion of the night, ſo that the eye which had ſeene ſhal doe ſo no more, &amp; his place ſhal ſee him no more:</hi> as if he ſhould ſay; though hee were neuer ſo great and mighty a man, that robbeth Gods Church, yea though his height did reach vnto heauen, yet for all his height, he ſhall not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into heauen, but ſhall fall to the earth like his owne dung, and his ſacrilegious ſoule ſhall ſtinke,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 10.</note> more vilely then his dung amids hel flames. <hi>His children ſhall flatter the poore, and his hands ſhall reſtore his ſubſtance,</hi> as if hee ſhould ſay; becauſe the father through pride and tyrannie op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed the poore, and ſpoiled Gods Miniſters, therefore God ſhall make the poſteritie of that man, for pouertie &amp; want to begge his bread at other poore folkes doores; yea that thing which the ſacrilegious father tooke away by violence,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 15, 16 17.</note> his barnes ſhall be brought to reſtore againe by force. <hi>Hee hath deuoured ſubſtance, and he ſhall vomite it; for God ſhall draw it out of his belly,</hi> ſeeing to him it belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, and in lieu thereof, <hi>he ſhall ſucke the gall of Aſpes, and the Vipers tongue ſhall ſlay him;</hi> that is, his portion ſhall bee with hypocrites, and the generation of vipers, for the old Serpent that wicked viper ſhall ſlay his ſoule, <hi>hee ſhall not ſee the riuers, nor the floods and ſtreames of hony and butter,</hi> that is to ſay, hee ſhall not taſte of the happineſſe of the heauenly Canaan. Hee on earth ſhut God from his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance on earth, but in the end, God ſhall ſhut him out of the earth, and debarre him from heauen, &amp; hurle
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:3528:45"/>him headlong into hell. <hi>He ſhall restore the labour, and ſhall deuoure no more, euen according to the ſubstance, ſhall bee his exchange,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23</note> and he ſhall enioy it no more. For he hath vndone ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, he hath forſaken the poore, and hath ſpoyled houſes which hee built not</hi> euen Church-mens houſes, yea Gods houſe, and God himſelfe hath he ſpoiled. <hi>Surely he ſhall feele no quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in his body, neither ſhall hee reſerue of that which he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, there ſhal none of his meate beleft, therfore none of his ſhall hope for his goods.</hi> As if hee ſhould ſay, becauſe hee would needes deuoure Gods meate, and the dyet of his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, therefore God ſhal ſend the deuourer to eate vp his meate. <hi>For when hee ſhall bee filled with his abundance,</hi> that is, with Gods portion and Church mens prouiſion, <hi>He ſhall be in paine, and the hand of all the wicked ſhall aſſaile him:</hi> that is to ſay; becauſe he was ſo wicked as to ſtretch out his hand to ſpoile God; therefore God ſhall make many wicked mens hands to ſpoile him: <hi>He ſhal be about to fill his belly,</hi> to wit, with Gods Miniſters meate, <hi>but God ſhall ſend vpon him his fierce wrath, and ſhall cauſe to raine vpon him, euen vpon his meat.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, Gods Miniſters meate ſhall doe him no good; for God ſhall either draw it out of his belly, or elſe he ſhall turne it in the midſt of his bowels into the gall of aſpes. And not only ſhall God draw his own Miniſters meate out of the <hi>God-ſpoilers</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable belly, but he ſhall alſo draw the <hi>ſacrilegious ſoule</hi> out of the deuouring body, &amp; it ſhal burne in the <hi>fire that is not blowne,</hi> that is, in hell fire that needeth no blowing. <hi>The heauen ſhall declare his wickedneſſe</hi> (for he was ſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and impious,
<note place="margin">Verſe 26, 27, 28, 29,</note> as to ſpoile the God of heauen) <hi>and the earth ſhall riſe vp against him</hi> (for he was ſo vngratious, as to robbe Gods Miniſters and houſhold ſeruants on earth) <hi>the increaſe of his houſe ſhall goe away, it ſhall flow away in the day of his wrath.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, the mans houſe that is increaſed, builded or reared vp, by the decreaſe or robbery of Gods houſe, it ſhall not alwaies ſtand, the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:3528:45"/>greaſe and fatneſſe of it ſhall flow away like water, the pelfe and wealth thereof, ſhall vaniſh and melt away like the fat of Lambes, or as doth the ſnow before the Sun. <hi>Such is the portion of the wicked from God, and the heritage that he ſhall haue at Gods hands;</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and deſtruction in ſubſtance, in body and ſoule, ſhall be the portion and heritage of all impenitent <hi>vnreſtoring God-ſpoilers,</hi> vnworthy of the title of <hi>Goſpellers,</hi> men worſe then idolaters, which doe indeed turne the true God into an idol, as the other doe an idol into God, and worſhip &amp; feare, neither true nor falſe deitie. A falſe God they know not, and the true God they will not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; for otherwiſe they would ſtand in awe, to ſpoile God of his portion, and to bereaue him of his inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. And therefore to ſhut vp this pleading for Gods Prieſts and their honourable maintenance, let me pray &amp; beſeech all <hi>Britaines,</hi> eſpecially my deere country-men of <hi>Scotland,</hi> that if they deſire either to be rich heere, or happie hereafter, that they would be bountiful &amp; liberal to Gods ſeruants, &amp; that euery man that hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the Church any thing, or withholden from Churchmen their <hi>Tithes</hi> in whole or in part by <hi>ſacrilegious impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> or wicked <hi>vſurpation,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Luk. 19.8.</note> that he would reſtore with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting <hi>Zacheus</hi> fourefolde, or at leaſt the principall ſtocke, which he hath in his hands. Let him I ſay, liſten with all diligence and conſcience vnto the precept of the moſt high vttered by the mouth of his prophet <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachie</hi> ſaying,
<note place="margin">Malach. 3.10.11.12.</note> 
                        <hi>bring euery Tithe into the storehouſe that there may be meate in mine houſe, and prooue me withall, ſaith the Lord of hoaſts, If I wil not open the windowes of heauen vnto you, and powre you out a bleſſing without meaſure; and I wil reproue the deuourer for your ſakes, and he ſhall not destroy the fruite of the ground, neither ſhall your vine be barren in the field ſaith the Lord of hoastes, and all nations ſhall call you bleſſed becauſe ye ſhall be a pleaſant land.</hi> Laſtly, let vs all liſten vnto the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:3528:46"/>godly and graue exhortation of wiſe king <hi>Salomon;</hi> ſaying <hi>honor the Lord with thy ſubſtance and with the firſt fruites of all thine encreaſe,
<note place="margin">Prouerb. 3.9,</note> ſo ſhall thy barnes be filled with abundance and thy preſſe ſhall ouerflow with new wine;</hi> and let vs with our whole hearts applaude our owne <hi>Salomons</hi> glorious and diuine endeauours tending to the perfit conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Church, and to the aduancing of Almightie Gods ſincere worſhip: and let vs bleſſe the God of <hi>Iacob,</hi> for raiſing vp vnto vs from the <hi>North,</hi> a <hi>Iacob,</hi> to be anin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of ſuch bleſſedneſſe vnto both <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> according to that which he once promiſed by his Prophet,
<note place="margin">Iſay. 4 3, 6. Iſay. 4.1, 25.</note> 
                        <hi>I will ſay to the North, giue, and to the South, keepe not backe.</hi> And againe, <hi>I haue raiſed vp from the North, and be ſhall come, from the east Sunne ſhall hee call vpon my name:</hi> and yet againe,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 8.9, 10.11, 12,</note> ſpeaking of the conuerſion of the Ilands and endes of the earth vnto Chriſt, as if hee pointed at our <hi>Iacob, Thou Iacob, whom I haue choſen, I haue taken thee from the endes of the earth, and called thee before the chiefe thereof, and ſaid vnto thee, thou art my ſeruant; I haue choſen thee, be not afraid, for I am with thee, behold all they that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke thee, ſhall be aſhamed, and they that ſtriue with thee ſhall periſh.</hi> Euen bleſſed be the God of <hi>Iacob</hi> for giuing vs a <hi>Iacob</hi> to be the inſtrument of ſo great bleſſedneſſe vnto this <hi>Ile,</hi> and to the Church thereof, and grant that wee may with both hands and hearts lay hold on ſuch bleſſed occaſions, as he doth now tender vs, by the hand of his bleſſed <hi>Iacob,</hi> for the amending of the defects of our Church, where through all nations may call vs a bleſſed people. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3528:47"/>
                  <p>A DEMONSTRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIVE DEFENCE OR TENFOLD PROBATION OF THE DOCTRINE OF THE CHVRCH OF ENGLAND TOVCHING one of the moſt important points of our Creed, neceſſary to be vnderſtood of all Chriſtians, <hi>which is of our Sauiours deſcending into</hi> hell after death, to binde and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due Sathan, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Written for the information and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of many mens mindes touching ſo weighty a matter, but eſpecially for the furthering of the <hi>Church of Scotlands full conformitie with</hi> that of England.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BY</hi> IAMES MAXVVELL Maſter of Artes, &amp;c.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>PSAL. 122. verſe 6.</hi>
                     </bibl> Pray for the peace of Ieruſalem, let them proſper that loue thee.</q>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed by IOHN LEGATT, Printer to the Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of Cambridge. 1617.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3528:48"/>
                  <p>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHERS IN GOD, THE ARCHBISHOPS, AND BISHOPS, HIS VERY GOOD LORDS, <hi>AND OTHER LEARNED AND GRAVE</hi> PASTOVRS OF THE CHVRCH OF SCOTLAND, <hi>IAMES MAXWELL</hi> WI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHETH, PEACE, VNITIE AND <hi>CONCORD FROM THE GOD OF CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CORD, AND PRINCE OF PEACE,</hi> AND HVMBLY DEDICATETH FOR A TESTIMONIE OF HIS DVTY, THIS PRESENT TREATISE <hi>OF CHRISTS DESCEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DING INTO HELL.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3528:48"/>
                  <head>A Demonſtration of Chriſts Deſcending into Hell.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ike as the diſſenſions and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in matter of faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene Chriſtian and Chriſtian, Greeke and Latine, Papiſt and Proteſtant, haue prooued the greateſt ſcandall and offence, to thoſe that are without the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of the Church, and the greateſt hinderance of both <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles conuerſion</hi> vnto Chriſt, that euer the hand of hell brought into the world, or the diuell did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe; ſo the contentions and diſſentions, the diuiſions and differences, ariſing betweene Proteſtant and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant (which haue a number of new denominations ſuch as ſorrow and ſhame will not ſo much as once ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me to mention) haue prooued queſtionleſſe the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſcandall of our reformed profeſſion, and the chiefeſt cauſe of many Papiſts auerſeneſſe from Reformation. And this may ſufficiently appeare by their daily obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting, and hitting vs in the teeth with our diuiſions and differences, and telling vs that our Church is ſo farre de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noide of Vnitie, that euen the reformed ſubiects of one &amp; the ſame Soueraigne cannot be brought to an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the matters and manner of Gods worſhip. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſay they, there repugnant expoſitions vpon that article or particle of faith, touching Chriſts deſcending into hell, their diſcrepant doctrines touching the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3528:49"/>eccleſiaſticall power, their generall auerſeneſſe from Prelacie, with their differences in matter of ceremonie, Sacramentall Miniſterie, and Church-ſernice. And what other thing elſe (ſay they) can it be, but a manifeſt token of a weake and ruinous Religion, to ſay no worſe, when as the profeſſours thereof,
<note place="margin">Mat. 12.25. Mark. 3.24.25 Luk. 11.17.</note> can neither agree with other Chriſtians, nor yet with themſelues according to that ſaying of our Sauiour, <hi>Euery kingdome or houſe diuided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it ſelfe ſhall be brought to deſolation?</hi> For the preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of which euill, and the remooning of which curſed ſcandall and cauſe of offence, ſeeing that Almighty God hath raiſed vp our Soueraigne, and endued him with a moſt diuine Spirit, both for pregnancie, and peaceable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, far beyond all the other Princes of the earth, yea and far beyond many profeſſed diuines;
<note place="margin">Iſay. 41, 5, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 20, 21, 25.</note> and that hee hath euen choſen our <hi>Iacob,</hi> and taken him from the <hi>endes of the earth,</hi> and <hi>called him before the chiefe thereof,</hi> (to ſpeake with the Euangelicall Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi>) to be the chiefe inſtrument of ſo glorious a worke; let vs in the conſideration thereof, both acknowledge the ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of the bleſſing that Almightie God offereth vs, by the hand of his ſeruant, (for Concord and Vnitie, eſpecially in the matters of God, is an ineſtimable bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vnto man, and a thing moſt acceptable and agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto God) and let vs likewiſe acknowledge the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable prouidence of God towards vs, diſpoſing all things as for our greateſt good, ſo for our chiefe comfort and contentment; in that he hath beene graciouſly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to picke out a King of the <hi>North,</hi> to be the Bringer and Brocher of this bleſſing vnto vs, according to that in the Prophet, ſaying, <hi>I haue raiſed vp from the North, and he ſhall come,
<note place="margin">Iſay. 41.25,</note> from the East Sunne ſhall he call vpon my name:</hi> and euen ſuch a King of the North, as hath loued vs ſo deerely as hee hath done, and who would not for all the kingdomes of the world, bring the Church of God, or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3528:49"/>his owne natiue Country, into any corrupt or diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable condition. No, I dare take it vpon my ſoule, that it is his zeale and loue towards the glorie of God, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and credite of our Country, and the happie and more perfit conſtitution of our Church, that hath ſet him a worke, about ſo bleſſed a buſineſſe, as the working of a perfit agreement and full conformitie betweene the Churches of theſe two kingdomes. For I ſuppoſe that no man is ſo far deuoide of comon ſenſe, but ſeeth ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly how that both <hi>Pietie</hi> &amp; <hi>Policie, Religion</hi> of Church and <hi>Reaſon</hi> of State, doe require that Britaines, which are the worſhippers of one true God, the ſeruants of one Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, the children of one Church, and the ſubiects of one and the ſame Soueraigne, ſhould agree in all things belonging to Gods worſhip, eſpecially. in all matters of faith, ſuch as is this preſent point of <hi>Chriſts deſcending into hell.</hi> The which though all Chriſtians doe profeſſe to beleeue according to the letter, yet we can not ſay that our verball or literall profeſſion thereof, is ſeconded with a ſolide conſent in the meaning and ſenſe. For firſt the <hi>Papists</hi> vnderſtand it of Chriſts deſcending in his ſoule to a certaine region or habitacle of hell, called <hi>Limbus Patrum</hi> to deliuer the fathers; an opinion voide of all good warrant: for we ſhall make it more then apparant In our Latine diſputation of <hi>the ſeate of ſoules,</hi> both by Scripture and Doctors, by authoritie and arguments, that the ſoules of the beleeuing people vnder the law, went not downe into any corner of hell, (for all that they can ſay to the contrary, and though <hi>Zuinglius</hi> ioyne with them herein) but to <hi>Paradiſe.</hi> And as for our <hi>Proteſtant</hi> writers, we ſee how ſome, namely, the <hi>Geneui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> expound it of Chriſts ſuffering the ſorrowes of hell in his ſoule before his death, denying his deſcending in ſoule after death into hell, to deliuer the faithfull from deſcending thither, and to conquer and binde Sathan in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3528:50"/>his owne ſtrongeſt holde, (though <hi>Mr. Caluin</hi> did not denie his foreſaid locall deſcending after death, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged it;) others expound it idly of Chriſts buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, others of his continuance in the graue vnder the power thereof for three daies; others of his tranſlating into the ſtate of the dead, and others moſt ridiculouſly haue deliuered that by the deſcending of Chriſts ſoule into hell, is to bee vnderſtood, no other thing but the aſcending thereof into heauen: all which opinions are falſe, fanaticall and friuolous; and the doctrine of the Church of England, and of ſome other reformed Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of Germanie, is only orthodoxe, and true; to wit that our Sauiours ſoule beeing ſeuered from the Bodie, which lay in the graue three daies, went downe into the very loathſome dungeon of the damned, for our ſakes (and not into any ſuperiour <hi>Limbus Patrum</hi> as <hi>Papiſts</hi> do dreame) partly to deliuer his elect children from deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thither, and partly to binde Sathan in chaines of darkeneſſe, and to triumph ouer him in his ſtrongeſt hold. The which doctrine is verified and iuſtified both by Scriptures authoritie, and Churches teſtimony, euen both by Gods word and mans. Firſt, by typicall prefigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſecondly by propheticall prediction, thirdly by pregnant hiſtoricall alluſion, fourthly by euangelicall explication and application, fiftly by apoſtolicall aſſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſixtly by all ancient Chriſtians common and Catholike confeſſion, ſeuenthly by Primitiue Doctors conſent &amp; vnanime profeſſion, eightly by the moſt part of learned Proteſtants ingenuous reception, &amp; ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ninthly by irrefragable reaſon and demonſtration, tenthly and laſtly, by the conſideration of ſuch oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, diſſentions and contradictions as the oppugners of our Sauiours locall deſcending haue fallen into about this point, and of the abſurde, vnlearned, and ridiculous, yea impious expoſitions, that the Genenians haue deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3528:50"/>of ſuch Scriptures as do moſt cleerly euince the truth of this article. The impiouſneſſe of which their doctrine ſhall appeare by our ſhowing, how in ſome things they doe iumpe with the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> enemies and oppoſers of the Meſſias his ſuffering death, and deſcending into hell, to deſtroy the author of death; and in ſome things with the ancient <hi>Hereticks Arrians</hi> and <hi>Apollinarians,</hi> which did denie our Sauiours humane reaſonable ſoule: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did expound thoſe places of Scripture, wherin men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made of the beeing of our Sauiours ſoule in hell after his death, in the ſame manner that the <hi>Geneuians,</hi> and other vpſtarts haue done of the <hi>preciſer</hi> ſort, Whereas the Doctors of the Primitiue Church, which oppugned thoſe heretickes, did expound them as the Church of England: I meane the reuerend <hi>Biſhops</hi> and other lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Doctors thereof, that haue beene ſince the daies of King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, of famous memorie, vntill this preſent time of the happie raigne of our moſt learned and religious Soueraigne King <hi>Iames</hi> the ſixt. Which be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing well conſidered, the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhall ſee, how that they haue a thouſand times better reaſon for them, to ioyne with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and with the ancient orthodoxe, and true Catholike Chriſtians, then to iumpe with the new <hi>Geneuians</hi> or any of the condemned hereticks in the expounding ſuch places of Scripture.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="part">
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <p>And firſt I ſay that there is in the Scripture,
<note place="margin">Gen. 37.24, Ionah. 1.17. &amp; 2.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7,</note> typicall prefiguration both perſonall and reall, of our Sauiours deſcending into hell; namely, <hi>Ioſephs putting into the pit without water;</hi> by his brethren mentioned in the 37. chapter of <hi>Geneſis;</hi> and <hi>Ionah</hi> his <hi>being in the belly of the Whale</hi> in the midſt of the ſea three daies &amp; three nights, as it is in the firſt and ſecond chapters of his propheſie. And therein our Sauiour himſelfe affirmeth that <hi>Ionah</hi>
                        <pb n="6" facs="tcp:3528:51"/>was a type or figure of him, and that his foreſaid conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was a figure or ſigne of his owne being after death in the <hi>hart of the earth,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 12.39.40,</note> as it is in the twelfth of <hi>S. Matthewes</hi> Goſpell, <hi>for as Ionas,</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>was three daies and three nights in the whales belly, ſo ſhall the ſonne of man be three daies and three nights, in the beart of the earth.</hi> The which cannot be vnderſtood of our Sauiours buriall, as our <hi>Geneuians</hi> would make vs beleeue; for his graue was not neere the heart of the earth, nor Chriſts body was not in the belly of the earth, but both were in the head, face, or top of the earth, and not within it, but without it, for it was a tombe hewen out of a rocke as it is in the Goſpell, and ſo thoſe words of <hi>Ionah</hi> were verified in the perſon of <hi>Ieſus</hi> really,
<note place="margin">Mat. 27.60.</note> 
                        <hi>Out of the belly of hell cried I,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Thou haſt brought vp my ſoule from the pit:</hi> for as <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nab</hi> was in the middeſt of danger, without danger, in the bottome of the ſea, without being drowned, ſo was our <hi>Redeemer Ieſus</hi> in the middeſt of danger without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and euen in the bottome of the fiery pit without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing burned, or conſumed thereby; as <hi>Ionah</hi> was in the belly of the Whale without being deſtroyed, ſo was <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> his ſoule in <hi>Leuiathans</hi> belly, which is hell, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deuoured of <hi>Leuiathan,</hi> the roaring and denouring Lyon. And as <hi>Ionah</hi> as brought vp from the bottome of the ſea; ſo was <hi>Ieſus</hi> his ſoule, brought vp from the bottome of the pit, wherein is no water, but all fire, and is ſo deepe that it is ſaid to bee without bottome. And as <hi>Ioſephs</hi> being in that pit without water, and <hi>Ionahs</hi> being in the Whales belly, and in the bottome of the ſea, were perſonall types and prefigurations of our Sauiours bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in hell, ſo haue we in the Scripture, reall types and prefigurations thereof, for as the <hi>bloody Sacrifices</hi> of the law, did ſhaddow out our Sauiours bloody ſacrificing of his bleſſed Body vpon the Croſſe for our ſins, in which doing he ſhut vp all thoſe bodily and bloody ſacrifices,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3528:51"/>with a ſolemne <hi>Conſummatum est,</hi> ſaying, it is finiſhed; ſo the <hi>burnt offerings</hi> of the law, did fore ſhew how our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſhould offer his ſoule for an <hi>holocaust</hi> or burnt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 19.30.</note> according as the Euangelical Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> had fore tolde, ſaying in the fiftie three chapter: <hi>He was taken out from priſon and from iudgement, and was cut out of the land of the liuing; for the tranſgreſſion of my people was he plagued,
<note place="margin">Iſay. 53.8, 9, 10.11.12.</note> hee made his graue with the wicked, and with the rich in his death, though he had done no wickedneſſe, and hee ſhall make his ſoule an offering for ſinne,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Hee ſhall diuide the ſpoile with the ſtrong, becauſe hee had powred out his ſoule vnto death.</hi> In which words the Prophet pointeth out our Sauiours <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, araignement, iudgement, execution,</hi> the <hi>crucifying</hi> and <hi>burying</hi> of his bodie, which was the <hi>bloody ſacrifice,</hi> that put an end vnto all bloody ſacrifices, with his <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring out of his ſoule</hi> vnto death, and making it an offering for ſinne, to wit a <hi>burnt offering.</hi> Where obſerue well, that though our Sauiour offered his very ſoule, to be a burnt offering for the expiation of the ſinnes of our ſoules, as hee had done before, his bodie for a bloody ſacrifice to expiate the ſinnes of our bodies, yet had not the flames of hel any power thereupon, in which reſpect the <hi>three children</hi> were a type of him, in their walking in the midſt of the ſeuen times hote fiery furnace,
<note place="margin">Dan. 3.21, 22, 23, 24, 25 26, 27, &amp; 6, 16, 22, 23,</note> without any hurt, as it is in the third of <hi>Daniel.</hi> Yea <hi>Daniel</hi> himſelfe being in the <hi>Lyons den,</hi> without any harme, as it is in the ſixt chapter, was a type and figure of our Sauiours con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering condition in hell; that though hee had offered the <hi>Lambe</hi> of his <hi>bleſſed body</hi> to the ſhambles of the ſhame full and accurſed croſſe to be ſlaine, and the <hi>Turtleedoue</hi> of his <hi>diuine ſoule</hi> to the hote furnace to be burnt: (ſuch bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning loue he bare vs) yet could not hell fire take any hold thereon, but was <hi>free among the dead,</hi> as it is in the eighty eight Pſalme, that is to ſay,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 88.4, 5, 6</note> free from the tormenting flames and paines of hel fire. And though he was laid in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3528:52"/>the loweſt pit in darknes and in the deepe (as the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt there ſubioyneth, immediately propheſying of Chriſts deſcending into the loweſt hell, and not into any vpper <hi>Limbus patrum</hi>) and that he was brought downe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the diuels darke dungeon, into the den of the roaring and deuouring Lyon, to haue ſeaſed vpon his ſoule, and to haue kept it captiue; yet was the diuell diſappointed, and was ſo far from detaining our Sauiours ſoule in cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie, as that he himſelfe was by him captiuated &amp; bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vp in chaines of darkenes; for the Apoſtle to the <hi>Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Epheſ 4.8.</note> teſtifieth that he <hi>led captiuitie captiue.</hi> So that he that did once lye downe, and couch as a Lyon (as the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arke <hi>Iacob</hi> in bleſſing his Son <hi>Iudah</hi> propheſied of <hi>Ieſus,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Gen. 49.6. Reuel. 5.5.</note> the <hi>Lyon</hi> of the tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi>) ſo ſoone as the denouring olde Lyon the diuell, hauing him in his denne, began to rowſe and ſtirre him vp, and to encounter with him, (for then was the King of heauens great <hi>Lyon baiting</hi>) hee left of to be <hi>Couchant,</hi> and became <hi>Rampant,</hi> and graſpling with him, gaue him the foile, and entered to the ſpoyle, according as <hi>Iacob</hi> had propheſied, ſaying, <hi>Iudah as a Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whelpe,
<note place="margin">Iſay 53.12.</note> ſhalt thou come vp from the ſpoile,</hi> and <hi>Iſay likewiſe</hi> (in the place before alleadged) ſaying, <hi>He ſhall deuide the ſpoile with the ſtrong,</hi> &amp; as the A poſtle in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> teſtifieth that he did, ſaying, <hi>and hath ſpoiled the principalities and powers,
<note place="margin">Coloſ. 2.15.</note> and hath made a ſhow of them openly.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <p>Secondly our Sauiours deſcent into hell, is in the Scripture not onely by typicall prefigurations, both per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall and reall, as hath bin now ſhewed; but alſo by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe propheticall predictions. For <hi>Dauid,</hi> who was both a type and a Prophet of Chriſt, propheſieth of it in many places,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.10. &amp; 18.5. &amp; 30.3. &amp; 88.6.</note> and namely, in the 16. Pſalme ſaying, <hi>Thou wile not leaue my ſoule in hell,</hi> and in the 18. <hi>The ſorrowes of hell hane compaſſed me,</hi> and in the 13. <hi>Lord thou haſt led forth my ſoule out of hell,</hi> and in the 88, <hi>Thou haſt laid me in the loweſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3528:52"/>pit, in darkeneſſe and in the depth:</hi> and ſo hath <hi>Zacharie</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of his deſcending into the very dungeon of the damned,
<note place="margin">Zach. 9.11, 12</note> (and not into any <hi>Limbus patrum</hi> as the Papiſts ſuppoſe) when he ſaith in his ninth chapter, propheſying there of Chriſt. <hi>I haue looſed thy priſoners out of the pit, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is no water.</hi> And if any one aske what theſe priſoners were, that were thus looſed by our Sauiours deſcending; I anſwer, that all the elect ſoules of Gods children were in effect priſoners of hell, and that they were indeed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered and looſed out of that priſon, by the vertue of Chriſts perſonall deſcending, though they were not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially and perſonally there themſelues. For God doth deliuer men from dangers and euils <hi>tam praeueniendo quam ſubueniendo,</hi> aſwell by <hi>preuention</hi> before the fall, as by <hi>ſubuention,</hi> when they haue fallen. The Romane Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors indeed, expound this place of Chriſts deſcending into a certaine blacke border of hell, which they call <hi>Limbus patrum,</hi> to deliuer the Patriarkes ſoules from thence: for as for the pit or priſon of the damned, from thence they hold there is no redemption. But truly they are deceiued in their opinion, for the pit or priſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto our Sauiour did deſcend, is called the <hi>lowest pit</hi> in the Scripture, and ſo muſt needes bee the priſon of the damned; <hi>Thou haſt laid me in the loweſt pit in darkenes,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 88.6.</note> and in the deepe,</hi> (ſaith the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi>) prophecying of his Sons deſcending into the Ioweſt hell. And the Prophet <hi>Zacharie</hi> calling it <hi>a pit without water,</hi> intimateth that it is <hi>a pit full of fire,</hi> and conſequently no <hi>Limbus patrum,</hi> nor blacke border of hell fire, but hell fire it ſelfe. And in our Latine diſputation of the <hi>Seate of Soules,</hi> as we ſhall proue both by Scriptures authoritie, and Fathers teſtimonie; that the ſoules of the faithfull Iewes before Chriſt, were in no ſubterraneall pit or priſon, but in <hi>Paradiſe:</hi> ſo ſhall we diſpute another noble queſtion, whether or no, the ſoules of the vertuous Gentiles were deliuered from the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3528:53"/>loweſt pit,
<note place="margin">Zach 9.11, 12 Pſal. 107.10, 11, 12, 13, 14.</note> at our Sauiours deſcending, and whether this place of <hi>Zacharie</hi> of our Sauiours looſing of thoſe priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of <hi>hope</hi> out of the pit, wherin is no water, and that of the <hi>Pſalmist,</hi> of the breaking of the bondes of ſuch as did dwell in darkenes, and ſit in the ſhaddow of death: and that of the Prophet <hi>Iſay,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iſay 61.1</note> prophecying of our Sauiours preaching libertie to the captiues, and to them that are bound,
<note place="margin">Luke 418. 1. Pet. 3.18, 19 20. &amp; 4.5, 6.</note> the opening of the priſon, as it is likewiſe in the Goſpell of <hi>S. Luke,</hi> and thoſe words of <hi>S. Peter,</hi> when hee ſaith that our Sauiour being dead in his body, but quick or liuing in his Spirit (for ſo readeth the Syrian text) went by the ſame Spirit and preached to the Spirits in priſon, which were in times paſt diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And finally, thoſe other words of the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>for vnto this purpoſe was the Goſpell preached alſo vnto the dead, that they might bee condemned according to men in the fleſh, but might liue accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to God in the ſpirit:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iſay 53.12. Mat. 12.29. Epheſ. 4.8. Coloſ. 2.15.</note> whether I ſay theſe places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and others the like wherein mention is made of our Sauiours ſpoyling of hell and Sathan, and of his leading captiuitie captiue, may perhaps be probably vnderſtood of his powerfull and mercifull deliuering from hell, ſome of the ſoules of the vertuous Gentiles, as of their Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, Law giuers, Gouernours, Kings, Queenes, and other priuate perſons renowned for their wiſedome, prudence, fortitude, temperance, bounty, chaſtity, iuſtice, mercy, and generally for their ciuill carriage, and morall conuerſation, ſuch as were <hi>Hermes Triſmegiſtus, Zoroaſter, Socrates, Plato, Aristotle, Pythagoras, Homer, Phocilides, The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ognis, Epictetus, Cicero,</hi> and ſuch as were <hi>Hercules, Theſeus, Cyrus, Solon, Lycurgus, Ariſtides, Cimon, Timotheus, Epamis nondas, Tarina, Camilla, Nicaula, Pauthaea, Penelope, Artemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> and others the like. For my owne part I doe profeſſe ſuch loue to thoſe vertuous wights, for their vertues ſake, that I had rather condemne twenty ſuch opinions, as that of the ſubterraneall <hi>Limbus patrum,</hi> then to damne
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3528:53"/>eternally the ſoule of one <hi>Socrates,</hi> or of one <hi>Cyrus,</hi> let alone of a <hi>Salomon:</hi> concerning whom, we ſhall likewiſe diſpute the queſtion, whether his ſoule went to <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> or to the hell of the damned; and ſhall proove the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his ſoule, againſt Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and other his Romiſh damners, by many authorities &amp; arguments.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="part">
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <p>Thirdly our Sauiours deſcending into hell,
<note place="margin">Iob 38.17.</note> is in the Scripture by pregnant hiſtoricall alluſion. In the booke of <hi>Iob</hi> the greeke interpreters allude thereunto moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently, for the Engliſh of the Septuagints reading of the 17. verſe of the 38. chapter is thus, <hi>Were the gates of hell opened vnto thee for feare, and did the Porters of hell at the ſight of thee, ſhrinke for feare?</hi> and in the tranſlation accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the hebrew, it is thus, <hi>Haue the gates of death beene opened vnto thee, or haſt thou ſeene the gates of the ſhaddow of death?</hi> and in the Goſpell,
<note place="margin">Mat. 12.24, 25 26, 29, 28, 29.</note> our Sauiour himſelfe alludeth diſertly thereunto, when he ſaith in the Goſpell, <hi>Elſe how can a man enter into a strong mans holde, except he firſt bind the ſtrong man, and then ſpoile his houſe:</hi> where note, how that immediately before, hee ſpake of his <hi>casting out of diuels,</hi> and his ouercomming of them, which argueth that Chriſt was to conquer the diuell; for all his ſtrength in his owne houſe, and both to foyle him, and ſpoile him in his owne ſtrongeſt hold.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="part">
                     <head>IIII.</head>
                     <p>Fourthly, our Sauiours locall deſcending into hell is in the Scripture, by Euangelicall explication or applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for <hi>S. Matthew</hi> in the ſame twelfth chapter,
<note place="margin">Mat. 12.39, 40</note> where he entreateth of our Sauiours caſting out of diuels, and of his entering into the ſtrong mans houſe to binde him and ſpoile him, teſtifieth, that <hi>Ionah</hi> in his being three daies and three nights in the Whales belly, was a type or figure of our Sauiours being three daies &amp; three nights in the heart of the earth; which cannot be vnderſtood of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3528:54"/>the place of his Body, but of the ſeate of his ſoule, as wee haue ſhowed before.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="part">
                     <head>V.</head>
                     <p>Fifthly,
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.2. Act. 2.26.27, 30.31.</note> Chriſts locall deſcent into hell, is in Scripture by Apoſtolicall aſſeueration. For firſt, <hi>S. Peter</hi> the prime Apoſtle in the ſecond of the <hi>Acts,</hi> mentioning both the parts of our Sauiours humanitie, to wit his ſoule and fleſh, ſhoweth how God had preordained that neither ſhould his <hi>ſoule</hi> be ſubiect to <hi>detention</hi> or <hi>deſtruction</hi> in <hi>hell,</hi> nor yet his <hi>body</hi> to <hi>detention</hi> or <hi>corruption</hi> in the <hi>graue:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.8, 9,</note> and he expoundeth the Prophet <hi>Dauids</hi> words, in the ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Pſalm: <hi>Thou will not leaue my ſoule in hell, neither wilt thou ſuffer thine holy one to ſee corruption,</hi> of the reſurrection of Chriſt; that his ſoule ſhould not be left in <hi>hell,</hi> neither his <hi>fleſh</hi> ſhould ſee <hi>corruption.</hi> For as the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could not be atchiued without a combination of Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and his ſoule;
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.18.19 &amp;, 4.6,</note> ſo it behoued the ſoule, aſwell to riſe in a manner out of hell, where it lay downe like the <hi>Lyon couchant</hi> of the tribe of Iudah; as the body to riſe out of the graue or tombe, where it was laide. The ſame Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in his firſt Epiſtle teacheth the ſame doctrine, in two ſeuerall places; the one where he ſaith that <hi>Chriſt beeing put to death, concerning the fleſh, but quickned in the Spirit</hi> (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the greeke text, or <hi>being quicke and liuing in the Spirit,</hi> according to the Syrian) <hi>went by the ſame Spirit, and preached vnto the Spirits in priſon;</hi> the other, where he ſaith that <hi>the Goſpell was preached vnto the dead, to the end that they might liue according to God in the Spirit.</hi> And as <hi>S. Peter,</hi> the prime Apoſtle (for ſo the Scripture calleth him) in the three places now alleadged affirmeth Chriſts deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into hell in his ſoule,
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.2, Mark. 3.16.</note> ſo <hi>S. Paul</hi> in as many places doth the like. The firſt place is in the tenth to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes</hi> where he affirmeth both his <hi>aſcending</hi> into <hi>heauen,</hi> and his <hi>deſcending</hi> into the <hi>deepe</hi> or <hi>bottomleſſe pit</hi> which is <hi>hell.
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.6.7.</note> Say not in thine heart</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>who ſhall aſcend into
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3528:54"/>heauen that is to bring Christ from aboue? or who ſhall deſcend into the (a byſſus) deepe or bottomles pit, that is to bring Chriſt from the dead?</hi> where note that the Greeke word <hi>abyſſus,</hi> which our Engliſh haue tranſlated, <hi>the deepe</hi> is neuer ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for the <hi>graue,</hi> but for <hi>hell</hi> and the <hi>bottomleſſe pit,</hi> it is often taken, as in <hi>Luke</hi> the eight,
<note place="margin">Luk. 8.31. Reuela. 9.1.2.11 &amp; 11.7. &amp; 20.1.3.7.10.14.15.</note> in the ninth of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation</hi> thriſe, in the eleuenth once, and in the twentieth twiſe; where it is likewiſe called <hi>Sathans priſon,</hi> and the <hi>lake</hi> of <hi>fire and brimstone.</hi> The ſecond place where <hi>S. Paul</hi> teacheth Chriſts deſcent into hell, is the fourth to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> thus, <hi>Now in that hee aſcended, what is it, but that bee alſo deſcended first into the lowest parts of the earth?</hi> where the lower or loweſt parts of the earth can ſignifie no other thing but that,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.8.9, 10.</note> which he calleth the <hi>deepe</hi> or <hi>bottomleſſe pit</hi> in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romanes;</hi> for as he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth an expreſſe oppoſition betweene <hi>aſcending</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending,</hi> which are contrary motions, ſo doth he between the two oppoſite places, to wit, the <hi>highest part of heauen,</hi> and <hi>the loweſt part</hi> of <hi>the earth.</hi> The third and the laſt place is the ſecond to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> where ſpeaking of our Sauiours Mediatourſhip, hee vſeth theſe words a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other,
<note place="margin">Coloſ. 2.15.</note> 
                        <hi>And hath ſpoiled the principalities and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and hath made a ſhow of them openly, and hath triumpbed ouer them in himſelfe;</hi> for ſo readeth the <hi>Syrian</hi> text, and the <hi>Greeke</hi> text likewiſe in moſt part of bookes, together with the <hi>Latine</hi> of <hi>Saint Hierome,</hi> of <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> of <hi>Dela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> of <hi>Castalso,</hi> of <hi>Stephanus,</hi> of the <hi>Tigurins</hi> or <hi>Leo Iuda,</hi> and of <hi>Arrias Montanus;</hi> where as the <hi>Geneuian</hi> tranſlation of <hi>Beza</hi> attributeth this triumph to Chriſt on the Croſſe, contrary to the common tranſlation, and expoſition of tenne of the Doctors of the Primitiue Church, as ſhall bee ſhewed other where. And truely Chriſt did triumph ouer the <hi>Principalities</hi> and <hi>powers</hi> when as hee did <hi>binde Sathan,</hi> and by his preſence terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3528:55"/>the whole infernall forces, the which thing hee did not on the <hi>croſſe,</hi> for there hee ſuffered himſelfe to bee foyled and ouercome; but hee did it in Sathans owne houſe, and ſtrongeſt holde. So that his triumph began in <hi>hell,</hi> in reſpect of his ſoules diuine vanquiſhing of the diuell, like as it began in the <hi>graue,</hi> in reſpect of his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies powerfull riſing from death to life; and it was fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed both in ſoule and body, when hee gloriouſly aſcended into heauen. So that they are mightily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued which doe thinke our Sauiour triumphed ouer Sathan and hell vpon the croſſe; for atriumph doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies follow vpon a perfit victorie, and doth not goe before it, much leſſe before the conflict, as our <hi>Geneuians</hi> would ridiculouſly haue it. Thus we ſee twentie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe paſſages of Scripture for our Sauiours <hi>deſcending into hell</hi> after death, (for ſo many haue we alleadged from the firſt to the laſt,) where as the <hi>Geneuians</hi> can not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſo much as one text bearing, that Chriſts ſoule went not to hell: only out of two texts in the Goſpell, they draw an argument againſt his deſcending; the one in that he ſaid to the penitent thiefe, <hi>To day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ioh. 23.43.46,</note> the other in that he ſaid a dying; <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into thy hands I commend my Spirit:</hi> but neither doth the one nor the other argument conclude punctually. Firſt the argument doth not follow; Chriſts Spirit was in his fathers hands, <hi>Ergo</hi> it was not in hell; for Gods hands is in hell aſwell as in heauen, according to that of the Pſalmiſt, ſpeaking of our Sauiour, belike by way of propheſie; <hi>If I aſcend into heauen thou art there, if I lie downe in hell thou art there;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 139, 8,</note> yea the hand of the Father was with his Sonne in hell, in a fatherly manner fortify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, in his conflict againſt the furie of the whole infernall forces, like as his hand and Spirit, was with him to raiſe him vp from the dead,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.11.</note> as the Apoſtle teacheth.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3528:55"/>Neither doth the other argument follow, Chriſt was that day or night in Paradiſe; <hi>Ergo</hi> he did not deſcend into hell; for to ſpeake nothing of his beeing in <hi>Paradiſe</hi> in his Godhead, I ſay that in his very ſoule hee might without all repugnancie; haue gone firſt to <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> which was the place due vnto him, beeing conſidered as a moſt perfit and iuſt man, free from ſinne; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to <hi>hell,</hi> which was the place due to all ſinners, and euen to him, in ſo farre as hee became the pledge, and ſurety for ſinners, a ſufferer for them both of death and diſhonour, and a deliuerer of them from ſinne and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, from Gods hatred and hell. But Godwilling in our Latine diſputation of the <hi>Seate of ſoules,</hi> we ſhall han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle the point of our Sauiours going to <hi>Paradiſe</hi> more accurately; where wee ſhall likewiſe diſpute the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the place, ſituation, exiſtence, and vſe of the terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriall Paradiſe, and ſhall by certaine probable argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments make it apparant; how that it was created in the heart of the world vpwards, like as hell was created in the heart of the earth downwards. And there ſhall wee refute an errour of the learned Spaniſh Ieſuite <hi>Pererius</hi> and of our <hi>Geneuians</hi> touching the <hi>non-existence</hi> of <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe;</hi> like as in our worke called <hi>Dies Domini,</hi> which deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth the doctrine of <hi>Hebrewes, Greekes</hi> and <hi>Latines, Theologians, Philoſophers</hi> and <hi>Historians;</hi> touching the worlds <hi>beginning, lasting</hi> and <hi>ending,</hi> wee doe refute the ſame Ieſuites, and ſome of our owne Proteſtants com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon errour touching the worlds beginning, in the moneth of <hi>September;</hi> and that by diuers new argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, beſides the authorities of <hi>Theologians, Aſtrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and <hi>Philoſophers.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="part">
                     <head>VI.</head>
                     <p>Sixtly, as the holy Scripture doth auouch our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours deſcending into hell, in his ſoule after death, in the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3528:56"/>foreſaid fiue reſpects; ſo doth the Catholicke or vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Churches common Confeſſion of faith auerre it; as may appeare by our common <hi>Creed,</hi> commonly called the <hi>Creede of the Apostles,</hi> wherein after the mention of our Sauiours buriall, is immediately ſubioyned his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending into hell, like as after his riſing from the dead, he is ſaid to haue aſcended into heauen. Neither could this point haue beene expreſſed in plainer words then it is, for plainneſſe was fitteſt for the expreſſion of the common faith of Chriſtians. The motion of <hi>aſcending</hi> and the place thereof <hi>heauen,</hi> are both of them taken literally and properly; and therefore their contraries, <hi>deſcending</hi> and <hi>hell</hi> muſt likewiſe be properly taken, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out running to a figure. And we may as well denie that in the Creed, <hi>aſcending</hi> ſignifieth <hi>a local</hi> motion vpwards, and that <hi>heauen</hi> ſignifieth the ſeate of God, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle of the bleſſed Spirits, and with all, ſay that by our Sauiours aſcending into heauen, is ſignified no other thing elſe, but his enioying of ſome ſpirituall ſolace and heauenly ioy; as to denie that his <hi>deſcending</hi> is a locall motion downewards, and that <hi>hell</hi> is the ſeate of Sathan and of his ſlaues, and as to ſay with the <hi>Genenians,</hi> that by Chriſts deſcending into hell, is nothing elſe meant, but his feeling of ſome ſpirituall ſorrowes or hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh horror. If <hi>hell</hi> muſt be taken by a figure in the Creed, then <hi>heauen</hi> in the ſame Creede ſhall bee but another fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure; and ſo ſhould our Creed be but a Creed of figures, and our faith, a faith of figures. And to ſay that there are many <hi>Creedes</hi> and <hi>confeſſions</hi> of faith (wherein there is no mention made of Chriſts deſcending into hell) it doth not argue that the authors and makers of thoſe confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, did not beleeue this point: for other clauſes are likewiſe often wanting, as namely, in the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creede, theſe words, <hi>Borne of the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>he was buried, hee ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3528:56"/>on the right hand of God, I beleeue the Catholike Church, the communion of Saints, the reſurrestion of the body, and the life euerlaſting,</hi> aſwell as thoſe wordes, <hi>he deſcended into hell.</hi> And yet the Fathers (no doubt) were aſwell perſwaded of theſe things they left out, as they were of thoſe things they put in. Againe, it is ſufficient that in none of the Creedes and confeſſions that euer were publiſhed aboue threeſcore, the deſcending of Chriſt into hell is denied: for yee ſhall not reade in one of them all, ſuch a clauſe, I beleeue that Chriſts ſoule beeing ſeuered from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, went not downe into hell, but aſcended vp into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. But not onely is it not denied ſo much as in one Creede of many: but alſo it is affirmed expreſſely, in ſome Creedes, as namely, in that of the Apoſtles, and in that of <hi>Saint Athanaſius,</hi> and implicitly it is in all the Creedes and confeſſions that euer were made, for more then fifteene hundreth yeares toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for it is implied in the word <hi>ſuffered,</hi> and in the word <hi>died.</hi> For in Chriſt the Mediatours death, are theſe three parts; the ſeparation of the ſoule from the body, the collocation of the body being dead in the graue, as being the bodies chamber of death, and the migration of the ſeuered ſoule into the blacke houſe of death, which is hell; where it behooued the ſoules of all men to bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, except the Sonne of God, by deſcending into that dungeon, had deliuered and exempted all beleeuing ſoules from deſcending.
<note place="margin">Pſal, 107.14, 16. Iob 38.17.</note> 
                        <hi>For he it was that brake thoſe gates of braſſe, and braſt the barres of yron aſunder,</hi> and <hi>to him the gates of hell and of death were opened for feare.</hi> It is certaine that Chriſts ſoule went to ſome place after death, and in the Creede wee finde no place mentioned, but <hi>hell,</hi> or <hi>heauen:</hi> now in it there is mention made, of his deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into hell after death, but there is no mention made of his ſoules aſcending, vntill at what time being riſen, after forty daies aboade with his Diſciples, hee aſcended
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3528:57"/>viſibly, in his whole humane nature. And that he aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not into heauen, before that time, wee may gather it out of his owne wordes to <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ioh. 20.17.</note> ſaying, <hi>Touch me not, for I am not yet aſcended to my Father;</hi> &amp; there is not ſo much as one letter in the whole Scripture, that ſheweth that our Sauiour was to aſcend twice to heauen, or that his ſoule was to deſcend twice from heauen: the which double <hi>deſcenſion</hi> and <hi>aſcenſion,</hi> are inferred neceſſarily of the <hi>Geneuian</hi> doctrine. And as the word <hi>died,</hi> in the Creede, doth imply our Sauiours deſcending in ſoule, to the houſe of death, though not to dye, (for Chriſts ſoule could not dye) but to ouercome death, and to deſtroy the author of death, the diuell, (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) ſo doth the word of <hi>ſuffering</hi> the like.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.55. Heb. 2.14.</note> For Chriſt ſuffered the greateſt humiliation and deiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that could be, for mans cauſe, and therefore it behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his ſoule to be humbled vnto hell, and without this hee had not beene ſubiected to the higheſt degree of humiliation in his ſoule, as hee was to bee, anſwerably to the humiliation of his body, which was in the higheſt degree, euen vnto the death of the croſſe: like as for that cauſe God exalted him, both in body and ſoule, in the higheſt degree,
<note place="margin">Philip. 2.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> (as the Apoſtle teacheth.) So that we ſee that Chriſts locall deſcending into hell, is denied in no Creede, but expreſſed in ſome, and implied in all.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="part">
                     <head>VII.</head>
                     <p>Seauenthly, the locall deſcent of Chriſts ſoule into hell, is confirmed by the common conſent, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant profeſſion of the Doctors of the primitiue Church, in their Sermons, Homilies, Commentaries, Expoſitions and Gloſſes, vpon the places of Scripture aboue allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, about twenty in number; and vpon the Creede, eſpecially this article thereof, as ſhall bee ſhewed more
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3528:57"/>particularly in our Latine worke by the expreſſe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of theſe three and forty Fathers, Doctours, and writers, <hi>Hebrewes, Greekes</hi> and <hi>Latines, Thaddaeus, Ignatius, Iuſtinus Martyr, Irenaeus, Tertullianus, Origines, Cyprianus, Arnobius, Lactantius, Euſebius, Athanaſius, Hilarius, Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Baſilius, Gregorius Nazianzenus, Ambroſius, Hieroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Ruffinus, Epiphanius, Chryſostomus, Augustinus, Caſſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Caeſarius, Philippus Preſbyter, Cyrillus, Primaſius, Euthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius, Theodoretus, Leo, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>igilius, Fulgentius, Caſſiodorus, Beda, Titus Boſtrenſis, Didimus, Ioannes Damaſcenus, Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phylactus, Oecumenius, Bernardus, Prudentius, Petrus Chryſologus, Rabbi Hoccadoſh, Rab. Simeon:</hi> whereunto ſhal be added, ſome ſixe or ſeauen Councels, as of <hi>Epheſus, Chalcedon, Alexandria, Conſtantinople, Toledo, Arles</hi> and others. So that if the Fathers of the Church haue any weight or authority amongſt the <hi>Geneuians,</hi> they ſhall ſoone ſee themſelues in a manifeſt errour which God grant they may as ſoone amend.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="part">
                     <head>VIII.</head>
                     <p>Eightly, Chriſts locall deſcent into hell after death, is confirmed by the ingenuous reception and ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the moſt part of learned proteſtant writers, as we ſhall ſhow in our Latine worke, by the teſtimonies of ſome thirty; to wit, <hi>Luther, Calum, Peter Martyr, Bullm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Pomeran, Pellican, Chytraeus, Aepinus, Bucer, Illyricus, Selneccer, Loſſius, Hemingius, Aretius, Rulandus, Marlerat, Vrbanus Rhegius, Lauater, Vitus Theodorus, Mylius, Muſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Mollerus, Westhemerus, Hereſbachius, Felinus,</hi> our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimen <hi>Alexander Aleſius,</hi> or <hi>Aeleis, Biſhop Latimer,</hi> and <hi>Robert Samuel Martyrs, Deane Nowell, Master Foxe,</hi> with the reuerend Biſhops and learned Doctors of Fngland, in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, and afterwards, to this preſent day of the happy raigne of King <hi>Iames</hi> the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3528:58"/>ſixt, together with the whole <hi>Lutheran</hi> Proteſtants in <hi>Denmarke, Norway, Sweden, Poland, Boheme, Hungary,</hi> and other parts of <hi>Germany,</hi> with ſome of thoſe, whome they call <hi>Caluinians;</hi> as namely, that moſt learned and iudicious <hi>Italian</hi> diuine, <hi>Hieronymus Zanchius.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="part">
                     <head>IX.</head>
                     <p>Ninethly, the doctrine of Chriſts locall deſcending into hell, is prooued by irrefragable reaſons: for firſt the doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth illuſtrate, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and magnifie, the <hi>loue</hi> of God towards mankinde, where as the doctrine of <hi>Geneua</hi> obſcureth, ecclypſeth, and diminiſheth it, exceeding much. For it is an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of great loue, that the Sonne of God would daigne to deſcend from his throne, and ſeate of maieſtie, into this earth of vilitie and miſery, which is his foote-ſtoole: but it is an argument of farre greater loue, that for our ſakes, he would yet deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d lower, euen ſo low, as to take upon him the ſhape of a ſeruant, and in that ſhape to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſo ſhamefull a death, as that vpon the croſſe; but it argueth the higheſt degree of loue that could bee, in that for our ſakes hee would deſcend ſo low as into the loweſt hell, the vile and loathſome dungeon of the damned, to the end that we ſhould not deſcend thither, nor be damned. Secondly, the very Ground, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Geneuians</hi> doe found their doctrine of Chriſts ſuffering the pangs of hell, doth prooue pregnantly this very point, which they denie of Chriſts deſcending in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell in his ſoule. The ground is this, It behooued the Mediatour of ſinfull mankinde to ſuffer what was due to ſinfull mankinde, whereupon it followeth neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, that he ſuffered the higheſt degree of humiliation, to wit to be humbled vnto hell in his ſoule, as his Bodie was humbled vnto the ſhame of the croſſe, &amp; the graue,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3528:58"/>for ſinfull mankinde had deſerued this deiection, and ſhould haue beene humbled ſo farre for his ſinfull and proud rebelling againſt God, if our Redeemer had not humbled himſelfe in our ſtead and for our ſakes to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt, and deliuer vs from this ignominie. Yea their very doctrine is contradictory to it ſelfe, for they hold that Chriſt was to ſuffer the torments of hell in his ſoule, and yet they will not haue him goe to hell; which two aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions cannot well ſtand together; for though that the ſoule may feele the horror, or apprehend the feare &amp; ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of hell, out of hel,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 18.4, 5, Mat. 26.37.38 39, 42, 46, Mar. 14.33 34, 35, 36, &amp; 15, 34,</note> &amp; that our Sauiours ſoule did ſo in the garden and vpon the croſſe, according as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Dauid</hi> had propheſied, of him ſaying, <hi>the ſorrowes of death and of hell, haue compaſſed me about,</hi> and as our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſaid of himſelfe, <hi>My ſoule is very heauy euen vnto the death,</hi> and as the Euangeliſts doe teſtifie of him, that hee <hi>began to waxe ſorrowfull: and grieuouſly troubled, to bee afraid and in great beauineſſe,</hi> and euen in ſuch an agonie vpon the apprehenſion of the fearefull cup of Gods wrath, that he ſweat drops of blood, and afterwards cried out, that he felt himſelfe in a manner forſaken of his Father, for our ſakes for a while; all which <hi>ſoule-ſuffering,</hi> the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> calleth by the name of the <hi>ſorrowes of death,</hi> and <hi>Dauid,</hi> the <hi>ſorrowes of hell;</hi> though I ſay that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ſuffered in his ſoule for our ſakes, theſe horrours and terrors of hell, in the very garden and on the croſſe, yet he could not ſuffer the pangs, paines, or torments of hell, without being in hell, no more then one can enioy, the ioyes of heauen out of heauen. But the truth is, that Chriſts ſoule was no more capable of thoſe tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of hell, then it was of deſperation or damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And though he deſcended into hell, yet it was not to ſuffer torment, but only the higheſt degree of humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and debaſement, and with all to begin his higheſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3528:59"/>exaltation in the ſame very place, where his loweſt hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation did end. Thirdly, the doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth magnifie and ſet out the Maieſtie of Chriſts victorie and conqueſt, where as the doctrine of <hi>Geneua</hi> doth obſcure and diminiſh the Maieſtie thereof. For who knoweth not, but that it is a greater glorie for a King or Captaine to vanquiſh and conquer his enemie in his owne kingdome, and to make his enemies owne pallace his priſon, then to doe it elſewhere? Wherefore ſeeing our Sauiour atchieued the greateſt, and the moſt glorious conqueſt that euer was, and triumphed the moſt magnificently;
<note place="margin">Mat. 12.29.</note> we muſt needs beleeue, that he did it in <hi>Sathans</hi> the <hi>ſtrong ones</hi> owne houſe, caſtle and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as it is in the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> and as the Church of <hi>England</hi> together with the <hi>Primitiue</hi> doth beleeue and teach; and not that he did it out of hell, or on the croſſe, as they iargon at <hi>Geneua.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="part">
                     <head>X.</head>
                     <p>Tenthly and laſtly, the veritie of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> doctrine touching our Sauiours <hi>deſcending into hell,</hi> may appeare by the contradictions, oppoſitions, and diſſentions, and fanaticall expoſitions of ſuch as haue oppugned it, or diſſented from it; ſome expounding thoſe words, <hi>hee deſcended into hell,</hi> of our Sauiours bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, others of his detention in the graue, and the moſt part of his ſuffering the paines and torments of hell, in the garden, and on the croſſe; ſome haue expounded it of his tranſlating into the ſtate of the dead, and ſome haue beene ſo fanaticall, as to ſay, that his deſcending in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell, meaneth no other matter but the aſcending of his ſoule into heauen after death. And as ſome of them haue moſt vnlearnedly and ridiculouſly vnderſtood <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> by <hi>hell</hi> in the <hi>Creed,</hi> and <hi>aſcending</hi> by <hi>deſcending,</hi> which is all one with the taking water for fire, or God for the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3528:59"/>diuell, ſo haue they as vnlearnedly and ridiculouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued diuers other places of Scripture. In the ſixteene Pſalme, by the Hebrew word NEPHESH,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 16, 10. Act. 2.27.</note> and in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of the <hi>Actes</hi> by the Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> (both which doe ſignifie the <hi>ſoule</hi>) they vnderſtand the <hi>body,</hi> which is the contrary part, and the other halfe of man, a thing that no learning diuine or humane will ſuffer. And though a man perhaps might excuſe ſuch a ſimple or ſingle <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noramus</hi> as this; yet how can he excuſe it, when it is dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled? for thoſe Geneuians will haue the word <hi>ſoule</hi> to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the <hi>body</hi> and a <hi>dead body,</hi> which in all learning di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, or humane, ſignifieth alwaies a <hi>liuing ſubſtance;</hi> and either the principall part, which is the <hi>ſoule,</hi> and that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, or elſe the whole perſon, figuratiuely. And as theſe admirable <hi>Metamorphoſers</hi> of <hi>Geneua,</hi> turne in one place <hi>hell</hi> into <hi>heauen</hi> and <hi>deſcending</hi> into <hi>aſcending,</hi> euen blacke into white, and in another place, Chriſts <hi>liuing ſoule</hi> they turne into his <hi>dead Body;</hi> ſo doe they turne <hi>hell</hi> into the <hi>graue,</hi> for the Hebrew word SHEOL; and the Greeke word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, which doe properly and principally ſignifie hell (as the learned in theſe languages doe well know, and as we ſhall ſhow particularly otherwhere, by allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the teſtimonies of the beſt <hi>Hebricians</hi> and <hi>Grecians</hi>) but eſpecially when the word of <hi>Soule</hi> is thereunto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, as it is in the ſixteenth Pſalme, and in the ſecond of the <hi>Actes,</hi> they do tranſlate <hi>Graue</hi> and not <hi>Hell;</hi> which is not only the ſecondary and improper ſignification of thoſe two words, but alſo quite repugnant to thoſe texts of Scripture, wherein mention is made of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſts <hi>ſoule:</hi> For though it be true that the ſaid two words doe ſometimes ſignifie the <hi>graue,</hi> yet it is but ſecondarily and improperly, and when the word of <hi>Body</hi> or <hi>fleſh</hi> is ioyned thereunto, but neuer when the word of <hi>Soule,</hi> is annexed, as it is in thoſe two places of Scripture,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3528:60"/>and becauſe they ſee the abſurditie that ſhould inſue of ſaying that Chriſts <hi>ſoule</hi> ſhould be <hi>buried</hi> in a <hi>graue,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for preuenting one abſurditie, they runne into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for as they turne <hi>hell</hi> into <hi>graue,</hi> ſo doe they Chriſts <hi>liuing ſoule</hi> into his <hi>dead body,</hi> the moſt blockiſh and ſtoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh abuſing of Scripture, that euer was heard tell off: yea more, the moſt impious, for in ſo doing they ioyne with the profeſſed enemies of Chriſt both <hi>Iewes, Arrian,</hi> and <hi>Apollinarian Heretickes.</hi> For firſt ſuch <hi>Geneuian</hi> expoſitors ioyne with the Iewes, who (as <hi>Aepinus</hi> the Proteſtant Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendent of <hi>Hamburge,</hi> writeth vpon the ſixteenth Pſalme) to ouerthrow the certainty of our faith, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſts deſcenſion into hell and his reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, did by the word <hi>ſoule,</hi> vnderſtand <hi>life,</hi> (though it bee not ſo bad, nor ſo farre fetcht as <hi>Bezas dead bodie</hi>) and by the word <hi>hell,</hi> they vnderſtand <hi>graue,</hi> as the <hi>Geneuians doe.</hi> And next they ioyne and iumpe with the old <hi>Arrian</hi> and <hi>Apollinarian Heretickes,</hi> which denied our Sauiours true humane ſoule, and therefore vnderſtood thoſe Scriptures as the <hi>Geneuians</hi> doe, and not as the ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxe fathers vnderſtood them, that out of thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, refuted their fooleries, as <hi>Athanaſius, Theodoretus, Epiphanius, Cyprianus, Auguſtinus, Fulgentius, Hieronymus, Ambroſius, Philippus Preſbyter, Ruffinus, Caſſiodorus, Euthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius, Beda, Petrus Chryſologus,</hi> and others whom the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth follow: all which ſhall be (God-willing) particularly prooued in our Latine worke. And the <hi>Geneuians</hi> doe ioyne with the ſame <hi>Apollinarian</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes in vnderſtanding by the <hi>Spirit of Christ</hi> in the third chapter of the firſt Epiſtle of <hi>Saint Peter,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.18.19.</note> his <hi>Diuinitie</hi> or <hi>God-head,</hi> and not his <hi>humane Spirit;</hi> though the other halfe of his humanitie, to wit his <hi>fleſh</hi> bee there menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned with it: like as in the ſame text, they turne <hi>Christs perſon,</hi> into <hi>Noahs,</hi> and <hi>Christs preaching in Spirit</hi> vnto
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3528:60"/>dead mens ſpirits after his paſſion, into <hi>Noahs preaching</hi> in body vnto liuing men, many hundreth yeares before the paſſion, and incarnation. Where note how that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all learning diuine and humane, they expound the word <hi>Spirit</hi> of a <hi>liuing man,</hi> and not of the <hi>ſoule</hi> of <hi>one deceaſed.</hi> And in the ſame abſurd manner, they turne Chriſts wraſtling vpon the croſſe, into triumphing, and make him to ſing his owne triumph before his full and abſolute victorie. Finally, as in expounding the Goſpel they turne the <hi>heart or middle of the earth</hi> into a <hi>Tombe,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Math. 12.40. &amp; 27.60.</note> which was not ſo much as within the foreskin (if I may ſo ſpeake) of the earth, ſo in expounding the Epiſtle, they turne the <hi>lower</hi> or <hi>lowest parts</hi> of the <hi>earth,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Eph. 4.8.9.</note> whereinto our Sauiours <hi>ſoule</hi> deſcended, into the <hi>vpmost parts</hi> or <hi>ſurface</hi> of the <hi>earth,</hi> where in body hee conuerſed, when hee was vpon earth. So that they turning thus vpſide downe, both in <hi>Goſpell</hi> and <hi>Epistle</hi> as they doe, we haue as little cauſe to iumpe or ioyne with <hi>Geneua</hi> in this point, as wee haue to runne with <hi>Rome</hi> for the finding out of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticall <hi>Limbus Patrum.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And thus I haue by a ten-fold probation, cleered the truth of the doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> touching our Sauiours deſcending into hell, and haue with all diſpelled the cloudes and miſtes, both of <hi>Romane</hi> and <hi>Geneuian</hi> opinions. For as it is moſt certaine that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours <hi>ſoule</hi> did after death <hi>deſcend into hell,</hi> which our <hi>Geneuians</hi> doe moſt vnlearnedly and ignorantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, ſo is it as certaine, that hee deſcended into the very <hi>loweſt hell,</hi> and not to any vpper region or ſubter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raneall <hi>Limbus Patrum,</hi> to deliuer the Fathers, as the <hi>Romanes</hi> doe imagine; for wee ſhall prooue both by Scriptures and Fathers, and many pregnant reaſons, that they went preſently after death into <hi>Paradiſe;</hi> and that there is no other <hi>Limbus</hi> or lodge for <hi>Fathers</hi> or <hi>Infants</hi>
                        <pb n="26" facs="tcp:3528:61"/>either, but it, nor no other <hi>Purgatorie</hi> after this life, but the fire of Gods Spirit in the ſame <hi>Paradiſe.</hi> And in the ſame worke, we ſhall likewiſe diſpute the queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our Sauiour went firſt into <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> before he went downe to <hi>hell;</hi> and whether the ſoules of the Patriarkes, went in his companie, to bee witneſſes of his victorie in hell? wherefore I would wiſh with all my heart, that for the furthering of the peace of the Church, both <hi>Romanes</hi> and <hi>Geneuians, Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Puritanes</hi> would ſubſcribe vnto the doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in this point, and borrow from her the golde of this orthodoxall doctrine, as they would ſhe ſhould borrow from them ſome thing that they can ſhow as good warrant for, as the Church of <hi>England</hi> can doe for this. And let them both, doe as they pleaſe, one thing I dare vndertake to prooue by publike diſputation, in any <hi>Colledge</hi> in Chriſtendome, and ſhall ſhall doe it, (God willing) before a few yeares goe about, in King <hi>Iames his Colledge;</hi> that the <hi>Romanes</hi> cannot ſhow ſo much Scripture, and ſo many teſtimonies of Fathers, nor ſo many pregnant reaſons, for any two poſitions or opinions that they differ in from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as wee ſhall ſhow for this one, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Chriſts deſcending into the dungeon of the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to deliuer vs from deſcending. And againe, that all the <hi>Geneuians</hi> in Chriſtendome (though they ſhould ioyne their whole wits together) ſhall neuer bee able to ſhow ſo many authorities, teſtimonies, reaſons and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, fetcht from Scriptures, Fathers, and Doctors, for the probation of the whole opinions, that they differ in from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as we ſhall ſhow for the probation of this one poſition, onely againſt them. The which being well conſidered, I hope my Countrey men will not be ſo fond of euery <hi>Gloſſe,</hi> that goeth forth from <hi>Geneua,</hi> as to take all to bee vndoubtedly true; and that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3528:61"/>hereafter they will not applaude promiſcuouſly all their pedling and paltrie opinions; ſeeing ſome of them are ſo abſurde and ridiculous, and other ſome ſo vnlearned and impious as we haue now ſhowed and can ſhow; how that they commit the like incongruities, abſurdities, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and impieties in their popular paritie, amongſt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, in their lay-preſbytery, in their exploding of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacie, in their denying of the Chriſtian Princes Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall facultie and ſacred immunitie from ſecular coer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and eccleſiaſticall cenſure: and to be briefe, in their ſuppreſſing and oppoſing of ſuch religious ceremonies, and ſolemnities as haue beene vſed of the ancient Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians through out the whole world, in the moſt flouriſhing and proſpering ages of the Church. The which errours and defects, I pray the God of <hi>Vnitie</hi> and <hi>Veritie</hi> to giue them grace ſpeedily to amend. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>IN the Epiſtle, page 6. line 19. for enough read enough, In the Contents numb. 9. for honorable in ſome copies read honorably, &amp; num. 17. after ſont, read for, in ſtead of or, in ſome copies. In the firſt Treat. p. 10. lin. 17 in ſome copies put out whenſoeuer, p. 35. lin. 9. for fabulous read friuolous, pag. 56. lin. 17. for hee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſeers, read the ouerſeers, pag. 40. lin 11. for Churchmen being, read Church-members, pag. 45. lin 23. for the other, read their other, pag. 51. lin. 29. betweene reſembled and ours, read, by, in ſome copies, p. 71 l. 10. after had ſeene, adde him. Tract. 2. pag. 10. line 31. in ſome copies read Tarina for Taxina, and Artemiſia for Arteniſia, pag. 16. lin. 6. for the death, read the dead.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
